<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sermons preached before his Maiestie 1. The bridegromes banquet. 2. The triumph of constancie. 3. The banishment of dogges. By Francis Rollenson, Batcheler of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Rollenson, Francis, ca. 1565-1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112081</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847340</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10994)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1582:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sermons preached before his Maiestie 1. The bridegromes banquet. 2. The triumph of constancie. 3. The banishment of dogges. By Francis Rollenson, Batcheler of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Rollenson, Francis, ca. 1565-1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Snodham for Robert Iackson, and are to be solde at his shop in Fleet-streete, ouer against the Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This edition bound with STC 20775: Rawlinson, John. The Romish Judas (London, 1611).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12373:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SERMONS PREACHED BEFORE HIS MAIESTIE.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Bridegromes Banquet.</item>
               <item>2. The Triumph of Conſtancie.</item>
               <item>3. The Baniſhment of Dogges.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> FRANCIS ROLLENSON, Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheler of Diuinitie.</p>
            <q>Omnia pro veritate nihil pro tempore.</q>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed by <hi>T. Snodham</hi> for <hi>Roger Iackſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his Shop in Fleet-ſtreete, ouer againſt the Conduit. 1611.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12373:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12373:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOVRABLE, THOMAS, LORD ELLES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MERE, LORD CHAVNCELOVR OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>Printing</hi> of Sermons, if both be done for the glory of God, and the good of his Church, are like the <hi>Two ſiluer Trumpets</hi> of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> excellent <hi>inſtruments</hi> to call men to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but if in <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Preaching, Diuines</hi> ſeeke their owne glory, and thirſt after popular applauſe, then they be but <hi>Trumpets</hi> of <hi>Rams-hornes,</hi> whoſe ſound leuels not the walles of <hi>Iericho,</hi> but <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> with the ground: I dare not auowe that theſe my <hi>labours, Preached</hi> and <hi>Printed,</hi> be <hi>Trumpets</hi> of <hi>Siluer,</hi> for then ſhould I paralele the <hi>proud Pharaſie</hi> in iuſtifying my ſelfe; neither will I acknowledge them to be of <hi>horne,</hi> for ſo ſhould I wilfully brand mine owne acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with <hi>ſhame,</hi> and carie <hi>Caines marke</hi> euer vpon me; let the <hi>cenſure</hi> be referred to him, who is the ſearcher of the reines, and whoſe <hi>all-ſeeing</hi> eie hath ouer-lookt the ayme and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my heart, vpon which this <hi>Nil vltrà</hi> is grauen; <hi>Deo &amp; Eccleſiae; For God and his Church; This God</hi> by <hi>One ſtarre</hi> conducted the <hi>wiſe men</hi> from the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> when they came to worſhip the <hi>ſtarre</hi> of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and offer their <hi>Gold, Incenſe,</hi> and <hi>Myrrhe</hi> to our <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet Chriſt:</hi> but he hath directed me to your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> preſence by <hi>Two ſtarres fixt</hi> by his gracious goodneſſe in the <hi>firmament</hi> of your noble <hi>heart, Vertue</hi> and <hi>Honour;</hi> there to make an oblation, not of <hi>Myrrhe, Incenſe,</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> but of <hi>one ſlender talent,</hi> and <hi>Two poore Mites, Three worthleſſe Sermons,</hi> preached as
<pb facs="tcp:12373:3"/>
once our <hi>Sauiour</hi> did in a <hi>Ship royall,</hi> but written out for the preſſe, as <hi>Ionah</hi> praied in the <hi>Whales belly;</hi> I know that the <hi>Magi</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> doe daily caſt out of their aboundance, <hi>Rich</hi> offerings into your <hi>Treaſurie,</hi> to whoſe writings I may iuſtly apply that of the Poet, and call them
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
The <hi>Garden</hi> and <hi>Table</hi> of <hi>Alcinous,</hi> ſo well fraught and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht they be with <hi>Knowledge, Iudgement, Wit,</hi> and <hi>Elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie;</hi> but the poore <hi>Widow</hi> must do as ſhe may, not as ſhe would: They that cannot bring <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Pearles</hi> to the building of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi> muſt preſent a <hi>Rams-skin</hi> and <hi>Goates-haire; All</hi> the <hi>Patriarches</hi> wore not <hi>Party-coloured Coates;</hi> and all the <hi>Seruants</hi> had not <hi>fiue Talents;</hi> They then that haue but one <hi>Talent</hi> in their <hi>Purſe,</hi> and one <hi>Coate</hi> to their backe, muſt meaſure their actions by their ability, euen as <hi>God himſelfe</hi> by <hi>ballance</hi> doth diſtribute his <hi>Graces; Yet many things in themſelues of no moment, are highly priced, becauſe of their dedication to the Temples</hi> (ſaith <hi>Plinie.</hi>) The <hi>two Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles being</hi> but of <hi>ſtone,</hi> were reuerently regarded, becauſe in them the <hi>finger</hi> of God writ the <hi>Law;</hi> nay, the very <hi>Beſomes</hi> and <hi>Aſh-pannes</hi> of the <hi>Temple</hi> were much eſteemed, becauſe they were inſtruments in the Lords houſe; ſo I hope theſe my <hi>Endeuours</hi> ſhall purchaſe the better <hi>Reſpect</hi> in the opinion of the <hi>Readers,</hi> for that they were, and are <hi>dedicated</hi> to the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout eare</hi> of his <hi>Sacred Maieſtie, the inuincible defender of the faith,</hi> and to the <hi>Iudicious eie</hi> of your <hi>honourable ſelfe,</hi> being a bountifull <hi>Nurcing-father</hi> of our <hi>Church;</hi> which if it ſhall pleaſe you out of your <hi>True worth</hi> fauourably to <hi>Accept, Patroniſe and Protect,</hi> I will boldly promiſe to ſecond them with a better <hi>Preſent.</hi> And thus as moſt bounden in duty, readie in ſeruice, and daily in <hi>Praier,</hi> vnto Almighty God, to be your <hi>Honours guide</hi> and <hi>fortreſſe</hi> both in this life and the life to come, I reſt moſt humble at your <hi>Honors</hi> commaund,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>FRANCIS ROLLENSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12373:3"/>
            <head>THE BRIDEGROMES BANQVET.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>CANT. CANT. 5. CAP. 1. VER.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I am come into my garden, my ſiſter, my ſpouſe: I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered my myrrhe with my ſpice: I ate mine honie-combe with mine honie, I dranke my wine with my milke: eate, O my friends, drinke, and make you me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, O welbeloued.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Alomon,</hi> the Author of this Text, was a <hi>King,</hi> a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> a <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> and therefore he may fitly be compared to the <hi>Cherubim,</hi> which<note n="a" place="margin">Ezech. 10.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ezechiel</hi> ſaw in his viſion, for as they had the face of a <hi>Lyon, a Man, an Oxe, and an Eagle,</hi> euen ſo <hi>Salomon,</hi> firſt, he was a royall <hi>Lyon</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> ſitting vpon an<note n="b" place="margin">1. Reg. 10.18.19.</note> Iuorie throne, ſupported by twelue artificiall <hi>Lyons,</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blems of <hi>Royaltie</hi> and <hi>Courage,</hi> which two like<note n="c" place="margin">Ex. 28.30.</note> 
               <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> in <hi>Aarons breaſt-plate,</hi> ought to be engrauen in euery Princes heart. Secondly, hee had the face of a <hi>Man,</hi> witneſſe his <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> of morall Philoſophie, the <hi>Prouerbes;</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hieron. in Prouerb.</note> by which he inſtructs men of greene and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ripe yeares in vertue and godlineſſe: Thirdly, he was an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uſled Oxe,</hi> labouring in <hi>Gods</hi> harueſt, treading out the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12373:4"/>
Corne; and trampling the Chaffe vnder his feete, for being <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> in his Sermons, he doth vnmaske that <hi>Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh ſtrumpet, Vanitie,</hi> raiſing the whole architecture of his ſpeech vpon this foundation.<note n="e" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Vanitie of Van ties, all is Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi> Laſtly, he had the <hi>face and the wings of an Eagle.</hi> For what Prophet euer mounted to ſo high a pitch, as this <hi>ſweet Singer of Iſrael,</hi> in his <hi>Song</hi> of <hi>Songs,</hi> that volume of my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries; called by Saint<note n="f" place="margin">Orig. Proam. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>Origen, Epithalamion,</hi> becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines the wooing and the wedding of the <hi>Sonne of God</hi> and his <hi>Spouſe</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> whoſe <hi>Loue</hi> was from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but their <hi>Mariage</hi> in the fulneſſe of time: Euery line in this ſong is the language of loue, and euery word relli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth <hi>heauenly paſſion;</hi> but this <hi>Verſe</hi> which I haue choſen for my Text, doth eſpecially deſcribe. Firſt, the <hi>Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of their <hi>Mariage;</hi> ſecondly, the <hi>Wedding feaſt;</hi> third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>entertainment of the gueſts:</hi> which three are the maine branches, growing out of this <hi>ſtemme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am come, &amp;c.]</hi> In theſe words is the <hi>Conſummation</hi> of Chriſtes marriage, by which is vnderſtood the <hi>Vnion</hi> of the two <hi>Natures, Diuine</hi> and <hi>Humane,</hi> the <hi>Contract</hi> whereof was Gods Promiſe of <hi>Chriſtes</hi> comming, and the <hi>Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> his <hi>Natiuitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In an <hi>Eſpouſall</hi> or <hi>Contract,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Cod. lib. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>4.</hi> leg. <hi>7.</hi> Gordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. Cod. lib. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>4.</hi> leg. <hi>12.</hi> Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian.</note> the <hi>Conſent</hi> both of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Parties is neceſſarily required: So heere: firſt God the Father is content, that his Sonne ſhall come into the world, and be made like vnto vs in all things, ſinne on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted; it was his owne decree: for all mankinde in<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
               <hi>Adam</hi> being corrupt,<note n="i" place="margin">Con. Mogunt. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quia primorum hominum pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum in omnes homines tranſiuit &amp; ſecum ſuam poenam traxit;</hi> becauſe the ſinne of the firſt <hi>Man</hi> was deriued by propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto all men, and drew the puniſhment with it. God looked vpon the poſteritie of <hi>Adam</hi> with two eies, the firſt being like a <hi>Doues eie</hi> waſht with milke, the ſecond like a <hi>flame of fire, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> according to whoſe ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall viewes he made two <hi>Decrees,</hi> the one of Election, the other of <hi>Reprobation;</hi> which two reſemble the two ſtreames
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12373:4"/>
that iſſue from the throne of God,<note n="k" place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> the one being <hi>all fire,</hi> the other<note n="l" place="margin">Reuel. 22.1.</note> 
               <hi>Water of life.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4. Rom. 9.16.</note> 
               <hi>Election is the decree of God, whereby on his owne free will, he hath ordained certaine men to ſaluation, without any fore-ſight of their good workes, to the praiſe and glory of his grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 9.21.</note>
               <hi>Reprobation is Gods decree, whereby according to the moſt free, and iuſt purpoſe of his will, he hath determined to reiect certaine men, vnto eternall destruction, to the praiſe of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice.</hi> Theſe decrees are built vpon two ſeuerall <hi>foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 11.32.</note> 
               <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne is the ground of <hi>Reprobation:</hi> of <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> is the <hi>foundation,</hi> called of his Father from all eternitie, to performe the office of a <hi>Mediatour,</hi> that in him all thoſe which ſhould be ſaued might be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen; as then he was predeſtinate to be the <hi>Reconciliation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and mankinde, ſo likewiſe there was preordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a <hi>Mariage,</hi> or vniting of the two <hi>Natures, Diuine</hi> and <hi>Humane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the Bridegrome he is willing, for he confeſſeth as much by the mouth of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> ſaying:<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> 
               <hi>In the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume of the booke it is written, that I ſhould fulfill thy will, O my God, I am content to do it, thy law is within my heart.</hi> Euer ſince the making of this <hi>decree, God the Sonne</hi> and his ſpouſe the <hi>Church,</hi> like a paire of <hi>Turtle Doues,</hi> haue loued and wooed each other, as appeareth by thoſe ſweet paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with which this <hi>Song</hi> is full fraught, and yet from the time that he was firſt promiſed, till the <hi>fulneſſe</hi> of time when he was conceiued,<note n="r" place="margin">Cant. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>He euer ſtoode behinde the wall, looking through the windowes, and appearing through the grates:</hi> Theſe <hi>windowes</hi> were the Sacraments, <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Paſchal Lambe;</hi> theſe <hi>Grates</hi> the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> of <hi>Aaron,</hi> all of them principall <hi>Types</hi> and <hi>figures</hi> of the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Cant. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Thus for a long time the Church, vnder his ſhadow onely had delight, and his fruite was ſweet vnto her mouth.</hi> But at length ſhe growes loue-ſicke, and cries,<note n="t" place="margin">Cant. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Stay me with flagons, and comfort me with Apples: for I am ſicke of Loue.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Cant. 1.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12373:5"/>
mouth, for his loue is better then wine.</hi> As if ſhe ſhould haue ſaid, how long will he appeare vnto me onely in <hi>types</hi> and <hi>figures?</hi> when ſhall mine eies ſee the <hi>Saluation</hi> of God, which he hath prepared to be a light to the Gentiles, and the glory of the people <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Cant. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let my beloued come into his garden, and eate his pleaſant fruite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let the word</hi> be made <hi>fleſh</hi> and dwell amongſt vs. Our Sauiour therefore<note n="y" place="margin">Cant. 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe heart from the beginning ſhe had wounded with one of her eies, and a chaine of her necke.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would not ſuffer her to pine away, and languiſh with expectation, anſweres her ſaying, <hi>I am come into my garden my ſiſter, my ſpouſe.</hi> As if he ſhould haue ſaid: the <hi>Contract of Marriage,</hi> which by my Fathers decree was from eternitie, is now conſummate by my Natiuitie: In which <hi>Conſummation</hi> three Circumſtances may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, the publiſhing of the Banes</hi> by the Angell <hi>Gabriel,</hi> thus ſpeaking to the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Luc. 1.28.</note> 
               <hi>Haile thou that art freely beloued, the Lord is with thee, bleſſed art thou among women;</hi> and hauing thus ſaluted her, he tells her, that ſhe ſhall conceiue and beare in her wombe a Sonne, and call his name <hi>Ieſus:</hi> But how ſhall this be, ſaith <hi>Mary,</hi> ſeeing I know no man? this ſhe ſpeakes, ſaith <hi>Theophilact,</hi> not doubting of the euent, but enquiring the manner: The <hi>Angell</hi> anſweres her:<note n="a" place="margin">Luc. 1.35.</note> 
               <hi>The holy Ghoſt ſhall come vpon thee, and the vertue of the moſt high ſhall ouerſhadow thee. Vide hic</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cyprian) cooperantem ſimplicem trinitatem, Quae eſt virtus altiſſimi? niſi Chriſtus, virtus &amp; ſapientia patris, &amp;c. See here the whole Trinitie are at worke together; what is this vertue? but Chriſt the vertue and wiſedome of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; of whom is this Vertue? but of the moſt high:</hi> Although then the Sonne alone was conceiued and incarnate, yet both the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> were preſent to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his conception, which is the ſecond circumſtance and the manner of the <hi>Mariage.</hi> He was not conceiued of the <hi>ſeede</hi> of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> as <hi>Ebion</hi> dreamed, but by the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12373:5"/>
holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> of the ſeede of <hi>Mary</hi> alone, as may appeare by theſe teſtimonies.<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeede of the woman ſhall bruiſe the Serpents head. Feare not</hi> Ioſeph<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>to take</hi> Mary <hi>for thy wife, for that which is conceiued in her, is of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> A ſtrange conception: here is <hi>Aarons</hi> rod cut from the ſtem bloſſoming, and a <hi>Virgin</hi> without a man conceiuing. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was conceiued by the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> there is an argument of his <hi>Diuinitie;</hi> and borne of a <hi>virgin,</hi> there is a proofe of his <hi>humanitie;</hi> ſo he is neither <hi>God</hi> only, hauing an aierie body, as <hi>Apelles</hi> the hereticke thought, nor meere man as the<note n="d" place="margin">Epipha. lib. <hi>2.</hi> tom. <hi>2.</hi> haereſ. <hi>69.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Arrians</hi> ſurmiſed, but <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man vnited,</hi> one <hi>Chriſt,</hi> conceiued by the holy Ghoſt, and borne of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin Mary,</hi> which <hi>natiuitie</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the third circumſtance, and the very forme of the <hi>Marriage,</hi> betwixt him and his <hi>Spouſe</hi> the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> out of the <hi>Virgins</hi> wombe came like a <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome out of his chamber full of glory, and yet in all humility;</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Philip. 2.6.7.</note> 
               <hi>For being in the forme of God, and thinking it no roberie to be equall with God, he made himſelfe of no reputation, tooke on him the forme of a ſeruant, and was made like vnto men, and was found in ſhape as a man.</hi> This his lowlineſſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth further in the very choiſe of his <hi>Mother,</hi> who was a poore Virgin, betrothed vnto a Carpenter. He was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued when ſhe was a <hi>Virgin</hi> betrothed, but hee was borne when ſhe was a <hi>Virgin</hi> married, becauſe hee would honour both <hi>Single life,</hi> and the marriage bed. A <hi>Virgin</hi> ſhe was to fulfill the <hi>Prophecie</hi> of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſaying:<note n="f" place="margin">Iſai. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>A virgin ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and beare a Sonne. Ante partum, in partu, poſt partum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgo,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Ierome: Before, at the very inſtant and after her deliuerie a Virgin,</hi> not paſt foureteene yeares of age (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> writ) <hi>Flos ipſe,</hi> in the flower of her youth ſhe bore him, who is the<note n="g" place="margin">Cant. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Roſe of the field, and the Lilly of the vallies. A Virgin, but yet very poore: God euer lookes on the inſide,</hi> but <hi>the world</hi> on the out-ſide of a man. Let one be as fooliſh as <hi>Nabal,</hi> and haue eares as long as <hi>Midas,</hi> yet if he haue mount <hi>Carmel</hi> for his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:12373:6"/>
and as it is in the Prouerbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſwim vp to the eares in riuers of gold, the world will honor him, and bowe the knee vnto him, as the idolatrous Iewes did to the golden Calfe of <hi>Horeb:</hi> but Gods eie ſearcheth the hart and the reines; he regardeth the poore and the needie, for euer they be moſt religious, moſt vertuous: he choſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> from the ſheepe-folde, following the Ewes great with young to raigne ouer <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and hee makes choiſe of one of the daughters of <hi>Dauid,</hi> to be the Mother of his Sonne, though ſhe was ſo poore, that the place of her <hi>Deliuerie</hi> was a Stable, and her firſt begotten ſonnes Cradle a Cratch. Why ſhould any man be proud of his wealth then, ſeeing both ſhe whom all generations call bleſſed, and hee that is Lord of heauen and earth, were both very poore? why ſhould any man like <hi>Ephraim, be fed with winde,</hi> and puft vp with his <hi>diſcent,</hi> his alliance, his worme-eaten <hi>antiquitie,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the Sonne of a poore <hi>Virgin,</hi> betrothed and married to a <hi>Carpenter;</hi> and yet both hee and ſhee were of the <hi>royall</hi> line of <hi>Dauid?</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 132.</note> 
               <hi>To whom the Lord had ſworne in truth, and he did not ſhrinke from it,</hi> ſaying, <hi>of the fruite of thy body will I ſet vpon thy throane.</hi> Thus was the marriage conſummate betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Church</hi> in the <hi>Virgins wombe:</hi> this wombe was the milkie way, by which he came into his garden, Oh bleſſed was that <hi>wombe</hi> of her that bore him, and thoſe paps that gaue him ſucke!</p>
            <p>The ſecond generall branch, is the <hi>Mariage feaſt of Chriſt,</hi> in which, firſt let vs ſee the <hi>Banquetting place:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly ſuruay his <hi>Banquet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> makes his <hi>Banquet</hi> in a <hi>Garden,</hi> but which of his <hi>Gardens</hi> is it? for <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath three. The firſt is <hi>Hortus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiae,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Hortus gratiae,</hi> the third <hi>Hortus gloriae.</hi> His firſt <hi>Garden</hi> is the kingdome of <hi>Power,</hi> and this is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie large and ſpacious, ſtretching it ſelfe from the higheſt heauens, to the nethermoſt parts of the earth: for his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is infinite; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Damaſcen, He can doe all things that he will.</hi> His ſecond <hi>Garden,</hi> is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12373:6"/>
of <hi>Grace</hi> in this world, whereby hee raigneth in the faithfull by the holy Ghoſt, of this <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaketh, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;<note n="i" place="margin">Dan. 7.13.14.</note> 
               <hi>As I beheld in viſions by night, behold one like the Sonne of man came in the cloudes of heauen, and approached vnto the ancient of dayes, and they brought him before him, and he gaue him dominion, and honour, and a kingdome, that all people, nations, and languages ſhould ſerue him: his domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is an euerlaſting dominion, which ſhall neuer be taken away, and his Kingdome ſhall neuer be deſtroyed.</hi> His third garden is the kingdome of <hi>Glory,</hi> which is alreadie in part begun, becauſe he is aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth at the right hand of his Father, but ſhall be complete at the generall reſurrection, when the <hi>Elect</hi> being gathered together, ſhall raigne continually with <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Neither the <hi>firſt nor this laſt Garden,</hi> is the place where the <hi>Banquet</hi> is kept, but onely the ſecond: in this the <hi>Bridegrome gathers his Mirrhe with his ſpice, in this he eates his hony-combe with this honie,</hi> in this he <hi>drinkes his wine and milke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The kingdome of <hi>Grace</hi> is here called a <hi>Garden,</hi> and this <hi>Garden</hi> is either <hi>ſhut vp</hi> or not <hi>ſhut vp.</hi> The <hi>Garden not ſhut vp</hi> is the <hi>Church</hi> viſible, in which growes as well the fruitleſſe <hi>Cedar,</hi> as the fat <hi>Oliue;</hi> the bitter <hi>Colloquintida,</hi> as the ſweet <hi>figge-tree;</hi> the prickie Bramble as the cheerefull <hi>Vine,</hi> for the Church viſible, is like vnto<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, in which were ſtabled, beaſts, both <hi>polluted</hi> and <hi>impolluted,</hi> it is like<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 37.3.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Coate, made of diuers colours; for in it are men of diuers diſpoſitions; a <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> and a <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus;</hi> a <hi>Iudas</hi> the brother of <hi>Iames,</hi> and a <hi>Iudas Iſhcariot;</hi> a <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and a <hi>Saphira;</hi> good and euill; <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates:</hi> here onely is the difference, the <hi>Wicked are weedes,</hi> and grow without priuiledge, they liue in the outward aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> yet are they not the true members of <hi>Chriſtes body.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>They went out of vs, but they were not of vs,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Dec. P. <hi>2.</hi> cauſ. <hi>24.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ad eccleſiam Dei non pertinent illi, qui in eius vnitate corporaliter mixti, per peſſimam vitam ſeperantur: They belong not to the Church, which being corporally mixed
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12373:7"/>
in the ſocietie thereof, are ſeperated by an euill life.</hi> In this <hi>Garden</hi> be diuers <hi>beds of Spices;</hi> ſo ſaies the <hi>Spouſe,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Cant. 6.1.</note> 
               <hi>My welbeloued is gone downe into his Garden, to the beds of ſpices, to feede in the Gardens, and to gather Lillies:</hi> Theſe <hi>Beds</hi> of ſpices be particular Churches; as for inſtance ours in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> it is a <hi>Bed of Spices, a Societie of the Elect:</hi> for here we haue,<note n="p" place="margin">Cant. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>Spikenard, Saffron, Calamus,</hi> and <hi>Cinamon, with all the trees of Incenſe, Mirrhe and Aloes, with all the chiefe ſpices.</hi> We haue true Preachers, whoſe tongues neuer cleaue to the roofe of their mouth. <hi>Siluer trumpets,</hi> and golden bels, that ring out peales of Gods praiſes in <hi>Sion,</hi> and ſound out his wonders in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> We haue zealous profeſſors, in colour like white Lillies for their pure faith, and as ſweet as <hi>Incenſe</hi> for their charity, which that they may ſtill more and more encreaſe;<note n="q" place="margin">Cant. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſe O North, and come O South, and blow on our bed, that the ſpices thereof may flowe out:</hi> But alas, how can they? for the <hi>Enemie</hi> hath ſowne three <hi>poiſonous weedes</hi> in our <hi>Bed, Atheiſme, Papiſme,</hi> and <hi>Simoniſme,</hi> which like Tares choke the wheate, and hinder the growth of our better <hi>plants.</hi> The firſt and the worſt is <hi>Atheiſme;</hi> for are there not amongſt vs whole kennels of<note n="r" place="margin">Apo. 22.15.</note> 
               <hi>Dogs,</hi> whoſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads are braſſe and iron; impudent, audacious, blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and <hi>conſcience</hi>-cauterized <hi>fooles,</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 104.</note> which in their hearts ſay there is no God? holding<note n="t" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> the Goſpel of <hi>his</hi> kingdome to be meere fooliſhneſſe; and Scriptures fables, coyned and ſtamped for currant, onely to awe the world; were there not ſuch monſters, why is the profeſſion of Religion growne policie? and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in name become <hi>Mache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uillians</hi> in practiſe; as mutable as <hi>Proteus,</hi> as changeable as the <hi>Camelion,</hi> temporizing their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> to day a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, to morrow a Proteſtant, the next day any thing for aduantage, a <hi>Turke,</hi> a <hi>Iew,</hi> an <hi>Infidell.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Tuſh,</hi> if there be a God, <hi>he hath forgotten, he hides away his face and will neuer ſee.</hi> Thus ſpoke their Tutor <hi>Auerrhoes,</hi> denying Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and prouidence herevpon earth; Againſt the Iewes the Queene of <hi>Saba,</hi> and againſt theſe <hi>Atheists</hi> the verie
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12373:7"/>
               <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall riſe in iudgement: for they hauing nothing to direct them but the glimmering light of Nature, would acknowledge both a God, and his diuine prouidence.<note n="x" place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>1.</hi> de ani.</note> 
               <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> commends <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> becauſe he taught that there was an <hi>immixt and moſt ſimple vnderſtanding, which knew all things,</hi> &amp; this is God. The <hi>Platoniſts</hi> cal'd him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is the <hi>Beholder</hi> of all things whatſouer, &amp; <hi>Orpheus</hi> confeſſed that there was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>One begotten of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by whom all things were made, and this is God:</hi> and yet we haue fooles amongſt vs. which in their harts ſay there is no God. The ſecond weed is <hi>Papiſme,</hi> a weed that ouerſpreads our <hi>Bed,</hi> for euil weeds euer grow apace: it is like <hi>Lotos</hi> which <hi>Homer</hi> ſpeaks of, he that taſts it is bewitched with the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof, like the companions of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes:</hi> for doth not Papiſtrie diſpenſe with all licentiouſneſſe? and hath not the whore of <hi>Babilon</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Reuel. 17.4.</note> 
               <hi>a golden Cup</hi> in her hand, with which ſhe makes drunken the inhabitants of the earth? and yet this weed muſt grow ſtill; who plucks it vp? it is cropt ſometimes I confeſſe, and the leaues are cut off, but as long as the root is quick, both <hi>leaues and branches</hi> will encreaſe and multiply like the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Hydra.</hi> Vpon this weed breeds, <hi>the Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hopper, the Canker-worme, the Caterpillar, and the Palmer-worme,</hi> which <hi>make our Vines waſt and pill the barke off our figge-trees;</hi> I meane thoſe<note n="z" place="margin">Reuel. 9 7.8.</note> 
               <hi>Locuſtes</hi> (ſpoken of by <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Diuine) comming out of the ſmoake of the bottomleſſe pit, whoſe forme is like vnto horſes prepared for battell; and on their heads as it were ermines of gold, their faces like vnto the faces of men, their haire like the haire of women, &amp; their teeth like Lyons.</hi> In a word, the whole <hi>Swarme of Ieſuites and Seminaries, Romiſh Alaſtores, Euill ſpirits,</hi> which muſt not be driuen away with <hi>Dauids Harpe,</hi> but <hi>Elijahs</hi> ſword: Theſe make profeſſion of Religion, yet are their actions died in blood; they vow voluntarie <hi>pouertie,</hi> yet ayme at crownes, and are euer med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in matters of State; they ſeeme <hi>humane,</hi> and as tender-hearted as <hi>women,</hi> (Oh, there is their <hi>aequiuocation</hi>) but their <hi>Teeth</hi> are <hi>Lyon-like;</hi> their <hi>diſſeignes</hi> violent; their ſtratagems
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12373:8"/>
cruell. Theſe <hi>Iebuſites</hi> liue amongſt vs, and are prickes in our ſides; they haue euer yet beene <hi>forgers of I reaſon,</hi> and euen now no doubt they are hammering ſome miſchiefe; and yet muſt they ſtill gall vs; I, what remedie can be found? Plucke downe the Cages of theſe vncleane birdes, and giue the law liberty to puniſh their harbourers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect of perſons, then ſee if theſe <hi>Locuſtes</hi> doe not quickly vaniſh away like ſmoake, and flie to their ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie dungeon. The third weede is <hi>Simoniſme,</hi> the roote whereof was firſt ſet by <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 18.18.</note> who offered <hi>Peter</hi> mony for the gift of the holy Ghoſt: and at this day it is watered by <hi>Bels</hi> Prieſts, and <hi>Baals</hi> Prophets, ſuch as make their <hi>profeſſion</hi> a meere <hi>Mechanicke Trade,</hi> or <hi>Occupation;</hi> and their <hi>Miniſterie</hi> a <hi>Ladder onely,</hi> to climbe to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Mercenaries</hi> no true <hi>Paſtors; Creepers</hi> in through the window, no true <hi>Preachers:</hi> you ſhall know them by their workes, for they ſeeke their owne, and not <hi>Chriſtes;</hi> they feede vpon the fat of the flocke, and cloath them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the wooll, but ſuffer the ſheepe to ſtarue for want of foode: They be like vnto the<note n="b" place="margin">Strab. Geog. lib. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aſtomi,</hi> of whom <hi>Strabo</hi> writes, which people haue no mouthes, but onely a certaine hole in ſteede thereof, whereby they receaue the ſweet ſent of flowers, which is their ſuſtenance: So theſe <hi>Simoniſtes</hi> haue no mouthes to ſhew forth the praiſe of God, but onely a tongue-leſſe hole, by which they ſucke vp the ſweetneſſe of Church-liuings, purchaſed by briberie at Steeple-faire. Well, it was not ſo from the beginning; for <hi>Aarons</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 28.34.</note> 
               <hi>robe</hi> round about the skirtes was hung with golden bels and <hi>Pomgranates,</hi> the firſt betokening <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 2.7.</note> the ſecond <hi>Hoſpitalitie,</hi> to ſignifie, that the <hi>Prieſts</hi> lips ſhould preſerue <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and his mouth ſhould be a <hi>ſiluer</hi> bell, to call the people to Gods tabernacle: likewiſe his dore muſt be euer open to the harbourleſſe, and his bread continually caſt vpon the waters. <hi>Sed motos praeſtat componere fluctus.</hi> I muſt ſpeake as<note n="e" place="margin">Pli. lib. 35.8.</note> 
               <hi>Timantes</hi> painted <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyphemus,</hi> onely ſhewing you the thumb of theſe Monſters,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12373:8"/>
thereby you may proportionate their whole bodies: and as<note n="f" place="margin">Aug. Ep. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of the <hi>Tares, Totus mundus in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligno poſitus eſt propter Zizania quae ſunt per totum mundum:</hi> So may I ſay of theſe three weedes, <hi>Atheiſme, Papiſme,</hi> and <hi>Simoniſme,</hi> by them our bed of <hi>Spices</hi> is almoſt ſpoiled.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Garden ſhut vp,</hi> is the Church <hi>Inuiſible,</hi> of this <hi>Salomon</hi> thus ſpeaketh,<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>My ſiſter, my ſpouſe is as a Garden encloſed, as a Spring ſhut vp, and a Fountaine ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp.</hi> Which inuiſible <hi>Church,</hi> is the <hi>Catholicke Societie</hi> of the faithfull, elected and choſen to eternall life, and it is ſaid to be <hi>inuiſible,</hi> becauſe it is onely of the <hi>Elect,</hi> who are not <hi>Viſible to men,</hi> but onely to God:<note n="h" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>for he alone knoweth who are his.</hi> The Papiſts vtterly diſtaſte this <hi>diſtinction of viſible</hi> and <hi>inuiſible,</hi> and yet they themſelues confirme it, ſaying:<note n="i" place="margin">Inter relig. Caeſ. cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia quatenus conſtat membris talibus, quae ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum charitatem viuunt, Sanctorum eſt tantum, &amp; eate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nùs ſpiritualis &amp; inuiſibilis. The Church as it conſiſteth of ſuch members which liue after the rule of Charitie, is onely of the Saints, and is ſo farre forth ſpirituall and inuiſible:</hi> To this alſo their owne decrees giue conſent:<note n="k" place="margin">Dec. P. <hi>3.</hi> diſt. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Societas cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; membrorum Chriſti eſt Eccleſia, in praedeſtinatis. The ſocietie of the body and the members of Chriſt, is the Church, conſiſting of the praedeſtinate.</hi> This <hi>Garden</hi> then is like the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> which was kept by a <hi>Cherub,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> ſhaking a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſword; This <hi>Cherub</hi> is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who ſuffereth no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing to enter into it, neither whatſoeuer worketh abomination or lies, but they which are written in the book of life. In the olde <hi>Paradiſe</hi> grew two principall trees,<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 3.22.</note> the tree of <hi>Life,</hi> and<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 2 17.</note> the tree of <hi>Knowledge,</hi> the like are in this garden: <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 3.15.</note> 
               <hi>whoſoeuer beleeueth in Chriſt, ſhall not periſh, but haue eternall life;</hi> here is the tree of <hi>Life,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> 
               <hi>And this is life eternall, that they know thee to be the onely very God, and whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> Here is the tree of <hi>Knowledge.</hi> And as <hi>Eden</hi> was watered with<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 2.</note> foure <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, Piſhon, Gihon, Hiddekel,</hi> and <hi>Perath,</hi> ſo hath this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12373:9"/>
               <hi>Garden,</hi> the <hi>Church inuiſible,</hi> foure waters of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, namely: <hi>Election, Vocation, Iuſtification,</hi> and <hi>Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>for whom God hath praedeſtinate to be made like the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his Sonne, them alſo he calls, whom he calls, he iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, and whom he iuſtifies, them will he alſo glorifie.</hi> Of theſe <hi>Waters,</hi> whoſoeuer drinkes, ſhall neuer thirſt againe; for they ſhall be in him a <hi>Well,</hi> ſpringing vp into euerlaſting life. This <hi>Garden</hi> is the place whither <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare his <hi>Banquet;</hi> and a <hi>Banquet</hi> he prouides very delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, for it is <hi>Mirrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice,</hi> the <hi>hony-combe</hi> and the <hi>hony, Wine</hi> and <hi>Milke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I gathered my Mirrhe with my Spice, &amp;c.]</hi> Theſe words may beare a double ſenſe: Firſt, <hi>Mirrhe</hi> is a gumme very bitter, but <hi>Spice</hi> is ſweet; by <hi>Mirrhe</hi> therefore may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the <hi>Law,</hi> by <hi>Spice</hi> the <hi>Goſpell:</hi> for the <hi>Law</hi> is bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it ſhewes vs our ſinnes, the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is ſweet, for it applies a remedie: the <hi>Law</hi> is a <hi>Rod</hi> of iron, called by<note n="s" place="margin">Zach. 11.7.</note> 
               <hi>Zacharie, Bandes;</hi> the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is like <hi>Aarons Rod,</hi> bearing freſh Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, named by the ſame Prophet <hi>Beautie:</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> is a<note n="t" place="margin">Numb. 17. Deut. 18.16.</note> 
               <hi>flaming fire,</hi> that conſumes; the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Cooling water</hi> of the Rocke which comforts: the <hi>Law</hi> is the <hi>ſauour</hi> of death; the <hi>Goſpel of life:</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Amb. in <hi>11.</hi> ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Nam data eſt Lex</hi> (ſaith <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) vt humanum genus terrore manifeſtatae legis froenaretur. The Law was giuen that mankinde might be terrified with the manifeſtation thereof:</hi> But of the contrary part,<note n="x" place="margin">Amb. in <hi>3.</hi> ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>Euangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um gaudium operatur:</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> worketh <hi>Ioy.</hi> Our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> therefore making his marriage <hi>feaſt,</hi> gathers <hi>Mirrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice,</hi> the one <hi>Bitter,</hi> the other <hi>Sweet,</hi> and mixeth them together: for if hee had giuen his <hi>Gueſts Mirrhe</hi> onely to eate, they would haue cried out like the children of the <hi>Prophets,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">2. Reg. 4.40.</note> 
               <hi>Mors in olla, Death is in the Pot:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the<note n="z" place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>Law is a killing letter, and cauſeth death:</hi> and if he had ſet before them <hi>Spice</hi> alone, then might they haue thought, that the <hi>Law</hi> was wholly abrogate: no, he came not to deſtroy, <hi>but to fulfill the Law;</hi> therefore he gathers <hi>Mirrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice</hi> together, qualifying the <hi>bitterneſſe of the Law,</hi> with the <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12373:9"/>Secondly, by <hi>Mirrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice,</hi> I rather thinke that the Spirit of God meanes <hi>the preaching</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Which is the ſauour of life vnto life, and of death vnto death,</hi> and therefore it is both <hi>Bitter</hi> and <hi>Sweet;</hi> firſt, it is ſweet, for it is the<note n="b" place="margin">Luc. 24.46.</note> preaching of repentance, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes in the name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and therefore it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in Greeke, which word amongſt prophane wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſignifies ioyfull <hi>newes;</hi> So <hi>Ariſtophanes</hi> vſeth it, ſaying,<note n="c" place="margin">Ariſtoph. in equit.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I haue tolde them good tidings;</hi> and can any thing be ſweeter to the ſoule of man, then the Gladſome <hi>Report</hi> of eternall life reuealed in the <hi>Goſpel?</hi> Secondly, it is <hi>Bitter,</hi> but yet this <hi>Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is not properly in the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but is cauſed by the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contempt and diſobedience of the <hi>hearers,</hi> by whoſe peruerſe nature the ſweetneſſe thereof is turned to bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; to the faithfull beleeuers the <hi>Goſpel</hi> bringeth <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and peace,</hi> if it doe not ſo to others, the fault is in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Againe, the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is both <hi>Sweet</hi> and <hi>Bitter, Sweet</hi> in it ſelfe, but very <hi>Bitter</hi> in the <hi>Profeſſion:</hi> this wee may gather by the<note n="d" place="margin">Reuel. 10.10.</note> 
               <hi>little booke that Iohn ate,</hi> giuen him by the <hi>Angel,</hi> which, <hi>in his mouth was ſweet as honie, but in his belly as bitter as Wormewood;</hi> This <hi>Booke</hi> is the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which in the mouth of a good Miniſter, is wondrous ſweet and comfortable, but in his belly extreame bitter; becauſe the true <hi>Preachers</hi> of the word,<note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>and all that liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus, doe euer ſuffer perſecution;</hi> they in this world haue the ſame entertainment that their Maiſter <hi>Chriſt</hi> had amongſt the Iewes, <hi>Gall, Vinegar,</hi> and a <hi>Whip:</hi> but of the contrarie part, in the <hi>Carnal-Goſpellers</hi> mouth this <hi>Booke</hi> is euer <hi>bitter,</hi> but yet <hi>ſweet</hi> in his belly; for it is death to him to preach the word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon: Oh no, he hates a <hi>Pulpit</hi> as much as the<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Prieſts of Dagon</hi> doe the Threſhold vpon which their God broke his necke: to him it is paine to ſpeake, for like <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> when he was bribed to hold his peace. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with a <hi>Siluer-angina,</hi> which ſtops his mouth, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12373:10"/>
makes him dumbe; but in his belly it is <hi>ſweet:</hi> for the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> enriches, promotes, and preferres him, and thereby he growes as <hi>fat as a Bull of Baſan;</hi> but marke his end, as <hi>Iudas</hi> ſaid vnto the high <hi>Prieſts</hi> ſeruants con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Chriſt, Whom I kiſſe, take him, that is he:</hi> So ſaies the <hi>world</hi> to the <hi>Diuel: Whom I kiſſe, lay hands on him, he is thine owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſaith <hi>Chriſt, I ate my hony-combe with my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.]</hi> Hereby is vnderſtood that <hi>Peace</hi> which our Sauiour hath made betwixt his Father and vs. The <hi>ſinne</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> in Paradiſe, made the breach betwixt God and mankinde: the death of <hi>Chriſt</hi> made the attonement and reconciliation, ſo ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>When we were ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne.</hi> As then <hi>Sampſon</hi> in his Riddle ſaid vnto his Companions,<note n="h" place="margin">Iudg. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>Out of the eater came meate, and out of the ſtrong one came ſweetneſſe:</hi> Which was meant of a <hi>dead Lyon,</hi> in whoſe bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Bees</hi> had hiued and made honie; ſo I may ſay of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> for he was a<note n="i" place="margin">Reu. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Lyon</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and from him being crucified for our ſinnes, and ſlaine for our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we receiue our <hi>hony and our hony-combe,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Peace</hi> with God the Father. <hi>Christ</hi> therefore is called the<note n="k" place="margin">Eſay. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> at whoſe birth a <hi>Quire of Angels</hi> ſung this Dittie,<note n="l" place="margin">Luc. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Glory be to God in the high heauens, and peace in earth, and towards men good will.</hi> Be the Sea neuer ſo rough and turbulent, yet when the <hi>Halcion</hi> hatcheth, it is euer calme: whereupon ariſeth this Prouerbe, <hi>Halcedonia ſunt circa forum, All is well, all things are quiet:</hi> So when they <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> brought forth the <hi>Sauiour</hi> of the world; the forehead of God all rugged with anger, for the ſinne of <hi>Adam,</hi> grew ſmooth and amiable:<note n="m" place="margin">Coloſſ. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>For it pleaſed the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that in him ſhould all fulneſſe dwell, and by him to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile all things to himſelfe, and ſet at peace through the blood of his croſſe, both the things in earth, and the things in heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here it is ſaid, <hi>I ate my hony-combe with my hony; honie</hi> is ſweet and good, I confeſſe, and the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12373:10"/>
vſeth <hi>It and Oyle,</hi> for the two emblems of <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> as we may read in the ſong of <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſaying,<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 32.13.</note> 
               <hi>He ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him vp to the high places of the earth, that he might eate the fruites of the fields, and he cauſed him to ſucke honie out of the ſtone, and Oile out of the hard rocke:</hi> But for the <hi>hony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe,</hi> why ſhould <hi>Chriſt</hi> eate it?<note n="o" place="margin">Zeph. 3.3.</note> Wolues are very hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, <hi>that will not leaue the bones till the morrowe:</hi> And ſo is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though he be not a Wolfe, yet he is a <hi>Lambe</hi> that is both hungrie and thirſtie, till hee haue taken away the ſinnes of the world: and therefore he <hi>Eates his honie-combe with his honie:</hi> ſo greedie is he to cancell the hand-writing which was againſt vs, ſo deſirous of our peace and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. S. <hi>Bernard</hi> writing vpon this word<note n="p" place="margin">Ioh. 19.28.</note> 
               <hi>Sitio, I thirſt,</hi> which our <hi>Sauiour ſpoke</hi> hanging vpon the Croſſe, makes this <hi>Dialogue</hi> betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>himſelfe. Sitio,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, Quid ſitis Domine?</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard: Chriſt</hi> anſweres, <hi>Sitio ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem veſtram, veſtram fidem, veſtrum gaudium.</hi> To this <hi>Sitto,</hi> I will adde <hi>Eſurio,</hi> and then will the <hi>Dialogue be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete I hunger, I thirſt,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Lord why art thou hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, why art thou thirſtie?</hi> ſay we: he replies, <hi>I hunger and thirſt for your ſaluation, for your faith, for your ioy, for your peace and attonement with God;</hi> and this peace hath hee made, this league hath he ratified.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>I haue drunke my wine with my Milke, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be three kindes of <hi>wine:</hi> the firſt is called, <hi>Vinum vanum &amp; deteſtabile,</hi> a vaine and deteſtable kinde of wine, ſo called in regard of the effects that flowe from the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous drinking of it: for too much<note n="q" place="margin">Hoſe. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>takes away the heart of man,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hoſeah,</hi> and is the very bellowes and incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of <hi>Luſt</hi> and wantonneſſe; too much of it makes vials of vengeance be powred vpon our heads: ſo ſaith <hi>Iſaiah,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iſai. 28.1.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be to the crowne of pride, to the drunkards of Ephraim, for his glorious beauty ſhall be a fading flower.</hi> And for this cauſe, as<note n="s" place="margin">Pli. lib. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Plinie</hi> reports, the <hi>Ladies</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> were forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Wine</hi> by the lawes, <hi>Ne in aliquod dedecus prolaberentur,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12373:11"/>
for feare of diſhonouring themſelues. The ſecond is, <hi>Vinum durum &amp; execrabile,</hi> a harſh execrable wine. Of this <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh, ſaying,<note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 32.32.33.</note> 
               <hi>Their Wine is of the Vine of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and of the Vines of Gomorrah, their Grapes are Grapes of gall, their cluſters be bitter: Their Wine is the poiſon of Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons, and the cruell gall of Aſpes.</hi> This is the pure <hi>Wine</hi> of the wrath of God, which <hi>Reprobates</hi> drinke in hell. I keepe the <hi>good Wine</hi> vntill now, and it is <hi>dulce &amp; delectabile, ſweet and delightſome,</hi> a Wine that <hi>cheares</hi> the heart of man, a wine that turneth euery thought into ioy: and this is it that <hi>Chriſt</hi> mixeth with milke, and drinkes a health to his <hi>welbeloued;</hi> by which is vnderſtood <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercie,</hi> as it is in the Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſaying,<note n="u" place="margin">Eſa. 55.1.</note> 
               <hi>Hoe, euery one that thirſteth, come ye to the waters, and ye that haue no ſiluer, come, buy, and eate, come, I ſay, buy wine and milke without ſiluer, and without mony:</hi> So likewiſe in <hi>Ioel,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ioel. 3.18.</note> 
               <hi>In that day the mountaines ſhall drop downe new Wine, and the hils ſhall flowe with milke:</hi> this wine is <hi>Grace,</hi> this milke is <hi>Mercie,</hi> which Chriſt offereth vnto all that will come vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I drunke my Wine with my milke.]</hi> This mixture is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, <hi>Wine and Milke Blent:</hi> ſhew that the worke of our <hi>Redemption, the Grace and Mercie of God in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> meete together and kiſſe each other, whereby we may gather, that <hi>Grace,</hi> whereby we are iuſtified, and made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable before God, is no quality inherent or dwelling in our ſelues, as the<note n="y" place="margin">Bell. de grat. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ieſuite</hi> auoucheth, but proceedeth from the <hi>Mercie</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> imputing vnto vs the righteouſneſſe of his Sonne: So ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>He hath made him to be ſinne for vs, that knew no ſinne, that wee ſhould be made the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God in him:</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Apoſt. Serm. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iuſtitia ſit, ſed ex gratia ſit, a Deo tibi ſit, non tua ſit: Sacerdotes tui in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit induantur iuſtitia: veſtis accipitur, non cum capillis naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp;c. Let there be righteouſneſſe, but let it be of grace, let it be of God, let it not be thine owne; Let thy Prieſts,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>be cloathed with righteouſneſſe; cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is receiued outwardly, it groweth not in vs as our
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12373:11"/>
haire, nor as the ſheepe are cloathed of their owne:</hi> So then Iuſtifying grace is no more ours, nor inherent in vs, then the veſture or garment, with which we are cloathed, which is not in vs, but onely adhereth, and is applied to vs. And is not this an excellent <hi>Banquet;</hi> Where <hi>Mirrhe and Spice</hi> is the <hi>Preaching of the Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>hony-combe,</hi> and the <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſpirituall peace,</hi> and the wine and milke <hi>Grace and Mercie?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The third and last generall part,</hi> is the <hi>Entertainment of the gueſts,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>Eate O my friends, drinke and make you merrie, O welbeloued.</hi> In which, I will obſerue two things: firſt, <hi>Who be the gueſts, that Chriſt inuites?</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>what is their entertainment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gueſts</hi> are our Sauiours <hi>welbeloued friends,</hi> a ſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted number, not the whole frie of the world, for, as<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>he died onely for his ſheepe,</hi> ſo was he borne onely for the <hi>Elect,</hi> his <hi>welbeloued friends.</hi> This Doctrine is gaine-ſaid by <hi>Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius,</hi> who as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirmeth, taught that the <hi>Grace</hi> of God, was not onely in reſpect of the outward meanes offered vnto all, but euen in his eternall Decree and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ordained for all, if they would receiue it; his reaſons be, becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>That God will that all men ſhall be ſaued,</hi> and S. <hi>Peter.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2. Pet. 3.9.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord would haue no man to periſh, but would haue all men come to repentance.</hi> Likewiſe,<note n="e" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt gaue himſelfe a ranſome for all:</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt died for all;</hi> as then all the <hi>World</hi> laies claime to his <hi>Croſſe,</hi> ſo in like manner to his <hi>Cratch;</hi> as he ſuffered death for all: ſo was he borne for all, and therefore the <hi>Gueſts</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> cals to his <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet,</hi> that is, to the <hi>Participation</hi> of his <hi>ſpirituall Graces,</hi> is no particular number, but the whole world. In anſwering theſe arguments, we muſt firſt conſider the <hi>Will of God,</hi> and ſecondly, the <hi>Death</hi> of <hi>Chriſt. Gods will</hi> is two-fold, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana &amp; reualata,</hi> his <hi>Secret will</hi> and his <hi>Reuealed will.</hi> Now then thoſe places of Scripture which <hi>Pellagius</hi> alledgeth, are to be vnderſtood of Gods <hi>Reuealed will,</hi> for by <hi>It</hi> hee would haue all men to be ſaued, becauſe he reioyceth not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12373:12"/>
at the deſtruction of his creature: but if we conſider his <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Will;</hi> then muſt we needs confeſſe, that<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 20.16.</note> 
               <hi>Many are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, but few are choſen:</hi> then muſt we needs acknowledge,<note n="g" place="margin">Pro. 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>That he reioyce that the deſtruction of the wicked:</hi> then muſt we of neceſſitie conclude, that from aeternitie his will is, that ſome ſhall not be ſaued, becauſe he reſpecteth a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther end; namely, the ſetting forth of his owne glory, which conſiſteth as well in <hi>Iuſtice</hi> as in <hi>Mercie.</hi> Secondly, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the death of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he dyed for all men, is moſt certaine, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> affirmes it; yet becauſe elſe where the Spirit of God ſaith,<note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>That he dyed for his ſheepe, and for the</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ephe. 5.25.</note> 
               <hi>Church:</hi> leaſt the <hi>Word</hi> ſhould ſeeme to thwart itſelfe, we muſt not take the letter, but follow the <hi>Scence,</hi> which is this. The death of our <hi>Sauiour</hi> in reſpect of it's ſufficiencie, hath ſatiſfied for all men; but is<note n="k" place="margin">Mag. ſent. li. <hi>3.</hi> diſt. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>efficacious</hi> onely to thoſe which were fore-ordained to life aeternall in Chriſt <hi>Ieſus:</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Auguſtine:</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Aug. tom. <hi>7.</hi> ad artic. falſ. impoſit.</note> 
               <hi>Quoad magnitudinem &amp; potentiam precij, Sanguis Chriſti eſt redemptio totius mundi, quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tamen non omnes captiuitate eruti ſunt, rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptionis proprietas hand dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penes illos eſt, qui me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra ſunt Chriſti: In respect of the greatnes of the price, the blood of Chriſt is the redemption of the whole world, but becauſe all are not redeemed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> captiuitie, the proper effect of redemption is onely wrought in the members of Chriſt.</hi> So likewiſe for his <hi>Birth,</hi> I ſay with <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Amb. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de fide. cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ille quidem miſericordia ſua omnibus natus eſt, ſed perfidia hocreticorum fecit, vt non omnibus naſceretur qui omnibus natus eſt. Hee in mercie was borne for all, but the vnfaithfulneſſe of haeretickes is the cauſe that he which is borne to all, is not borne for all.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Elect</hi> onely are the ſelected <hi>Guests,</hi> whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> inuites to his banquet, ſaying; <hi>Eate O my friends, drinke, and make you merry, O Welbeloued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What is their entertainment? Marueilous kind and louing;</hi> as may appeare by the <hi>Bridegromes</hi> words, <hi>Eate, drinke, and be merrie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But me thinkes this is a ſtrange ſpeech: why doth hee that ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Luc. 6.25.</note> 
               <hi>Woe be to them that be full,</hi> here bid vs eate and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12373:12"/>
drinke? Why doth he that ſaith, <hi>Wo be to them that laugh,</hi> here bid vs be merry? What are <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mammon</hi> confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate? is there friendſhip betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Belial?</hi> no, far be it from vs ſo to imagine, for theſe words are the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Spirit, howſoeuer the <hi>fleſh</hi> may miſ-expound them: They be like <hi>Muſicke,</hi> which according to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers diſpoſition, doth euer alter it's operation; for play vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an inſtrument before a <hi>Tyger,</hi> and he will grow more fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and rent his owne fleſh from his bones for anger: but let the <hi>Dolphin</hi> or the <hi>Hart</hi> heare any melodie, it ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſheth and delights them, that thereby they may be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to their death: euen ſo let one of thoſe, whom <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillius</hi> calleth <hi>Venties,</hi> Bellie-gods, or him that <hi>Athenaeus</hi> tearmes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Wine-bottle</hi> and a <hi>Meale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barrell,</hi> read theſe words and he will forth-with grow more luxurious, for his apprehenſion will reach no further then the fleſh-pots of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> Let any of our <hi>Hermophrodites,</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foeminate and wanton chamberers heare them, and they wil preſently begin to be as mad-merrie as the<note n="o" place="margin">Pom. Mel. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tabareni,</hi> of whom <hi>Pomponius Mela</hi> writes, which doe nothing all day long but make merrie, pipe and daunce: but of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary part, the <hi>Regenerate</hi> whoſe eares are circumciſed; they heare <hi>Chriſts</hi> voice, and they know his heart. They heare him ſay, <hi>Eate O my friends,</hi> and they know that he meanes <hi>Myrrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice,</hi> the <hi>Gospel;</hi> the food of the hungry ſoule, which euery one that hopes to be ſaued muſt be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to eate. They heare him ſay, <hi>Drinke O my friends,</hi> and they know it is <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Milke, Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercie;</hi> which whoſoeuer refuſeth being offred him, will Chriſt at the laſt day reiect with an <hi>Ito maledictie,</hi> depart thou cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. They heare him ſay, <hi>Be merrie O my welbeloued,</hi> and they know it is becauſe the <hi>Hony-combe with the honie</hi> is eaten by Chriſt, that is to ſay, hee hath made our peace with God the Father. <hi>Eate O my friends,</hi> ſaith Chriſt; hee inuites all to his Table, the word is preached to all, but all will not heare it, all will not come to his <hi>Feaſt?</hi> for they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12373:13"/>
haue either married a Wife, or hyred a Farme, or bought a yoke of Oxen, and therefore they muſt be excuſed. Theſe are the children of <hi>Martha,</hi> they are euer combred about worldly affaires, and wholy drawne from God, by the <hi>Diuels</hi> three golden hookes; <hi>Honour, Pleaſure,</hi> and <hi>Wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others being bidden, in plaine wordes refuſe to come; for they had rather, like the barbarous<note n="p" place="margin">Pom. Mel. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Trogloditae,</hi> feed on Toades and Serpents, then <hi>Mirrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice:</hi> their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks are onely for <hi>traditions</hi> of <hi>men;</hi> their plats diſtaſte the <hi>Word</hi> of life: ſuch be our <hi>Engliſh Recuſants,</hi> to whom if I were <hi>Iacob Iſachars</hi> bleſſing ſhould be theirs; which was this:<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 49.14.</note> 
               <hi>Iſachar is a ſtrong Aſſe couching betwixt the burthens;</hi> why may not I tearme them ſo, ſeeing that <hi>Gregorie</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting vpon theſe words in <hi>Iob: the</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 1.14.</note> 
               <hi>Oxen were plowing, and the Aſſes feeding in their places</hi> by them; by <hi>Oxen</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the <hi>Clergie,</hi> and by <hi>Aſſes</hi> the <hi>Laytie,</hi> which muſt feed by the <hi>Oxen,</hi> and beleeue as the <hi>Church</hi> beleeues; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contented with an <hi>implicite</hi> faith; for <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the mother of <hi>Deuotion,</hi> and ſo doe our <hi>Recuſants,</hi> whoſe backes are euen broken with the burthens of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> and his <hi>diſciples.</hi> Some againe will come and ſit downe at the Table of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>eate,</hi> but they neuer diſgeſt the <hi>Mirrhe</hi> and <hi>Spice:</hi> ſuch are they, which either in heart being <hi>Romiſh,</hi> will come to the Church to ſaue their <hi>Lands,</hi> or elſe being <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> and of no Religion, come for feare of being ſuſpected to be <hi>Papiſts,</hi> you ſhall know them by their attention; for like as Adders refuſing the voyce of the Charmer, doe euer ſtoppe one eare by laying it cloſe to the ground, and the other with her tayle, ſo they barre the entrance of the Word; either by worldly <hi>Cogitations</hi> or priuate <hi>Conferences,</hi> but of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary part, the <hi>Elect</hi> which are the true friends of <hi>Chriſt, they come</hi> to the table willingly &amp; eate chearfully, for they euer hunger and thriſt after righteouſneſſe: what though the Word be bitter in reſpect of the <hi>Profeſſion?</hi> yet it is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12373:13"/>
               <hi>ſweet</hi> in regard of <hi>Contemplation,</hi> &amp; therefore they eate it as the food of their <hi>Soules.</hi> Secondly ſaith <hi>Chriſt; Drinke O my friends.]</hi> Here our <hi>Sauiour</hi> exhorts vs, to embrace his <hi>grace</hi> &amp; <hi>mercy,</hi> being freely offered vnto vs. And who would not pledge this health, conſidering that he which drinkes ſhall neuer thirſt again?<note n="s" place="margin">Apulei. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apuleius</hi> reporteth an excellent ſpeech of a certaine wiſe-man at his table, which was this; <hi>Prima era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera ad ſitim pertinet, ſecunda ad hilaritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tertia ad volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, quarta ad inſaniam. The firſt bowle of wine is drunke to quench the thirſt; the ſecond, to prouoke mirth; the third, for pleaſure, the forth makes a man mad:</hi> But it is far otherwiſe in drinking this <hi>Wine and Milke:</hi> for the firſt <hi>draught, is</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="t" place="margin">Eſa. 53.11.</note> 
               <hi>a fulneſſe of knowledge</hi> by the illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Gods <hi>ſpirit:</hi> the ſecond is, <hi>Certitudo ſalutis,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of ſaluation, reueiled</hi> vnto vs by the ſame <hi>Spirit,</hi> which in our hearts cryes <hi>Abba Father:</hi> the third is, <hi>Confidentia,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>Confidencie:</hi> whereby we approach boldly to the Throne of <hi>Grace:</hi> the fourth is,<note n="y" place="margin">Ephe. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>Adoptio, Adoption;</hi> by which we receiue power to be actually accounted the Sonnes of God by Chriſt. O let vs therefore drinke this <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Milke,</hi> that we neuer hereafter may thirſt againe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly ſaith <hi>Chriſt; Be merrie, O my Welbeloued.]</hi> Nay further, <hi>Be drunke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>;</hi> for ſo is it word for word in the <hi>Hebrew; be drunken, but</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Ephe. 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>not with Wine,</hi> for that is a voluntarie mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and the <hi>Soules corruption: Be drunken, but not with ſin,</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay. 29.9.</note> for <hi>then</hi> the <hi>Soule ſtaggers,</hi> &amp; falles into a ſpirituall ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: but be <hi>drunken with ioy, becauſe I haue Eate my Hony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combe</hi> with my Honie, &amp; <hi>purchaſed</hi> your<note n="b" place="margin">Ephe. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>peace. Be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, becauſe I haue bailed you out of Deaths dungeon, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered</hi> you from the <hi>bondage of Sathan. Be merry and reioyce alwaies, becauſe</hi> your names are writ in Heauen. Laſtly, be euen <hi>drunken</hi> with mirth and ioy becauſe being my friends vpon earth, you ſhall be filled in heauen with the pleaſures of Gods houſe. To which holy tabernacle, he that was born for vs bring vs: to whom with the Father, &amp; the holy Spirit, be all honor and glorie now and euer-more.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12373:14"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſecond Sermon.</hi> THE TRIVMPH OF CONSTANCIE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>APOC. 3.11.12. VER.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, I come ſhortly hold that thou haſt: that no man take thy Crowne.</p>
                  <p>Him that ouercommeth will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God, and he ſhall goe no more out: and I will write vpon him the Name of my God, and the Name of the Citie of my God, which is the new Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, which commeth downe out of Heauen from my God, and I will write vpon him my new Name.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the two ends of the<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 25.13.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>Mercie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat,</hi> were ſet two <hi>Cherubims of bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Gold,</hi> whoſe wings were ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out on hie, and their faces one againſt an other, both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Mercie-ſeat.</hi> This <hi>Seate</hi> of <hi>Mercie</hi> is<note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 3.24.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt:</hi> theſe <hi>Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims,</hi> the <hi>Prophets</hi> and the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> both which in all their Writings, looke and leuell their pennes at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the true <hi>propitiatorie.</hi> The <hi>Prophets</hi> being the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> were taught of God in<note n="c" place="margin">Num. 12.16.</note> 
               <hi>Dreames &amp; Viſions,</hi> both that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould come into the world to ſuffer, and alſo what ſhould happen
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12373:14"/>
before his birth: The <hi>Apoſtles</hi> being the <hi>Prophets</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> were after the ſame manner inſtructed in all occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences concerning the Church till the laſt day, &amp; <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming into the world to iudge. Of this ranck was <hi>Iohn,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtolicall Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>Propheticall Apoſtle,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by this <hi>Booke</hi> of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> being a <hi>Register</hi> of intricate <hi>Viſions;</hi> wherein there be couched as many<note n="d" place="margin">Hier. ad pauli.</note> 
               <hi>Myſteryes</hi> as <hi>Words.</hi> The <hi>Author</hi> hereof was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Secretarie Iohn;</hi> the <hi>place</hi> in which he penned it <hi>Path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> an Iſland in the<note n="e" place="margin">Strab. lib. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aegaean Sea,</hi> whither hee was bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by<note n="f" place="margin">Euſ. eccle. hiſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Domitian</hi> the <hi>Emperour;</hi> The <hi>time</hi> when theſe <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſions</hi> were ſeene, was the <hi>Lords day:</hi> and his firſt <hi>Viſion was of one like vnto the Sonne of Man, hauing in his right hand ſeauen ſtarres, and ſtanding in the middeſt of ſeauen gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candle-sticks;</hi> the <hi>Myſterie</hi> hereof is reueiled by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaying: <hi>The ſeauen Starres are the Angels of the ſeauen Churches, &amp; the ſeauen Candleſtickes, are the ſeauen Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Epheſus, Smyrna, Pergamus, Thiatira, Sardi, Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphia, and Laodicia:</hi> to the <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Byſhops</hi> whereof our <hi>Sauiour</hi> writes ſeauen <hi>Epiſtles,</hi> commending ſome, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing others, and exhorting all to <hi>Perſeuerance,</hi> to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> to <hi>Repentance:</hi> but to omit the reſt, at the ſeauenth verſe of this <hi>Chapter</hi> begins the <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> a Citie of <hi>Miſia</hi> in <hi>Aſia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Strab. lib. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> in the <hi>firſt</hi> part wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he commendeth the <hi>Angels</hi> patience, threatens his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and aſſureth him of <hi>ayd</hi> and aſſiſtance. In the <hi>latter part,</hi> which is my Text, hee firſt exhorts him to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie,</hi> in theſe words; <hi>Behold, I come ſhortly, hold that thou haſt, that no man take thy crowne.]</hi> Secondly, recounts the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Conquerors,</hi> ſaying; <hi>Him that ouercommeth will I make a Pillar in the Temple of my God, and hee ſhall goe no more out, and I will write vpon him the Name of my God, and the Name of the citie of my God, which is the new Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, which commeth downe out of Heauen from my God, and I will write vpon him my new Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Exhortation</hi> lies in theſe words, which are the very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12373:15"/>
Nauill of the <hi>Verſe: Hold that thou haſt,</hi> about which theſe two <hi>Motiues</hi> twine, like the Serpents about <hi>Mercuries rod.</hi> Firſt; <hi>Behold, I come ſhortly:</hi> ſecondly, that <hi>No man take thy Crowne. Hold that thou haſt: Constancie</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance</hi> are in the ſcriptures ſet forth by foure <hi>Metaphors, Ploughing, Running, Standing</hi> and <hi>Holding.</hi> For the firſt, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſaith,<note n="g" place="margin">Luc. 9.62.</note> 
               <hi>No man that putteth his hand to the Plough, and looketh backe, is apt to the Kingdome of heauen.</hi> This <hi>Plough is Gods ſeruice,</hi> and the <hi>Profeſſion of Chriſt;</hi> to which when a man hath once ſetled himſelfe, hee muſt by remembring <hi>Lots</hi> wife, take heed that he looke not backe. <hi>Religion</hi> is fitly reſembled by the <hi>Plough,</hi> for the life of a true <hi>Profeſſour</hi> and a <hi>Plough-man</hi> are alike, both full of labour and trauaile: the one eates his bread in the ſweat of his face, the other groneth continually vnder the Croſſe. To this <hi>Plough,</hi> all that hope for heauenmuſt put their hands; <hi>for the Kingdome of heauen ſuffers violence,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chriſt</hi>) therefore we muſt take paines for it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue conſtantly at our worke, without looking backe from <hi>Zoar</hi> to <hi>Sodome,</hi> and from the paines of the <hi>Plough</hi> to the pleaſures of the world.</p>
            <p>For the ſecond S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith;<note n="h" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.</note> 
               <hi>So runne that you may obtaine;</hi> In ſome ſort all men runne, but becauſe all doe not obtaine, it ſeemeth there is <hi>Error</hi> either in the choice of the way, or in the maner of running. There is but one way to heauen<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 7.13.</note> and it is narrow and ſtrait; &amp; this is <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the<note n="k" place="margin">Luc. 14.6.</note> 
               <hi>Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> whoſoeuer followeth not this <hi>Path,</hi> wandereth from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and therefore looſeth aeternall life: as the <hi>Way,</hi> ſo the maner of <hi>running is but One,</hi> it muſt be without <hi>ceaſing, ſtoppe,</hi> or <hi>ſtay,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 10.22.</note> for onely <hi>hee which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth vnto the end ſhall be ſaued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the third, the ſame <hi>Apostle</hi> ſaith;<note n="m" place="margin">Ephe. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>Stand there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp; your loynes girded about with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritie.</hi> Now what elſe is it to <hi>ſtand, but to be</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Ephe. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>strong in the Lord and in the power of his might?</hi> to be <hi>constant Souldier,</hi> no faint-hearted Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? Such as be weake in faith cannot but fall, becauſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12373:15"/>
like the<note n="o" place="margin">Dan. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Beare</hi> in <hi>Daniels Viſion,</hi> they ſtand onely vpon the <hi>one ſide,</hi> &amp; but vpon one <hi>Leg:</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Cant. 5.15.</note> but ſuch as be <hi>ſtrong in faith, haue legs like marble pillars ſet vpon ſockets of gold,</hi> permanent, firme &amp; ſolid, and vſing them both they muſt needs <hi>ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>fourth,</hi> my <hi>Text</hi> ſaith; <hi>Hold, that thou haſt.</hi> That is to ſay; <hi>perſeuere in faith</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Vſe thy function</hi> without <hi>feare.</hi> This is the Pharaphraſe of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours</hi> ſpeech, the <hi>Scope</hi> whereof is to make the <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> like vnto the<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 30.28.</note> 
               <hi>Spider</hi> in the <hi>Prouerbs:</hi> of which <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Spider taketh hold with her hands, and is in Kings pallaces:</hi> ſo muſt he with <hi>constant faith and vndaunted courage, the two hands of the ſoule,</hi> lay faſt hold vpon the <hi>Croſſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and neuer let his <hi>Hold goe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hold that thou haſt]:</hi> This <hi>Exhortation</hi> is an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the <hi>poiſon</hi> of <hi>Haereticks,</hi> and a <hi>Shield</hi> to blunt the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Tyrants:</hi> which two ſorts of <hi>men</hi> in the <hi>Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> Church (like brethren in euill) were leagued and linkt in conſpiracie againſt <hi>Christ,</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters:</hi> the <hi>One ſort being Sathans Aduocates,</hi> the other his <hi>Aſſaſcinates. Haeretickes</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Apoc. 9.3.</note> 
               <hi>like the Locuſts</hi> with <hi>Scorpion-like</hi> tailes, did not onely hurt <hi>Reprobates,</hi> with the deadly ſting of their <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous</hi> errour, but alſo endeuoured thereby to kill them which had the <hi>Seale</hi> of God on their fore-heads. <hi>Tyrants,</hi> like the<note n="s" place="margin">Apoc. 12.</note> great <hi>red Dragon with ſeauen heads and ten hornes,</hi> neuer ceaſed to perſecute the <hi>Spouſe</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to make warre with her ſeed; what by the <hi>Impostures</hi> of <hi>Haereticks</hi> and the <hi>crueltie</hi> of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> many Chriſtians were drawen to leaue their <hi>Hold,</hi> and fall backe from the <hi>Truth.</hi> Againſt theſe enemies of the <hi>Gospel</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> this <hi>good Angel of Philadelphia,</hi> had hitherto (according to his little ſtrength) oppoſed himſelfe; Now becauſe hee ſhould not faint in the middeſt of his conflict, our <hi>Sauiour</hi> encourageth him with this exhortation ſaying: <hi>Hold that thou haſt,</hi> as if he ſhould haue ſaid; <hi>Thou haſt begun in the Spirit, end not thee in the fleſh; as yet thou beareſt the Image of God, then faſhion not thy ſelfe according to the world, thine Alpha</hi> hath beene
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12373:16"/>
               <hi>Sinceritie, then let not thy Omega be ſenſualitie: without per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance the best Profeſſour is a branch cut from the Vine, he can bring foorth no fruit; a painted Tombe full of rotten bones, and a fruitleſſe figge-tree with goodly bloſſomes.</hi> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, <hi>Be of a ſtout and valiant courage in the managing of thine office: ſubdue feare, let not the rough hand and rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged face of Tyrannie affright thee, or weaken thy reſolution; the perſecutour may deſtroy thy bodie, but he cannot kill thy ſoule: therefore be not diſmaid, for he that looſeth his life for my ſake, ſhall finde it againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As <hi>Chriſt</hi> writes to this <hi>worthy Angel,</hi> ſo in like maner he doth to the <hi>Angels</hi> of all <hi>Churches</hi> in the world; whether they be in the <hi>Eparchia,</hi> to wit, <hi>Arch-angels,</hi> or <hi>Monarchs,</hi> or in the <hi>Meſarchia,</hi> namely, <hi>Cherubims and Seraphims,</hi> or <hi>Biſhops:</hi> or in the <hi>Hyparchia, ministring spirits</hi> or <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> of the Word; to euery one of theſe particularly he ſaith; <hi>Hold that thou haſt:]</hi> For neuer was there more need of <hi>Holding,</hi> then in this age. Indeed, in the <hi>Primatiue Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in pſal. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> I confeſſe with <hi>Augustine,</hi> that the <hi>Diuell</hi> was both <hi>Leo aperte ſaeuiens, &amp; Draco occulte inſidians;</hi> by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and out-ragious crueltie hee ſhewed himſelfe a <hi>Lyon,</hi> and by his ſecret poiſoning of <hi>Religion</hi> a <hi>Dragon;</hi> yet his malicious power was curbed, and<note n="t" place="margin">Apoc. 20.2.</note> hee himſelfe bound in chaines for a thouſand yeeres, ſo that notwithſtanding all his <hi>ſubtiltie</hi> and <hi>crueltie, Trueth</hi> like a Palme-tree flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and <hi>Chriſts Croſſe</hi> like <hi>Aarons Rod</hi> did bloſſome, and bring forth much fruit: but now the old <hi>Serpent</hi> is let looſe, and of late yeares hath acted both the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Dragon</hi> without reſtraint, both by <hi>policie</hi> and <hi>puiſſance,</hi> ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying to extinguiſh the light of <hi>Truth:</hi> neither haue his attempts beene effectleſſe, for what by <hi>Magogs</hi> ſword in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> and <hi>Gogs</hi> vſurped <hi>Keyes</hi> in the <hi>West,</hi> hee hath driuen <hi>Truth</hi> like a Doue into the holes of the Rocke, and baniſhed <hi>Faith</hi> from amongſt men.</p>
            <p>In the time of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> the<note n="u" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</note> 
               <hi>Myſterie of iniquitie</hi> began to worke, by the <hi>Agencie</hi> of <hi>Haereticks,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Simon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12373:16"/>
Magus,</hi> the <hi>father of Deceiuers, Menander, Cerinthus, Ebion,</hi> the <hi>Nicholaitans,</hi> and many other of the ſame counterfait ſtampe; all which be returned to the bottomleſſe pit from whence they came, and in their place ſucceed<note n="x" place="margin">Apo. 16.13.</note> Frogges, vncleane Spirits, whom the <hi>Dragon,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> haue ſent out of their mouthes vnto the kings of the earth, to gather them to the battaile of that great day of God Almightie. Theſe are the croaking frie of <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and <hi>Seminarie Prieſts,</hi> which are <hi>ſent from Rome</hi> to the Courts of Princes, to ſtir them vp to make warre againſt the true <hi>Profeſſours</hi> of the <hi>Gospel:</hi> theſe are the <hi>Leproſie</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the bane of <hi>Christian</hi> Common-wealths; theſe are the true-borne ſonnes of their <hi>father,</hi> the olde <hi>Serpent;</hi> for as he in the ſubuerſion of mankind began with the woman and tempted her, ſo they inſinuate themſelues into our <hi>weaker veſſels,</hi> and lead them <hi>captiue</hi> to <hi>Babylon.</hi> For reformation whereof, I wiſh that that Edict were in force amongſt vs, which<note n="y" place="margin">Heſt. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſueroh</hi> vpon the contempt of Queene <hi>Vaſti,</hi> made and proclaimed amongſt the <hi>Meedes</hi> and <hi>Perſians:</hi> Namely, <hi>that euery one ſhould beare rule in his owne houſe.</hi> In auncient time, <hi>Rome</hi> was hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for a <hi>Goddeſſe,</hi> and <hi>ſhee had her Temple,</hi> and her ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of <hi>Blood.</hi> So ſaith <hi>Prudentius:</hi> 
               <q>
                  <l>Delubrum Romae colitur, nam ſanguine &amp; ipſa<note place="margin">Prud. lib. <hi>1</hi> Con. Sym.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>More Deae, nomen<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> loci ſeu numen habetur.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And euen ſo is ſhe now <hi>Idolized</hi> by theſe <hi>Frogges,</hi> her <hi>Priests,</hi> whoſe <hi>oblations</hi> are euer bloody; if her <hi>Deitie</hi> be offended, nothing can appeaſe her wrath but death: How many of Gods annointed <hi>Princes</hi> haue theſe <hi>Idolatrous ſhauelings ſacrificed</hi> vpon her altar? and how many treaſons did they broach to entrapt that <hi>Mirrour</hi> of her <hi>Sexe, Englands Debora,</hi> our deceaſed Soueraigne? From whence came the <hi>Salt-peter</hi> which made the <hi>Gun-powder?</hi> was it not brought from him who challengeth <hi>Peters Chaire,</hi> and ſhould therefore like his pretended <hi>Praedeceſſour,</hi> be the<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>Salt</hi> of the earth; but he hath loſt his <hi>ſauour,</hi> and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12373:17"/>
therefore he is now good for nothing, but to be caſt out, and troden vnder the foot of men. Well, I may iuſtly ſay of theſe <hi>Frogges,</hi> as the Greeke <hi>Poet</hi> did of the people of <hi>Caria, Aegypt,</hi> and <hi>Lydia.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The <hi>Locuſtes</hi> which did peſter the <hi>Primatiue Church,</hi> were venemous vermine, and did much hurt with their <hi>Lion-like</hi> teeth, and <hi>Scorpion-like</hi> tailes; but <hi>theſe</hi> doe quite out-ſtrip and ſurpaſſe them in miſchiefe and crueltie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When</hi> that glorious <hi>Woman</hi> clothed with the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and crowned with twelue <hi>Starres</hi> was in her trauaile, then the <hi>Beaſt</hi> with ſeauen heads and ten hornes ſtood before her, to deuoure her <hi>Child,</hi> when it ſhould be brought foorth: that is to ſay, the <hi>Romiſh Empire,</hi> did wholy oppoſe it ſelfe againſt the kingdome of <hi>Chriſt</hi> when it was firſt preached: witneſſe the cruell Perſecutions vnder <hi>Nero, Domitian, Traian,</hi> and the reſt.<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 7.7. Apoc. 13.11.</note> This <hi>Beaſt</hi> I confeſſe was <hi>fearefull, terrible and very ſtrong;</hi> but nothing in <hi>compariſon</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt</hi> with two <hi>hornes</hi> like a <hi>Lambe,</hi> and whoſe ſpeech is like the <hi>Dragon</hi> that is now come out of the earth, for he plaies both the <hi>Tyrant</hi> and the <hi>Imposter:</hi> he doth all that the firſt <hi>Beaſt</hi> could doe, in ſhedding of blood; and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer by ſignes and falſe miracles hee deceiueth them that dwell on the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> is <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> that <hi>Man of ſinne,</hi> that <hi>child of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> that <hi>Belial</hi> ſubiect to no yoke, who according to the ſignification of his name, is both <hi>for</hi> &amp; againſt <hi>Chriſt:</hi> who he is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er. ep.</hi> 12.5.</note> &amp; where he dwels S. <hi>Bernard</hi> tels vs, ſaying; <hi>Bestia in Apocalypſi cui datu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt os loquens blasphemias Petri cathedra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occupat:</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the <hi>Apocalipſe,</hi> to which was giuen a mouth ſpeaking blaſphemies, doth occupie <hi>Peters</hi> chaire. <hi>Iam-pridem Romae natus eſt Antichristus; Antichriſt</hi> a good while ſince was borne at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ioachim</hi> the <hi>Abbot.</hi> This is he who calleth himſelfe <hi>Christs Vicar,</hi> and yet robs <hi>Chriſt</hi> of his honour; who is ſtiled the <hi>Seruant</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:12373:17"/>
of <hi>Seruants,</hi> and yet exalteth himſelfe aboue all, that is called <hi>God:</hi> this is that <hi>purple Whore</hi> which maketh her Followers drunken with the <hi>Cup</hi> of her abhominable <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie,</hi> and is drunke her ſelfe with the blood of <hi>Saintes</hi> and <hi>Martyrs.</hi> In a word the <hi>Papacie,</hi> in which both the <hi>tyrannie</hi> of the <hi>Romane Emperours,</hi> and the leauen of aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Haereticks</hi> concurre and meet together: ſeeing then that <hi>Sathan</hi> is vnchained, ſeeing that theſe <hi>Frogs</hi> crawle in euery corner of <hi>Christian</hi> Common-wealths, and ſeeing that this <hi>Beaſt</hi> doth continually bend his ſharpe <hi>hornes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the true <hi>Profeſſours</hi> of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> it doth nerely concerne all <hi>good Angels,</hi> whether they be <hi>ſpirituall</hi> or <hi>temporall, To hold that they haue,</hi> by <hi>perſeuering in true faith</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>by exerciſing their Functions</hi> without <hi>feare.</hi> Of all other Angels, <hi>Antichrists</hi> malice is moſt againſt <hi>Archangels, or Princes;</hi> his indeauour is to make them his <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> by treading vpon their necks, and depriuing them of their crownes: for who knoweth not how arrogantly hee claimeth to be <hi>Lord</hi> of the whole earth,<note place="margin">Gel. diſt. <hi>96.</hi>
               </note> and challengeth both an Eccleſiaſtick and ciuill <hi>Supremacie:</hi> doth it not then behoue <hi>Princes to hold faſt that they haue? God grant</hi> then that <hi>true Faith</hi> may be their <hi>Shield,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> their <hi>Sword,</hi> and the <hi>ſaluation of God</hi> their <hi>Helmet,</hi> that being thus armed they may be enabled to reſiſt all the aſſaults of that blaſphemous <hi>Antichriſtian horne.</hi> Let their <hi>Diadems,</hi> (O Lord) be like vnto <hi>Aarons Miter,</hi> vpon which theſe words were ingrauen; <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord:</hi> for <hi>Sinceritie</hi> in Religion is the moſt ſteadfaſt proppe of roiall authoritie, and the moſt firme ſupporter of a throne, it is like the <hi>braſen Bulles,</hi> that held vp the ſacred <hi>Lauer,</hi> or the yuorie <hi>Lions</hi> of <hi>Salomons kingly Seat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Behold, I come ſhortly: hold that thou haſt, that no man take thy crowne.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Exhortation</hi> being finiſhed, the <hi>Motiues</hi> follow, which be theſe: <hi>Firſt, Behold I come ſhortly; Secondly, that no man take thy crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:12373:18"/>Theſe two are of a contrary nature: the firſt is <hi>ſweet,</hi> and flowes with hony, the ſecond is bitter, &amp; full of gall; in the firſt the voice of <hi>Christ</hi> is like a <hi>ſweet</hi> Cymball; in the ſecond like the ſound of many waters; the firſt is a <hi>Motiue</hi> of <hi>Comfort,</hi> promiſing aid &amp; aſſiſtance, the ſecond of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> threatning a degradation for want of perſeuerance: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: as it is in the Prouerbe, out of the mouth of <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes both <hi>hote</hi> and <hi>cold;</hi> a <hi>hote Cordiall and a cold Coraſiue,</hi> ſuch is his <hi>Rhetorike,</hi> if by faire promiſes he cannot perſwade, his cuſtome is by threatnings to Compell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce venio citò. Behold I come ſhortly.]</hi> This <hi>Motiue</hi> is a proclamation very ſhort, but wondrous pithie and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous, wherein euery word is remarkeable.</p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>Ecce, Behold.</hi> When the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeakes of the firſt comming of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> he begins his Prophecie with an <hi>Ecce,</hi> ſaying,<note n="b" place="margin">Eſay. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce Virgo, &amp;c: Behold a Virgin ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue and beare a Sonne, and ſhee ſhall call his Name, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel.</hi> So in this Booke, where there is any mention made of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſecond comming, there is euer prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an <hi>Ecce:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Apoc. 22.12.</note> 
               <hi>Behold I come ſhortly, and my reward is with me.</hi> Whereby we may coniecture that the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> would haue vs attentiue, for he is about to proclaime ſome won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. In his firſt comming there is, <hi>Ecce humilitatem; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> his wonderfull <hi>humilitie:</hi> but here in his ſecond comming, there is <hi>Ecce gloriam, behold his admirable glory.</hi> Betwixt this and that <hi>Ecce,</hi> there is as great <hi>difference,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Tabor</hi> and <hi>Caluerie:</hi> the firſt of which ſaw his beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Tranſfiguration,</hi> the ſecond his vncouth <hi>Deformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce, behold his humilitie:</hi> in his firſt comming, hee was the<note n="d" place="margin">Cant. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Lillie of the Vallies,</hi> for his mother was a poore <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin,</hi> his cradle a cratch, his followers fiſhers, his apparrell a cote without ſeame, and his ſteed, an aſſe: but <hi>Ecce, behold his glory.</hi> In his ſecond comming, he <hi>ſhall be the</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cant. 2.1.</note> 
               <hi>Roſe of the field, full of maiestie,</hi> attired in glorious apparrell, and girded about with ſtrength; his attendants ſhall be <hi>Legions</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:12373:18"/>
of <hi>Angels,</hi> his <hi>Court</hi> in the clowdes, and his ſteed<note n="f" place="margin">Apoc. 19.11.</note> a white <hi>horſe. Ecce: behold his humilitie,</hi> when hee came firſt,<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 12.47.</note> it was to ſuffer for our ſins,<note n="h" place="margin">Eſa. 53.4.5.</note> to <hi>beare our infirmities, to carry our ſorrowes, to be wounded for our tranſgreſſions, to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for our iniquities, to make our peace with his own chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to heale vs with his ſtripes: then</hi> was his head crowned with thornes, his eares filled with <hi>Crucifige</hi> and blaſphemies; his eyes cloſed vp with dimme death, his face made blew with blowes, his mouth made bitter with gall and vineger, his hands and feete nailed to the Croſſe, and his whole bodie rack't and tentar'd <hi>ad modum timpanicae pellis,</hi> like the head of a Tymbrell or a Tabret. But <hi>ecce, behold his glory</hi> in his ſecond comming, he ſhall<note n="i" place="margin">Eſay 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>eaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of his aduerſaries, and auenge himſelfe of his enemies,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Cant. 5.</note> 
               <hi>his head ſhall be like fine gold,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Apoc. 19.12.</note> 
               <hi>and vpon it many crownes, his eyes like a flame of fire, his cheekes like beds of ſpices and ſweet flowers, his lippes like Lillies dropping downe pure mirrhe, his hands like rings of gold ſet with the Chriſolite, his bellie like white yuorie couered with Saphires, his legges like marble pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſet on ſockets of gold, and his countenance like Libanon, excellent as the Cedars. Oh, who then</hi> would not for a little time in this world <hi>hold faſt</hi> and be <hi>conſtant,</hi> hauing ſuch a <hi>Patterne and ſuch a Patron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce venio, Behold I come.]</hi> Theſe words haue a relliſh both of life and death, they be as <hi>ſweet</hi> as <hi>hony,</hi> and as bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as worme-wood; they be reſtoratiue to the <hi>Elect,</hi> but poiſon to the reprobates: &amp; therefore our <hi>Sauiour</hi> ſpeakes them to comfort the one, and terrifie the other. To the wicked nothing is more yrkeſome then the day of <hi>death,</hi> and the day of <hi>Doome. O mors quam amara, &amp;c? O death how bitter is thy memorie</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Wiſe-man) to him that putteth his truſt in his poſſeſſions?</hi> And the <hi>Euangeliſt</hi> tels vs, that at the laſt <hi>day</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Apoc. 6.15.</note> the <hi>kings</hi> of the <hi>earth, and the great men, and the rich men, and the chiefe captaines, and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie men ſhall hide themſelues in dennes, and among the rockes of the Mountaines, and ſhall ſay to the Mountaines and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12373:19"/>
fall on vs, and hide vs from the preſence of him that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the Throne, and from the wrath of the Lambe:</hi> but on the contrary part, <hi>Death</hi> to the righteous is euer welcome: <hi>For bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their workes follow them:</hi> and for the day of <hi>Doome,</hi> it is to them <hi>Mell in ore, melos in aure, Iubilaeus in corde;</hi> the name of it is as <hi>honie,</hi> the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it melodie, and the very thought of it a yeere of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilie:</hi> wherefore the <hi>Saints</hi> departed cry <hi>Quouſque Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne? How long Lord? Veni domine Ieſu, veni citò,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iohn, Come Lord Ieſus, come quickely:</hi> to whom our <hi>Sauiour</hi> makes this comfortable <hi>Reply; Ecce venio, behold I come. This <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enio, I come:</hi> may well be compared to<note n="n" place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids Harpe, and</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ioſuah 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſhuas Trumpet;</hi> the <hi>ſweet warble</hi> of <hi>Dauids harpe</hi> refreſhed king <hi>Saul</hi> in his agonie, and did driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>euill spirit; the ſound of Ioſhuas Trumpet</hi> made the walles of <hi>Iericho</hi> tremble, and leueld them with the ground: the like operation proceedes either from the hearing or reading of theſe two words; <hi>Ecce Venio, behold I come. Let</hi> one of the <hi>Elect</hi> heare them; imagine his ſhoulders be ouer loaden with the Croſſe, his head prick't with thornes, and his back embrodered with ſtripes, (as indeed in this world the <hi>righteous</hi> euer ſuffer affliction and perſecution, which like <hi>euill</hi> ſpirits haunt and torment them) yet I ſay, let them but heare this <hi>ecce venio,</hi> and their countenances will be cheared, and their hearts comforted, ſo pleaſant is the harmonie of this heauenly <hi>Harp, But</hi> let a <hi>Reprobate</hi> either heare or read them: ſuppoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as it is in the Prouerbe, hee ſwimme vp to the very eares in riuers of gold, be crowned with Roſe-buddes, and ſleepe vpon a bed of yuorie (as indeed the wicked in this life are euer moſt happy, free from Croſſes, free from tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations) yet I ſay, let them in the very ſurfet of their pleaſures; but heare this <hi>ecce venio,</hi> and like<note n="p" place="margin">1. Sam. 1.37</note> 
               <hi>Nabal,</hi> their hearts will die within them: and like<note n="q" place="margin">Dan. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Balthaſar</hi> at the ſight of the <hi>hand-writing</hi> on the wall, the ioynts of their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12373:19"/>
loynes will be looſed, and their knees ſmite one againſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſo fearefull is the ſound of this heauenly <hi>Trumpet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ecce venio eitô, Behold I come quickly.</hi> The comming of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is both <hi>certaine, ſuddaine, and ſhort:</hi> firſt, it is moſt certaine, ſo we gather out of the word, <hi>Venio, I come:</hi> for our <hi>Sauiour</hi> herein ſpeakes of a <hi>future</hi> iudgement, as if it were <hi>preſent.</hi> Secondly, it ſhall be ſuddaine; <hi>for behold, I come,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, like a theife in the night.</hi> Thirdly, it ſhall be <hi>ſhort: Behold I come ſhortly,</hi> though his comming be certaine, yet the time when is vncertaine: for it ſhall be <hi>ſuddaine</hi> and <hi>ſhort.</hi> I cannot then but condemne the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them that dare aſſigne the very yeare, month, and day of <hi>Chriſts</hi> comming to Iudgement; conſidering that their aſſertion, is flat oppoſite and contrary to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſaith;<note n="r" place="margin">Marc. 13.33.</note> 
               <hi>that the houre and day of Christs comming, is not knowen to the Angels, nor to the Sonne of Man, but to the Father onely:</hi> and yet <hi>Cuſanus like</hi>
               <note n="s" place="margin">Gen. 11.4.</note> 
               <hi>Nimrod,</hi> to get him a name, hath built a <hi>Babel</hi> of meer coniectures: as firſt; his opinion is, that the world ſhall end between the yeere 1700. and 1734. becauſe as <hi>Chriſt</hi> roſe againe in the foure &amp; thirtith yeare of his age, ſo the Church of God ſhall riſe at the latter day in the foure and thirtith <hi>Iubile,</hi> which make one thouſand ſeuen hundreth years. Secondly, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> in the foure and thirtith <hi>Iubile,</hi> there came a conſumption of <hi>ſinne</hi> by Water, for the Flood was one thouſand ſixe hundred fiftie ſixe years after the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the world: ſo in the foure &amp; thirtith <hi>Iubile,</hi> after the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> there ſhall be a finall conſumption of ſin by <hi>fire.</hi> Other coniectures he hath, but being but coniectures, I let them paſſe, ſaying with <hi>Augustine; De ſaluatoris reditu, qui expectatur in fine, tempora dinumerare non audeo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Epiſt. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>nec ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem Prophetarum hac de re numerum annorum existimo praeſciuiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Of our <hi>Sauiours</hi> returne, which is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the end, I dare not number the times, neither doe I thinke that any of the Prophets knew the number of the yeares: but rather that to ſtand which the Lord ſaith:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12373:20"/>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note>
               <hi>It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons, which the Father hath kept in his owne power.</hi> The Lord to great pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe would haue <hi>that day</hi> kept ſecret, that our hearts ſhould be in continuall expectation of it.<note place="margin">Aug. in pſal. <hi>36.</hi> con. <hi>1.</hi> Ser. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid ad te</hi> (ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine) quando venies? ſic vine, quaſi hodiè venturus ſit, &amp; non timebis cum venerit.</hi> What is it to thee when hee commeth? ſo liue as though hee ſhould come to day, and thou ſhalt not be afraid when hee commeth. <hi>Remember</hi> thine end, and thou ſhalt neuer doe amiſſe; the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Death</hi> and the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Doome</hi> are two <hi>Pole-starres,</hi> vpon which we that be <hi>Pilgrims</hi> and trauailers vpon earth, muſt euer fixe our eyes; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Aramathia</hi> made his <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> in his <hi>Garden;</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in their <hi>banquetting houſes</hi> had euer the picture of <hi>Death:</hi> ſo ought wee in the midſt of our worldly pleaſures and delights continually to caſt vp our accounts, &amp; daily to number our dayes. What know wee when the <hi>Bridegrome</hi> will come? It behoueth vs therefore like <hi>wiſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins</hi> euer to haue our <hi>Lampes full of Oyle,</hi> and to be in readineſſe, to giue attendance: <hi>For behold Chriſt will come certainely, ſuddainly, and ſhortly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hold that thou haſt, that no man take thy crowne.]</hi> In ſpeaking the firſt <hi>Motiue,</hi> the <hi>face of Chriſt</hi> was to looke vpon like the<note n="u" place="margin">Apoc. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>Gasper-stone,</hi> which is <hi>greene</hi> &amp; <hi>beautifull:</hi> but in this hee reſembleth the<note n="x" place="margin">Apoc. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>Sardine,</hi> which is <hi>red</hi> and <hi>bloodie,</hi> for there is <hi>Comfort,</hi> here is <hi>terrour;</hi> there <hi>his</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Cant. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>mouth was as ſweet things, and he wholy delectable; here out of his mouth proceeds a</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Apoc. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>ſharpe two-edged ſword,</hi> and his countenance is very fearefull.</p>
            <p>This word <hi>Corona,</hi> a <hi>Crowne,</hi> hath in the Scriptures diuers ſignifications, ſometimes it ſignifieth <hi>aeternall life:</hi> as in the ſecond chapter of the <hi>Apocalipſe:</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Apo. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Be faithfull vnto the death, and I will giue thee the crowne of life;</hi> &amp; ſo the <hi>Papists</hi> vnderſtand this place, whereupon they gather that the <hi>Decrees of Election</hi> and <hi>Reprobation be changeable:</hi> for the <hi>Schoole-men</hi> teach, that the <hi>Number</hi> of the <hi>Elect</hi> and of the <hi>Reprobate,</hi> is certainely and vnchangeably decreed
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12373:20"/>
and purpoſed of God in his aeternall counſell, ſo that it can neither be increaſed nor diminiſhed, for he hath abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely appointed how many ſhall be ſaued, and how many reiected: but yet they ſay, that he hath not certainely and vnchangeably decreed what particular men ſhall make vp, or be of this determined and purpoſed number; becauſe that <hi>Men</hi> hauing as they ſay, <hi>Free-will,</hi> doe ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from God, and ſometimes returne vnto him. The <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe <hi>Numbers,</hi> they call the <hi>Formall number;</hi> which is <hi>certaine;</hi> the latter they call the <hi>Materiall number,</hi> which is vncertaine and changeable: ſo by their doctrine, he that is <hi>elect</hi> may finally be blotted out of the booke of life, and become a <hi>Reprobate;</hi> and hee that is a <hi>Reprobate</hi> may be made an <hi>elect</hi> this their <hi>Poſition</hi> they endeuour to proue, by this <hi>Text of Scripture</hi> amongſt the reſt: by which words they affirme that it is euident, that he which is <hi>elect</hi> to wear a <hi>Crowne of life</hi> may looſe it: and another which was not <hi>elect,</hi> may ſupply his place. But this their Collection is contrary to the intention and meaning of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God that writ it, who is neuer in oppoſition to himſelfe.<note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 10.29.</note> 
               <hi>My Father is greater then all, and no man is able to take them out of his hand,</hi> therefore our <hi>election</hi> is certaine; <hi>For</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>with God there is no variablenes, neither ſhadowing by turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Horum qui electi ſunt, ſi quiſpiam perit, fallitur Deus, ſed nemo eorum perit, quia non fallitur Deus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de cor. &amp; gra. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Aqui. part. <hi>7.</hi> queſt. <hi>24.</hi> art. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine.</hi> Of the elect if any periſh God is deceiued; but none of them can periſh, becauſe God cannot be deceiued. Likewiſe <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Simpliciter in libro vitae, ſcripti nunquam deleri poſſunt;</hi> ſimply they that are written in the booke of life, can neuer be blotted out: of this Text of Scripture then we muſt ſeeke for ſome other Expoſition, for by it cannot be vnderſtood the <hi>Crowne of aeternall life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> this word <hi>Corona,</hi> a <hi>crowne,</hi> ſometimes ſignifieth any <hi>faithfull man,</hi> which by the Miniſterie &amp; preaching of the word is conuerted from <hi>Gentiliſme to Chriſtianity.</hi> So S. <hi>Paul</hi> calles the <hi>Philippians,</hi> ſaying;<note n="d" place="margin">Philip. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore my brethren,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12373:21"/>
beloued and longed for, my ioy and my crowne, ſo continue in the Lord ye beloued.</hi> Thirdly, it is the <hi>Badge</hi> or <hi>Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance</hi> of <hi>Authoritie,</hi> both <hi>Temporall</hi> and <hi>Spirituall;</hi> and ſo is it to be vnderſtood in this place: in which our <hi>Sauiour</hi> exhorteth the <hi>Angel,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Philadephia,</hi> to <hi>constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> in his <hi>Function,</hi> for feare an other be placed in his <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and take the dignitie of the <hi>Biſhoprick</hi> from him. By this threatned <hi>degradation</hi> may all <hi>Arch-angels</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> learne to know, that <hi>Crownes</hi> be no <hi>perpetuities.</hi> If <hi>Salomon</hi> turne his heart from the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and build high places to <hi>Chemoſh,</hi> the abhomination of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab,</hi> &amp; <hi>Molech,</hi> the abhomination of the children of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> God will ſurely rent his kingdome from him and giue it vnto his<note n="e" place="margin">1. Reg. 11.11</note> ſeruant: if <hi>Eli</hi> the high Prieſt will not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten the wickedneſſe of his ſonnes, but ſuffer them to run into ſlaunder, and ſtay them not,<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 4.11.18.</note> he and they both ſhall goe with blood to their graues, and the <hi>Prieſt-hood</hi> be conferred vpon an other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore hold that you haue, that no man take your Crownes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond generall part of my Text, is a Catalogue</hi> of the <hi>Rewards, that Chriſt promiſeth</hi> to beſtow on <hi>Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours;</hi> ſaying, <hi>Him that ouercommeth, will I make a pillar in the Temple of my God, and hee ſhall goe no more out: and I will write vpon him the Name of my GOD, and the name of the Citie of my God, which is the new Ieruſalem, which commeth downe out of heauen from my God, and I will write vpon him my new Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Him that ouercommeth, &amp;c.]</hi> Reward makes men both valiant and ventrous:<note n="g" place="margin">1. Sam. 18.27</note> for a <hi>wife, Dauid</hi> will fetch two hundreth fore-skins of the <hi>Philistims;</hi> for gold the<note n="h" place="margin">1. Reg. 9.28.</note> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of <hi>Salomon,</hi> will <hi>tenni confidere ligno,</hi> hazard their liues in a ſhip, and <hi>ſaile</hi> to <hi>Ophir.</hi> Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> therefore to ſtirre vp our courage, and put ſpirit in our faint hearts, doth as the <hi>Romanes</hi> did: they had lawes for the <hi>Triumphs</hi> of <hi>Generals,</hi> and diuerſities of <hi>crownes</hi> appointed for well
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12373:21"/>
deſeruing <hi>Martialiſts;</hi> and this was done in policie, to make their men of warre ſtout and valiant: ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> to encourage thoſe that march vnder his <hi>Standard, the Croſſe,</hi> proclaimeth their <hi>Rewards:</hi> ſaying,<note n="i" place="margin">Apoc. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>To him that ouercommeth will I giue to eate of the tree of life; which is in the middeſt of the Paradice of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 2.13.</note>
               <hi>To him that ouercommeth will I giue to eate of the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na that is hid, and will giue him a white ſtone, and in the ſtone a new name written, which no man knoweth ſauing he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Him that ouercommeth will I make a Pillar in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of my God, &amp;c.]</hi> Oh then, who would not be a ſouldier in the Campe of <hi>Chriſt?</hi> preferring his <hi>thornie crowne</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>diadem</hi> of <hi>gold;</hi> his <hi>Croſſe</hi> before a <hi>chaire</hi> of <hi>estate;</hi> his <hi>Whip</hi> before a <hi>Scepter;</hi> his <hi>Reed</hi> before all temporall <hi>Royaltie;</hi> his <hi>White coate</hi> before raiments of <hi>Needle-worke;</hi> his <hi>ſcoffes</hi> and <hi>taunts</hi> before worldly <hi>applauſe;</hi> his <hi>gall</hi> and <hi>vinegar</hi> before the rich <hi>Gluttons</hi> delicious fare; &amp; his <hi>death</hi> before <hi>life;</hi> conſidering that <hi>Cum Domino iudices venient qui nunc pro Domino iudicantur,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine) They ſhall come with the Lord as Iudges, who are now iudged for for the Lords cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Him that ouercommeth will I make a Pillar.] A Pillar</hi> is the Embleme of three things, <hi>Remembrance, Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence</hi> and <hi>Continuance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is the <hi>Register</hi> of <hi>Memorie. God</hi> turned<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 19.26.</note> 
               <hi>Lots</hi> wife into a <hi>pillar</hi> of <hi>Salt,</hi> becauſe contrary to the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Angel, ſhee looked backe towards <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah:</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith; <hi>Remember Lots wife.</hi> The ſight of this <hi>Salt pillar,</hi> was to make men remember the iudgements of God, and to terrifie them from backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding and reuolting.<note n="m" place="margin">2. Sa. 18.18.</note> 
               <hi>Abſolom</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Dauid,</hi> in his life time did reare a <hi>Pillar:</hi> for he ſaid; <hi>I haue no ſonne to keepe my name in remembrance,</hi> and he called the <hi>Pillar</hi> after his owne name.<note n="n" place="margin">1. Macca. 13.27.28.</note> 
               <hi>Simon</hi> made vpon the Sepulcher of his father and his brethren a building, high to looke vnto
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12373:22"/>
of hewen ſtone behind and before; and ſet vp <hi>ſeauen Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars</hi> vpon it, one againſt another, for his <hi>father, his mother, and foure brethren,</hi> and ſet armes vpon the <hi>Pillars</hi> for a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall memorie.</hi> For this cauſe the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> kings made thoſe ſtately <hi>Pyramids,</hi> and <hi>Obeliskes,</hi> to perpetuate their memorie. <hi>Hercules</hi> alſo erected two <hi>Pillars</hi> vpon two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>montories, the one in <hi>Europe,</hi> the other in <hi>Africa,</hi> as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents and records of his victories. And<note n="o" place="margin">Gel. lib. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Artemiſia,</hi> the Queene of <hi>Caria,</hi> made a Tombe for her husband <hi>Manſolus,</hi> reckoned amongſt the wonders of the world; which was compaſſed about with thirtie ſixe <hi>Pillars,</hi> all which were to preſerue his <hi>Name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, a <hi>Pillar</hi> ſometimes ſignifieth <hi>Preheminence;</hi> as it is in the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galathians:</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Galat. 2.9.</note> And when <hi>Iames</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> and <hi>Iohn, knew of the grace that was giuen vnto me, which are counted to be Pillars; they gaue to me, and to Barnabas the right hands of fellowſhip: that we ſhould preach vnto the Gentiles, and they vnto the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Dexteras Paulo &amp; Barnaba ſocietatis, ſed Tito qui cum eis erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. lib. <hi>1.</hi> in Epiſt. ad Gala.</note> 
               <hi>dexteras non dederunt;</hi> ſaith <hi>Ierom.</hi> They gaue the right hands of fellowſhip to <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; <hi>Barnabas,</hi> but not to <hi>Titus</hi> who was with them, becauſe hee had not attained vnto ſuch meaſure of grace, as was requiſite in the <hi>Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi> Out of this may be confuted our Engliſh <hi>Arians,</hi> which hold that all Miniſters ſhould be equall, and that a <hi>Biſhop</hi> neither is nor ought to be ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to a Prieſt, neither that there is any difference at all betwixt them.<note n="q" place="margin">Hier. ad Euang.</note> We know that <hi>Biſhops</hi> and Prieſts in the Apoſtles time were all one; for thoſe whom the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calleth<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 20.17.</note> 
               <hi>Elders</hi> or <hi>Preſbiters,</hi> he nameth<note n="s" place="margin">Act. 20.28.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers.</hi> Likewiſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> exhorteth the <hi>Presbiters</hi> or <hi>Prieſts</hi> to feed the Flocke, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. That is, <hi>ouerſeeing,</hi> from whence the name of <hi>Epiſcopus</hi> or <hi>Biſhop</hi> is deriued: yet according to the names of honor, which the vſe or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the <hi>Church</hi> hath obtained: a <hi>Biſhop</hi> is greater then a <hi>Prieſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ep. <hi>19.</hi> ad. Hier.</note> ſaith S. <hi>Augustine,</hi> neither is it contrarie to the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12373:22"/>
               <hi>Scripture,</hi> that there ſhould be a <hi>Prioritie</hi> amongſt Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for euen the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> though in reſpect of their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postleſhip</hi> they were al one, yet there was a ſuperioritie and precedencie amongſt them: for the prioritie of ſpeaking was giuen<note n="t" place="margin">Act. 1.15.</note> to <hi>Peter</hi> in the election of <hi>Matthias:</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 15.13.</note> the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſentence is pronounced by <hi>Iames: Paul</hi> is ordained the chief <hi>Apostle</hi> of the <hi>Vncircumciſion,</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter</hi> of the <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion;</hi> and among the Apoſtles themſelues,<note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Iames, Cephas,</hi> &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> are counted <hi>pillars,</hi> which is a title of <hi>Preheminence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, a <hi>Pillar</hi> is the <hi>byeroglyphick</hi> of <hi>Continuance,</hi> God in ſigne of his euerlaſting eſſence,<note n="y" place="margin">Exod. 13.21.</note> 
               <hi>went before the people of Iſrael by day in a Pillar of a clowde to lead them the way, and by night in a Pillar of fire to giue them light, that they might goe both by day and by night: Chriſt</hi> in token of his <hi>aeternal Deitie,</hi> is ſaid in the Canticles of <hi>Salomon,</hi> to <hi>haue</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Cant. 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>legges like Marble pillars, ſet on ſockets of Gold.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which by <hi>Salomon</hi> is called the<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 9.1.</note> 
               <hi>Houſe of Wiſedom,</hi> is ſaid to be built vpon ſeauen <hi>pillars,</hi> that is to ſay it hath a <hi>firme</hi> &amp; <hi>ſolid foundation;</hi> for <hi>numerus ſeptenarius perfectione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſignificat,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Augustine; the ſeuen-fold num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſignifieth perfection:</hi> whereupon the <hi>Lambe</hi> of God, our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> is ſaid to haue<note n="b" place="margin">Apoc. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſeuen hornes &amp; ſeuen eies;</hi> by which are intimated <hi>his abſolute power,</hi> &amp; <hi>perfect knowledge.</hi> In that <hi>Chriſt</hi> then ſaith; <hi>Hee will make him that ouercommeth a Pillar,</hi> you muſt note, that his <hi>Meaning</hi> is this: <hi>his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance in righteouſneſſe ſhall be had in euerlasting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance: his glory ſhall be greater then of the ordinarie ſort of the elect, and his happineſſe in heauen ſhall abide and continue for euer: for he ſhall be made a Pillar in the Temple of God, and he ſhal go no more out.</hi> In theſe words our <hi>Sauiour</hi> alludes vnto the two<note n="c" place="margin">1. Reg. 7.21.</note> 
               <hi>Great braſen Pillars,</hi> which King <hi>Salomon</hi> made &amp; ſet vp in the Porch of the <hi>Temple;</hi> calling the name of the one <hi>Iachin,</hi> &amp; of the other <hi>Boaz:</hi> the firſt of which is by interpretation; <hi>He will eſtabliſh:</hi> and the ſecond ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth <hi>ſtrength:</hi> as if he ſhould haue ſaid, <hi>God will performe his promiſe towards this houſe, and the power and glory of it ſhall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12373:23"/>
continue for euer.</hi> And ſo will <hi>Chriſt</hi> deale with them that <hi>ouercome, He</hi> will make them both <hi>Iachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz:</hi> that is to ſay, according to his ſtable and firme promiſe, he will deliuer them from the mouth of the Lions in this life, by breaking their iaw-bones; and in the world to come they ſhall for euer raigne with the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and<note n="d" place="margin">Apoc. 14.4.</note> follow him whither ſoeuer he goeth, and <hi>neuer any more goe out of the Temple.</hi> Hereby we may gather, <hi>that they which once haue receiued a true liuely faith, &amp; are thereby iustified before God, can neuer finally fall away, neither can that faith vtterly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh or faile in them though it may for a time ſomwhat decay, &amp; be empaired, yet ſhall it reuiue, &amp; they be raiſed vp againe.</hi> The Papiſts impugne this doctrine,<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de iuſti. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> teaching <hi>that a man may fall away from the faith which he once truly had, &amp; be depriued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of the ſtate of grace;</hi> becauſe God ſaith:<note n="e" place="margin">Ezech. 18.24</note> 
               <hi>If the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man turne away from his righteouſnes, &amp; commit iniquity, &amp; doe according to all the abhominations, that the wicked man doth, ſhall be liue? all his righteouſnes that he hath done ſhal not be mentioned; but in his tranſgreſſion that he hath committed, &amp; in his ſin that he hath ſinned, in them ſhall he die.</hi> Likewiſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of ſome<note n="f" place="margin">Tim. 1.29.</note> 
               <hi>That they had made ſhip-warck of their faith,</hi> vpon which place the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> conclude, that a man may fall from the faith which he once truly had; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Texts of ſcripture they alledge for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. As that out of S. <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Luke 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>They receiue the word with ioy, but they haue no root, which for a while beleeue, but in the time of tentation go away.</hi> Out of S. <hi>Matthew;</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 24.12.</note> 
               <hi>the loue of many ſhal waxe cold.</hi> And out of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians;</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27.</note> 
               <hi>I do chaſtice my body, leſt when I haue preached to others I ſhuld be a Reprobate.</hi> In making anſwer to theſe obiections, let vs but obſerue the true meaning of theſe words. <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Faith, Loue,</hi> and <hi>Reprobate,</hi> and then this <hi>Gordian knot;</hi> wil with eaſe be looſed. Firſt, wheras the Prophet <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiel</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>fall of a righteous man:</hi> you muſt note that he meaneth ſuch righteous perſons, as to the worlds eye rather <hi>ſeeme</hi> ſo to be, then be <hi>ſo indeed,</hi> &amp; thus S. <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:12373:23"/>
teacheth vs to expound it, who, where as other <hi>Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts</hi> write thus, <hi>From him that hath not ſhall be taken away, euen that which he hath;</hi> hee ſaith,<note n="k" place="margin">Luke 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>that which hee ſeemed to haue:</hi> God taketh away his grace from him that hath it not, but onely ſeemeth to haue it, and giueth ſtill to him that hath: he then that is <hi>hypocritically</hi> righteous, wee grant may fall away finally, but he that is truely <hi>righteous,</hi> and a <hi>Pillar</hi> in the <hi>Temple</hi> of God <hi>ſhall goe no more out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Faith</hi> is either <hi>Viua</hi> or <hi>Mortua, A liuely or a dead faith;</hi> of the <hi>dead faith</hi> there may be made a <hi>ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke,</hi> it was <hi>Iudas</hi> his <hi>caſe: ſuch</hi> a faith is a <hi>reed ſhaken</hi> with euery blaſt of winde, it is a combuſtible ſubſtance like Timber, hay and ſtubble, the leaſt flame of any fire will burne it: but the <hi>Liuely faith</hi> which is euer accompained with a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> like the <hi>Ship</hi> in which our <hi>Sauiour ſlept,</hi> may be toſt and ſhaken with wind and waues, but neuer caſt away, neuer ſwallowed vp in any gulfe, for it is a <hi>houſe</hi> built vpon the rocke, no tempeſtuous guſt can ouer-turne it. It is a well of liuing water ſpringing vp to euerlaſting life, he that drinkes of it ſhall neuer thirſt againe:<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>For hee that beleeueth is already paſſed from death to life,</hi> he is made a <hi>Pillar</hi> in the houſe of God, and <hi>ſhall no more goe out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, as there is a dead faith, ſo there is a <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait Loue,</hi> the one being the <hi>roote,</hi> the other the <hi>branch:</hi> therefore where there is ſuch a <hi>faith, charitie</hi> there muſt needs waxe cold:<note n="m" place="margin">Cant. 8.7.</note> but <hi>true Loue,</hi> by much <hi>water cannot be quenched, neither can the floods drowne it.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">1 Cor. 13.8.</note> 
               <hi>It doth neuer fall away:</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 33. <hi>diſt.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>In quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fuerit haec charitas, radix illi erit, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſcere non potest,</hi> in whom ſoeuer this charitie is, <hi>it ſhall be a roote vnto him, hee cannot wither, but euer flouriſh like</hi> a greene Oliue tree in the court of Gods Temple, neuer to be tranſplanted, neuer <hi>to goe out any more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, this word <hi>Reprobate,</hi> vſually in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſignifieth ſuch a one as is<note n="p" place="margin">Iud. verſ. 4.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>before of old ordained to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation,</hi> &amp; <hi>reiected</hi> or <hi>reproued of God.</hi> But ſometimes it is taken in another ſence, and is all one
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12373:24"/>
with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is <hi>it reproued,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.27.</note> or <hi>reprobate to men,</hi> and ſo doth S. <hi>Paul</hi> vſe it, when hee ſaith; <hi>I chaſtice my body, leſt when I haue preached to others, I ſhould be a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</hi> In this ſpeech the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> doth not feare leſt God ſhould caſt him away, or finally reiect him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the contrary, ſaying:<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 8.38.39.</note> 
               <hi>for I am perſwaded that neither death nor life, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, ſhall be able to ſeperate vs from the loue of God, which is in Christ Ieſus our Lord.</hi> But his meaning is this, leſt if hee preached one thing and practiſed an other, hee might be reproued and reproached of men. No,<note n="s" place="margin">Aug. de cor. &amp; grat. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> he that is <hi>Elect,</hi> and whoſe faith worketh by loue, either neuer <hi>falleth at all,</hi> or if he doe, hee is reuiued and raiſed vp againe before this life be ended: <hi>for hee that is a Pillar</hi> in the <hi>Temple of God, ſhall goe no more out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Him that ouercommeth will I make a Pillar &amp;c.] Vpon this Pillar, Chriſt</hi> promiſeth to write three Names. <hi>The Name of God, the Name of new Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>his owne new Name: And I will write vpon him the Name of my God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pro. 22.1.</note>
               <hi>A good name</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, is to be choſen aboue great riches, it is better then a good oyntment, it fatteth the bones:</hi> What honor was it for <hi>Moſes</hi> to be called <hi>Gods Seruant?</hi> and for <hi>Dauid</hi> to be adorned with this Title, <hi>a man after Gods owne heart? Publius Scipio</hi> did reckon his name <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricanus</hi> amongſt his greateſt glories. And <hi>Paulus Aeme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> thought himſelfe, well ſatisfied for his paines and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in the wars, becauſe the <hi>Romanes</hi> gaue him the name of <hi>Macedonius.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Catal. glor. m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd. part. <hi>11.</hi> conſid. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Honor &amp; decus eſt habere pulchru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nomen:</hi> ſaith <hi>Caſſanaeus, it an honour and glory to haue a faire name;</hi> and therefore <hi>Socrates</hi> wiſhed that <hi>parents</hi> would giue their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſignificant</hi> and wel-ſounding names. Such a name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> our <hi>Sauiour</hi> promiſe to write vpon them that <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e in goodneſſe,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I will write vpon him the name of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God. God</hi> hath diuers names in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſome being deriued from his <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> other from his proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties:
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12373:24"/>
as he is a <hi>Being of himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>an aeternall Eſſence,</hi> hee is called <hi>Iehoua,</hi> of <hi>Haia, to Be:</hi> as he is <hi>mightie, El;</hi> as <hi>holy Cadoſeh;</hi> as <hi>all-ſufficient Schaddai:</hi> but his principall name is <hi>Iehoua: a name of ſuch holineſſe,</hi> that the <hi>Chaldaeans (as Reuchlinus</hi> ſaith) to auoid prophanation, would not write it, but expreſſed it in their Bookes by certaine prickes; and the <hi>Iewes</hi> blinded with a ſuperſtitious conceit, in ſtead thereof vſed <hi>Tetragrammaton, Adonai,</hi> and <hi>Elohim;</hi> this name <hi>ſo holy</hi> ſhall be grauen vpon them that be <hi>pillars</hi> in <hi>Gods Temple.</hi> Whereby <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifieth, that <hi>God</hi> will be their <hi>Iehoua,</hi> and they ſhall be his <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Apoc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.7.</note> hee will be their <hi>God,</hi> and they ſhall be his people. This name is<note n="y" place="margin">Apoc. 7.2.</note> that <hi>Seale</hi> wherewith the ſeruants of <hi>God</hi> are marked in their fore-heads, which who ſo hath, no helliſh<note n="z" place="margin">Apoc. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>Locuſt</hi> can hurt him: this name is like the<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrokes</hi> of blood <hi>vpon</hi> the <hi>postes of the Iſraelites houſes,</hi> no plague nor deſtruction ſhall light vpon them that beare it: this name is like vnto the<note n="b" place="margin">Ioſhua 2.18.</note> 
               <hi>Corde</hi> of red <hi>thread</hi> in <hi>Rahabs</hi> window, it preſerues them that haue it from the <hi>Sword</hi> in the day of <hi>Vengeance.</hi> The <hi>Letters</hi> of his <hi>name Iehoua,</hi> are by the Iewiſh <hi>Rabbins</hi> called, <hi>Literae flatus &amp; literae quietis. Breathing</hi> &amp; <hi>reſting let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</hi> Wherby thus much may be collected; Firſt, as <hi>God is a ſpirit,</hi> ſo he is the <hi>ſole Father</hi> and giuer of life: he will raiſe vp the <hi>Elect</hi> at the laſt day in incorruption, clothing them with <hi>immortalitie,</hi> and beſtowing vpon them life <hi>aeternall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there is no way to finde <hi>Reſt</hi> but in <hi>God</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, hee is like <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke to the tyred and wearied<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>Doue;</hi> hee is that liuing <hi>ſtone</hi> vpon which onely<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 28.11.</note> euery elect <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> muſt lay his head and ſleepe: hee is that<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 13.10.</note> 
               <hi>Altar</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the <hi>Saints</hi> departed repoſe themſelues, reſting from their labours,<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 4.9.</note> and finding <hi>reſt</hi> for their ſoules. And thus by the <hi>writing</hi> of <hi>the Name of God,</hi> three things by <hi>Chriſt</hi> are promiſed: <hi>a heauenly Inheritance, a life aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and a reſt euerlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:12373:25"/>
               <hi>And the name of the Citie of my God which is the new Ieruſalem, which commeth downe out of Heauen, from my God, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it is an honour to haue a <hi>good name,</hi> ſo it is a <hi>glorie</hi> to be of <hi>a famous Nation,</hi> or a <hi>Citizen</hi> of a <hi>famous</hi> Citie. The<note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 4.9.</note> woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> wondered that <hi>Chriſt</hi> being a <hi>Iewe</hi> by birth, would aske drinke of her being a <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan;</hi> for the <hi>Iewes</hi> medled not with the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them as ignoble, in compariſon of themſelues, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked people: as wee may gather by their blaſphemous ſpeech to <hi>Chriſt; Say we not well, thou art a Samaritan and haſt the diuell?</hi> There is a great difference in the <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie</hi> of <hi>Nations. Quaedam gentes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iulius Mater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus) ita a coelo formatae ſunt vt propria ſint morum vnitate conspicuae. Some nations are ſo framed of heauen, that they may be knowne by the proprietie of maners what countrymen they be.</hi> And this varietie commeth from the <hi>diuerſitie</hi> of <hi>Climates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ptolo. <hi>2.</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dripart: Liuius. Apulei. Iul. Maternus.</note> and the influence of the ſtarres. The <hi>Iewes</hi> be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians learned,</hi> the <hi>Syrians co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous,</hi> the <hi>Sicilians acute,</hi> the <hi>Africans craftie,</hi> the <hi>Scythi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans cruel,</hi> the <hi>Grecians vnconſtant,</hi> the <hi>Italians generous,</hi> the <hi>French-men raſh,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards vaine-glorious,</hi> the<note n="h" place="margin">Tit. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Creti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans liers, euill beaſts, ſlow bellies,</hi> the <hi>Germans</hi> and <hi>Brittanes valiant.</hi> Theſe ſtampes of nature being conſidered we may conclude, that it is farre more honourable for a man to be of one Nation or one Citie then another. Our <hi>Sauiour Chriſt,</hi> then becauſe he would demonſtrate the <hi>Glory</hi> of the <hi>Elect:</hi> ſaith that he <hi>will write vpon them the Name of the Citie of Ieruſalem:</hi> hee will enfranchiſe and make them free of a famous <hi>Citie:</hi> but wee muſt not looke for this <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in <hi>Iudaea;</hi> no, for of that <hi>Citie,</hi> not one ſtone is left vpon another, but we muſt caſt our eyes vpwards,<note n="i" place="margin">Apoc. 21.2.</note> 
               <hi>For it comes downe from God, out of heauen, prepared as a Bride trimmed for her huſband.</hi> The old <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was a type of the <hi>Church Millitant,</hi> this <hi>New Ieruſalem</hi> is a figure of the <hi>Church tryumphant:</hi> the <hi>Old</hi> was often beſieged and ſackt;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12373:25"/>
a ſhaddow of the afflictions of the <hi>Elect</hi> here vpon earth; the <hi>New</hi> is ſaid to be garniſhed with twelue ſeuerall preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones,<note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 21.19.20.</note> the <hi>Iasper,</hi> the <hi>Saphire,</hi> the <hi>Chalcedonie,</hi> the <hi>Emerald,</hi> the <hi>Sardonyx,</hi> the <hi>Sardius,</hi> the <hi>Chryſolite,</hi> the <hi>Beril,</hi> the <hi>Topaze,</hi> the <hi>Chryſopraſus,</hi> the <hi>Iacinth,</hi> and the <hi>Amethyst:</hi> by which are ſignified the glorious endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the <hi>Elect</hi> in heauen. In the number of <hi>twelue,</hi> there be foure <hi>Triplicities,</hi> and this Citie being foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare, the precious ſtones like thoſe in<note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 28.17.</note> 
               <hi>Aarons Breaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate,</hi> are ſet three &amp; three in a ſquare: by which foure <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicities,</hi> foure things may be vnderſtood, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre &amp; meet together to make the <hi>Elect</hi> moſt glorious.</p>
            <p>The firſt, is the <hi>Glorification of the body;</hi> the qualifie and ſtate whereof may fitly be reſembled by the three ſtones of the firſt <hi>Triplicitie;</hi> namely the <hi>Iasper,</hi> the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire,</hi> and the <hi>Chalcedonie.</hi> Firſt, the <hi>Iasper</hi> is greene, and being worne diſpelleth all <hi>Phantaſmes;</hi> and driueth away euill ſpirits, (ſaith <hi>Iſodore:</hi>) the healthfull ſtate of our bodies after the reſurrection, ſhal paralele this <hi>Iasper,</hi> they ſhall be like greene Oliue trees, neuer withering, neuer fading; here while wee liue <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> the <hi>Purſeuants</hi> of death, are euer like <hi>Sauls</hi> euill ſpirits, at our elbowes haunting vs: <hi>Dauid</hi> had the ſtone, <hi>for his reines chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him in the night ſeaſon; Iob</hi> his boiles and botches; <hi>Miriam</hi> her leproſie, and euen the moſt righteous haue their infirmities: but at the laſt day our bodies ſhall be ſo changed that ſickneſſe ſhall exerciſe no tyranny ouer vs. Secondly, the <hi>Saphire,</hi> is <hi>hard</hi> and <hi>blew,</hi> of the colour of heauen, it killes the Spider, and driueth away poiſonous ſerpents: ſuch like ſhall our <hi>bodies</hi> be, <hi>heauenly and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull,</hi> no <hi>deformitie</hi> ſhal come neere to blemiſh them;<note n="m" place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>for Chriſt ſhall change our vile bodie, that it may be faſhioned like vnto his glorious body, according to the working, wherby he is able euen to ſubdue al things to himſelf.</hi> Thirdly, the <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dony is ſo hard that no toole of yron can graue it:</hi> euen ſo, thogh now <hi>Sathan</hi> workes vs like <hi>waxe,</hi> and makes vs receiue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12373:26"/>
his marke, by tempting and alluring vs to giue our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſeruants to vncleanneſſe, yet then our bodies ſhall be purified; we ſhall tread vpon the <hi>Lyon</hi> and the <hi>Dragon:</hi> the diuell ſhall haue no more any power to make our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies his Synagogue: for they ſhall be the aeternall Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the <hi>holy Ghoſt.</hi> The <hi>ſecond thine is, the Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Soule;</hi> the condition whereof we ſhall ſee in the three ſtones of the ſecond <hi>Triplicitie;</hi> to wit, <hi>the Eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauld, the Sardonyx, &amp; the Sardius.</hi> Firſt, the <hi>Emerauld</hi> is in colour <hi>Greene, delightſome to looke on,</hi> and very ſoueraigne againſt the <hi>falling Sickneſſe:</hi> like vnto this precious ſtone ſhall the <hi>ſoules</hi> of the <hi>Elect</hi> be made, <hi>all glorious within, and full of grace,</hi> being ſo confirmed in <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> that whereas now the moſt <hi>iust man</hi> hath the <hi>falling ſickneſſe</hi> ſeauen times a day, then <hi>Sin ſhall haue no more dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Sardonyx</hi> is of three colours, it is <hi>Niger in imo, candidus in medio, rubicundus in ſupremo;</hi> the lower part of it is <hi>blacke,</hi> the <hi>middle white,</hi> the <hi>top</hi> of it <hi>red:</hi> ſo our <hi>Soules</hi> ſhall be <hi>Nigrae in imo,</hi> blacke below, for they ſhall contemne the malicious diſſeignes and ſtratagems of the diuell, and ſmile in ſcorne at the deſtruction of him and his angels. They ſhall be <hi>Candidae in medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> white in the midſt, being clothed like the Lillies of the field, in long white robes of righteouſneſſe; laſtly, they ſhall be <hi>in Supremo rubicundae, Red aboue,</hi> that is to ſay <hi>all glorious,</hi> in regard of the golden crowne of immortalitie. Thirdly, the <hi>Sardius</hi> is a <hi>red stone,</hi> and the vertue of it is, to driue away timorouſneſſe and feare; this ſhewes our <hi>future boldneſſe</hi> and <hi>confidence:</hi> here vpon earth wee work our ſaluation in <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>trembling;</hi> but hereafter we ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach boldly vnto the throne of God, with <hi>Palmes</hi> in our hands in ſigne of victorie, hauing waſht our long white <hi>robes</hi> in the blood of the <hi>Lambe.</hi> The <hi>third thing is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of Charitie,</hi> the attributes whereof be three: for <hi>Charitie</hi> muſt be <hi>pure, good and true:</hi> theſe three, are ſet forth, by three ſtones in the <hi>third Triplicitie.</hi> Firſt, the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12373:26"/>
               <hi>Chryſolite</hi> is of a golden colour; whereupon it hath that name, it ſparkleth, and being laid before the <hi>fire,</hi> wil quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be inflamed &amp; burne. This ſtone is an Embleme of our pure <hi>loue</hi> towards God the <hi>Father;</hi> whoſe preſence, when we behold him face to face, ſhall be ſo attractiue, that our hearts ſhall be ſet on fire with his loue. Secondly, the <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill</hi> is greene, &amp; hath power to procure <hi>Loue;</hi> this ſtone is the Embleme of that <hi>good loue,</hi> which ſhall be betwixt God the <hi>Sonne</hi> and vs: who loued vs firſt, and was incarnate, and we then ſhall loue him moſt dearely, being incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated and made fellow heires with him. Thirdly, the <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paze</hi> is yellowiſh, reſembling the Sun-beames, and it is an Embleme of our true loue towardes God the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which like the beames of the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſhall euer ſhine, and whoſe <hi>heare</hi> ſhall neuer be quenched, neuer extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. The <hi>fourth thing is the perfection of Iustice,</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the three ſtones in the fourth <hi>Triplicitie. Iustitia est virtus,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe) ſuum cui<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tribuens: Iustice is a vertue that giues euery one his due: to euery one of vs that hath it, it imparts Continencie; to our neighbour friendſhip; and to God honour.</hi> Which three are diſcribed by the <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopraſus, the Iacinth, and the Amethyſt.</hi> Firſt, the <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praſus in the night ſhines like fire, in the day like golde.</hi> In it behold our future perfection in <hi>Continencie</hi> and <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance,</hi> wee are now <hi>fraile</hi> and vnſtable; our <hi>paſſions</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> are euer changing; in the <hi>day-time</hi> of proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie wee ſhine like gold, wee <hi>reioyce</hi> in the <hi>Lord,</hi> and magnifie his holy Name; but in the <hi>Night</hi> of aduerſitie, we are of<note n="n" place="margin">Iob. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>Iobs</hi> Wiues minde, who counſailed her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to curſe God and die. But in the world to come, we ſhal be <hi>Et ignei; &amp; aurei, vel tanquam aurum probatum in igne: Like gold tryed in the fire,</hi> purged of all our <hi>droſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie paſſions</hi> and <hi>earthy</hi> affections. So abſolutely <hi>Continent,</hi> that if wee were lyable to Croſſes, yet ſhould no Croſſe croſſe vs. Secondly, the <hi>Iacinth</hi> euer ſuites it ſelfe to the temperature of the Aire; if the aire be cleare, it is bright; if
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12373:27"/>
the aire be dimme, it is darke. Such like hereafter ſhall our <hi>dispoſition</hi> be altogether <hi>harmonicall: Might</hi> there be in <hi>Heauen</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Eccle. 3.4.</note> 
               <hi>a time to weepe, and a time to laugh, a time to mourne, and a time to dance, wee ſhould mourne with them that weepe, and laugh with them that daunce,</hi> ſuch ſhould be the <hi>Symphathie</hi> of the <hi>Elect.</hi> Here vpon earth it is quite contrarie, <hi>Wee weep with them that laugh, and laugh with them that weepe;</hi> one enuies at anothers proſperitie, and reioyceth at anothers miſerie and affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saith the <hi>Poet; One Tyler enuies</hi> an other: <hi>One Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> another; <hi>one Muſitian</hi> an other, <hi>one Beggar</hi> another: and one <hi>Courtyer</hi> an other: but marke our alteration, the ayre at the laſt day ſhall be purged, and it will euer be faire and cleare weather: all <hi>grudging</hi> and enuie ſhall be baniſhed, and we ſhall for euer be linked together in bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue and friendſhip. Thirdly, the <hi>Amethyſt</hi> is of a purple colour, and ſparkles like the fire: <hi>a fit figure</hi> of that due honour which the zealous Elect in heauen ſhall giue to God for euer: whilſt we are clothed with this <hi>fleſh,</hi> euen the moſt righteous man is luke-warme in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: but when this <hi>Corruption</hi> ſhall haue put on incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <hi>We ſhall ſtand vp like fire, and our words ſhall burne like a Lampe,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Apoc. 19.1.</note> euer ſinging and ſaying; <hi>Hallelu-iah, Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> and <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>power be to the Lord our God.</hi> And thus by the <hi>foure Triplicities</hi> of precious ſtones, in the wall of the Citie of new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> whoſe name <hi>Chriſt</hi> heere promiſeth to write vpon them that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come; are ſignified the foure heauenly indowments of the <hi>Elect:</hi> namely, the <hi>Glorification</hi> of the bodie, the <hi>Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the Soule, the <hi>Conſummation</hi> of Charitie, and the <hi>perfection</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> all which proceed from<note n="q" place="margin">Rom. 9.16.</note> the <hi>free grace of God;</hi> no deſert or merit in our ſelues. And thus much may be proued, by the <hi>Comming downe of this holy Citie out of heauen from God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I will write vpon him my new Name.]</hi> In the <hi>Epiſtle</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:12373:27"/>
of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to the Angel of the <hi>Church of Pergamus, He</hi> promiſeth to giue them that ouercome a<note n="r" place="margin">Apoc. 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>white ſtone, and in that ſtone a new name written:</hi> and here he ſaith, that he will write <hi>vpon him that ouercommeth his owne new name.</hi> In the firſt place hee alludeth vnto the cuſtome of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> by <hi>white</hi> and <hi>blacke stones,</hi> ſhaddowing in that figuratiue ſpeech, the myſterie of our <hi>Election,</hi> and the<note n="s" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 8.18.</hi> Bern. ſer. <hi>2.</hi> in die Penticoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Seale</hi> of Gods Spirit, whereby wee both know and are aſſured of our <hi>Saluation.</hi> In the ſecond place, he hath reference to an vſe which was amongſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting <hi>Statues, Pillars,</hi> and <hi>Arches,</hi> in honour of their <hi>Men of valour</hi> and <hi>Conquerours;</hi> vpon which were ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen their worthy Exploits. Hereby declaring the great glory that ſhall be beſtowed vpon ſuch as <hi>perſeuere in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, defend the truth, and ſubdue feare.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Phil. 2.8.9.</note> Our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) becauſe hee humbled <hi>himſelfe and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came obedient vnto the death, euen the death of the Croſſe; is highly exalted by GOD, and hath a name giuen him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue euery name.</hi> Hereby is ſignified, that God the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> hath giuen vnto <hi>him</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Dan. 7.14.</note> 
               <hi>Dominion and Honour, and a Kingdome, that all people, Nations, and Languages ſhould ſerue him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Glorious</hi> name will <hi>Chriſt</hi> write vpon <hi>his ſeruants,</hi> ſetting them at his right hand in the heauenly places, farre aboue all Principalitie, and Power and might, and Domination, and euery name that is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in this World: <hi>Shall</hi> then ſuch as be conſtant and courageous be <hi>made Pillars</hi> in Gods houſe, hauing writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vpon them <hi>the Name of God, the Name of new Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> and <hi>Chriſts new Name,</hi> titles aeternall and truely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? O then who would not (by their godly life) ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ambitious of this glorie? What a huge tower did <hi>Nimrod</hi> build to get him a name? <hi>Themistocles</hi> vſed to walke vp and downe ſolitarily in the night, and one aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him the cauſe, hee anſwered; <hi>The Trophies</hi> and <hi>fame</hi> of <hi>Milciades</hi> awake <hi>me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:12373:28"/>Let then the glorious memorie of <hi>Dauid, Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiah,</hi> and <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> ſtirre vp all earthly <hi>Arch-angels</hi> to walke before God with vp-right hearts. Let the <hi>fame</hi> of <hi>Auguſtine, Ambroſe, Baſile, Athanaſius,</hi> and the reſt of the ancient learned <hi>Biſhops,</hi> moue all our <hi>Cherubims</hi> and <hi>Seraphims</hi> terreſtriall, to be induſtrious and painefull in Gods harueſt. And laſtly, let the Example of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who was neuer idle in his Miniſterie: being as <hi>Ierom</hi> ſtiles him;<note place="margin">Hier ad Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</note> 
               <hi>Vas electionis, tuba Euangelij, rugitus Leonis nostri<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; flumen eloquentia Christianae: A choſen veſſel, the trumpet of the Gospel, the roaring of our Lion, and ſtreame of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian eloquence,</hi> be a motiue to perſwade all <hi>Miniſtering Angels,</hi> in <hi>ſeaſon</hi> and out of <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> to preach the glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome tydings of aeternall life; that all of them at the laſt may be made <hi>Pillars</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> To whom with the Sonne and the holy Spirit, be aſcribed all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie both now and euer-more. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:12373:28"/>
            <head>The third Sermon. <hi>THE BANISHMENT</hi> OF DOGGES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Apoc. cap. 22. Verſ. 15.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For without ſhall be Dogges.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>foure Ages</hi> of the World, and the foure <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> are reſembled by<note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 2.32.33.</note> foure <hi>Mettals; Gold, Siluer, Braſſe,</hi> and <hi>Iron:</hi> the firſt <hi>Age</hi> and <hi>Monarchie</hi> were both <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den;</hi> the <hi>Second</hi> worſe then the firſt, like <hi>Siluer;</hi> the <hi>third Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen;</hi> and the <hi>fourth Iron.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eccles. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Thus to all things, there is an appointed time, and a time to euery purpoſe vnder Heauen;</hi> a time of Doue-like innocencie, and a time of <hi>Serpent-like</hi> ſubtiltie; a time of ſecret crueltie, and a time of open <hi>Tyrannie.</hi> Now as it hath beene heretofore in the <hi>Ages,</hi> and <hi>Monarchies</hi> of the world, ſo likewiſe haue we ſeene a chaunge and alteration in the ſtate of <hi>Christianitie,</hi> of it there haue beene foure ſeuerall <hi>Ages:</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> was the <hi>Lambe-age,</hi> in this liued<note n="c" place="margin">Ioh. 1.36.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt the Lambe of God,</hi> and the <hi>bleſſed</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Apoc. 14.4.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins that followed him whither ſoeuer he went,</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:12373:29"/>
the <hi>holy Apostles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples which were not defiled with women,</hi> but kept themſelues chaſte and cleane, both from carnall contagion, and ſpirituall whoredome.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> was the<note n="e" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Foxe-age: when the myſterie of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie began to worke</hi> by the meanes and agencie of <hi>Haeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> who like <hi>little</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Cant. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>Foxes ſought to destroy the Vine, which our Sauiour had planted with his owne right hand:</hi> Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Simon Magus, Cerinthus, Menander,</hi> the <hi>Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and many other of the ſame Leauen: who though they did diſagree in opinion amongſt themſelues, hauing like <hi>Samſons</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iudg. 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Foxes,</hi> their heads ſeperated and diſioyned, yet were they tyed together by the Tailes: for euery ones aime and inuention was with the <hi>fire-brand</hi> of <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> to make hauocke of <hi>Chriſts harueſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third,</hi> was the <hi>Wolfe-age;</hi> our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee this time, and therefore he ſaith to his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and in them to all true Beleeuers.<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, I ſend you forth like Sheepe among Wolues;</hi> theſe <hi>Wolues</hi> were cruell <hi>Tyrants,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Nero, Caligula, Domitian</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Emperours:</hi> all which were<note n="i" place="margin">Zeph. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>like Wolues in the Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, that leaue not the bones till the Morrow;</hi> being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame rauenous and greedie of <hi>Christian</hi> blood.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> is the <hi>Dog-age,</hi> and that is this wherein wee liue, and therefore my <hi>Text</hi> is ſutable to the <hi>Time.</hi> The <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> call onely thoſe fortie dayes the <hi>Dog-dayes,</hi> wherein that <hi>Constellation,</hi> called the <hi>Dogge,</hi> meeting with the <hi>Sunne</hi> in our <hi>Meridian</hi> doubleth his heate; by whoſe influence, burning agues, frenzies, and ſuch like hote diſeaſes are bred in mans bodie: but I am of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie opinion, euen euery day is now a <hi>Dogge-day:</hi> for that ſpiritual <hi>Dog</hi> the <hi>Diuell,</hi> is continually in our Zenith, (being<note n="k" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>Prince of this world, that ruleth in the ayre &amp; in the children of diſobedience</hi>) and by his powerfull temptations makes vs euen runne madde with deſire of <hi>Sinning;</hi> ſo that I may confidently ſay, that that curſe is light vpon vs, which <hi>Moſes</hi> proclaimed againſt the obſtinate <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites,</hi>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:12373:29"/>
ſaying;<note n="l" place="margin">Deu. 28.28.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord ſhall ſmite thee with madneſſe and with blindneſſe, and with aſtonying of heart.</hi> I might I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe haue done better to haue choſen a Text more plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and of a ſweeter relliſh in the eare; but in this ſeruice euery man muſt doe as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did in their Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions to the building of the <hi>Tabernacle,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 35.23.</note> 
               <hi>They that were rich</hi> brought <hi>Gold, Pearles,</hi> and <hi>precious ſtones,</hi> but the poorer ſort a <hi>Ramskin</hi> or a little <hi>Goates haire;</hi> ſo I, (for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe in reſpect of knowledge I will ranke my ſelfe) for want of a better preſent will vncaſe a Dogge, and <hi>offer</hi> vp his <hi>skin,</hi> take it in good part it is the widdowes mite; let the greatneſſe of my good will counteruaile the weakeneſſe of my performance; yet will I not leaue my Text without an Apologie, whereunto ſhall I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare it? <hi>It</hi> is like the <hi>Image</hi> of <hi>Selinus,</hi> which outwardly was onely rough hewen, being neither curiouſly carued, nor gorgeouſly ouer-guilt, but there was a window in the breſt thereof, which being opened, his <hi>golden heart</hi> might be diſcouered, &amp; his rich intrailes: ſo here: though the words be harſh and vnſauorie, yet if you looke into them with a ſpirituall eie you ſhall finde <hi>Sathans ſubtilties diſcloſed, Sinne vnmask't,</hi> and <hi>Hell diſcribed.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>For without ſhall be Dogges.</q>
            <p>Theſe words are like the <hi>Angels</hi> great<note n="n" place="margin">Apo. 20.1.</note> 
               <hi>Chaine,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in both the <hi>Deuill</hi> and his followers are <hi>faſt bound</hi> and <hi>fettered,</hi> the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkes</hi> whereof be three, ariſing naturally out of the words of the <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Transformation, A Detestation, A Separation.</head>
               <p>Firſt, a <hi>Transformation:</hi> for the wicked are here called by the name of a <hi>Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, a <hi>Deteſtation:</hi> for <hi>Reprobates</hi> are named <hi>Dogges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, a <hi>Separation:</hi> for the righteous ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Citie of God, but the <hi>Vngodly</hi> ſhall be without.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:12373:30"/>
                  <head>The Transformation.</head>
                  <p>Wee read in the Scriptures of two kindes of <hi>Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations;</hi> the firſt <hi>Corporall,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Spirituall:</hi> The <hi>Corporall</hi> is when the bodie is changed from his ſhape, putting on a new forme: ſuch was that of <hi>Lots</hi> wife, who contrarie to the commandement of the <hi>Angel, Looking backe became a pillar of Salt. Aben Ezra</hi> flying from the letter of the <hi>Text,</hi> denyeth this <hi>Transformation,</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſhee was onely conſumed with a fierie ſhower compounded of <hi>Salt</hi> and <hi>Sulphur;</hi> but not onely the words auouch this <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> but <hi>alſo</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">
                        <list>
                           <item>Thrag. in gen <hi>19.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Hieroſol. in gen <hi>19.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Rab. in gen <hi>19.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Kimbi. in gen <hi>19.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
Ioſeph. lib. <hi>1.</hi> antiq. Vatablu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> authoritie ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry authenticke affirmes the like. Such likewiſe for the time was that <hi>Transfiguration</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Luke 9.25.</note> 
                     <hi>The faſhion of whoſe countenance as be prayed was changed, and his garment was white and glistered.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Spirituall Transformation</hi> is, when the <hi>Will,</hi> the <hi>Minde,</hi> and the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding,</hi> are <hi>changed</hi> and <hi>corrupted:</hi> The firſt creature that was thus <hi>Transformed</hi> was the <hi>Diuell,</hi> who was once<note n="q" place="margin">Eſai. 14.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the ſonne of the <hi>Morning:</hi> and <hi>an</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Ezech. 28.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Annointed Cherub, walking in the middeſt of the ſtones of fire:</hi> that is, ſaith <hi>Gregorie; In aliorum comparatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne caeteris clarior fuit: In compariſon hee was more excellent then the reſt of the heauenly Spirits, till Schiſme or Faction,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding <hi>Pride, Malice,</hi> and <hi>Lying; caſt</hi> him and his <hi>Adhae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents from heauen to Hell, and transformed</hi> him into a <hi>Lyon,</hi> a <hi>Serpent,</hi> and a <hi>Dragon;</hi> for ſo is he ſtiled in the Scriptures not that he bears the materiall forme of any of theſe three <hi>Beaſtes: for being a Spirit hee hath neither fleſh nor bones,</hi> but becauſe hee reſembleth them in qualitie &amp; diſpoſition; as the<note n="s" place="margin">Gen. 3.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Serpent</hi> he is <hi>ſubtile</hi> in his <hi>temptations:</hi> as the<note n="t" place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Lyon hee goeth vp and downe roaring and compaſſing the earth, ſeeking whom hee may deuoure:</hi> and as <hi>the</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc. 12.9.</hi> And Caeſar in Apoc cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Dragon hee is quicke in ſight, and is altogether delighted in Blood and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> hauing thus by ſinne loſt his firſt ſhape, his whole courſe was afterwards to procure ſome Aſſociates in his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12373:30"/>
                     <hi>Metamorphoſis,</hi> therefore when <hi>God</hi> had created <hi>Man,</hi> according to his owne <hi>Image</hi> in<note n="x" place="margin">Epheſ 4.24.</note> 
                     <hi>righteouſnes</hi> and <hi>true holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> he aſſailed the firſt woman <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ah,</hi> and by her as his inſtrument, the firſt <hi>Man Adam,</hi> tempting them both, and they both conſented to eate of the forbidden fruite, miſled and blinded by this bewitching baite of Ambition:<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 3.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Eritis ſicut Dij, You ſhall be as gods, knowing good and euil.</hi> Through this their <hi>diſloialtie,</hi> and diſobedience, that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Image</hi> wherewith God had deck't man, was cancel'd and defaced, not onely in themſelues but in all their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie; ſo ſaith the <hi>Apostle:</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> 
                     <hi>As by one man ſinne entered into the world, and by ſinne death, ſo death entered vpon all men, in that all men haue ſinned;</hi> by <hi>Originall ſinne</hi> then, which is <hi>Corruption</hi> ingendred in our firſt <hi>Conception,</hi> whereby euery facultie both of bodie and ſoule is prone and diſpoſed to iniquitie, whole <hi>Mankind</hi> is <hi>transformed</hi> and changed from good to euill; wee haue loſt our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, our righteouſneſſe, and our immortalitie, and draw now nothing from the loynes of our parents, but<note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Ignorance, Impotencie of minde; Vanitie,</hi> and an inbred and natural inclination to conceiue and deuiſe ſuch things as are euill: yet here is not the period and ſtint of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> malice; he knowes that <hi>Man</hi> is <hi>deformed by Original ſinne,</hi> but <hi>Actuall ſinne muſt</hi> abſolutely <hi>transforme</hi> him, therefore marke his <hi>Plot,</hi> and obſerue his <hi>Practiſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As God obſerued a Methode in <hi>Mans creation,</hi> ſo the <hi>Diuell</hi> hath his <hi>paſſages</hi> and order in his <hi>transformation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God firſt ſaid,<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> 
                     <hi>Let vs make Man:</hi> the bleſſed <hi>Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> went to councell, and this <hi>Conſultation</hi> proueth <hi>Mans</hi> excellencie aboue all other creatures whatſoeuer, for in the reſt God onely had his <hi>Fiat,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> 
                     <hi>Let there be light, and there was light;</hi> but in <hi>Man</hi> hee had his <hi>Faciamus, Let vs make man:</hi> as if hee ſhould haue ſaid,<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 1.28.</note> 
                     <hi>The King of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to rule ouer the fiſh of the ſea, and ouer the fowles of the heauen, and ouer euery beaſt that moueth vpon the earth:</hi> euen ſo <hi>Sathan</hi> on the contrary part conſults, and takes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12373:31"/>
councell with himſelfe and his <hi>Angels</hi> of darkneſſe in the <hi>vnmasking</hi> and <hi>transforming</hi> of man: <hi>Let vs change man</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Diuell</hi>) and <hi>let vs vtterly depriue him of the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Gods Image:</hi> for hereby ſhall he be made like vnto the beaſts that periſh. This is our Aduerſaries plot, but the execution thereof is hindered, becauſe hee is not as God onely is, <hi>the Searcher of our reines,</hi> and the <hi>Knower</hi> of our thoughts; wherefore he plaies the Politician to diſcouer our corrupt imagination and ſiftes vs <hi>by the Concupiſcence of the Eie, the concupiſcence of the hart; and the pride of Life:</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.16.</note> for theſe three are the <hi>Rootes</hi> from which all other <hi>ſinnes</hi> are braunch't and take their growth.</p>
                  <p>If therefore the Diuell ſpie either <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>Woman</hi> walke like the<note n="f" place="margin">Eſay. 3.16.</note> daughters of <hi>Zion, with a wandering eye,</hi> hee preſently makes this poſition; <hi>Out of the aboundance of the heart the eye lookes and theſe glaunces are ſhafts drawen out of the Quiuer of wantonneſſe,</hi> wherefore forthwith hee accommodates and applyes himſelfe herein to <hi>Mans</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt appetite:<note n="g" place="margin">Numb. 25.</note> if hee be a <hi>Zimri</hi> he will prouide him a <hi>Coſbi;</hi> if a<note n="h" place="margin">Iudg. 16.1.9.</note> 
                     <hi>Sampſon</hi> a <hi>Dalilah;</hi> if a <hi>Herode an Herodias,</hi> who ſhall like<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 39.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Potiphars</hi> wife catch him by the garment; ſaying: <hi>Lye with me, ſleep with me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, as the<note n="k" place="margin">Iudg. 12.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Ephramits</hi> were knowen from the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liadites</hi> by the pronouncing of <hi>Shibboleth;</hi> and the <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeans</hi> from the <hi>Iewes,</hi> by their phraſe and <hi>Idiome</hi> of ſpeech: euen ſo the diuell by the tongue of <hi>Man</hi> diſcries the <hi>Concupiſcence</hi> of the heart, and the <hi>Sinne</hi> to which hee is moſt deuoted; wiſh but for <hi>Nabaoths</hi> vineyard as<note n="l" place="margin">1 Reg. 21.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Ahab</hi> did; or but ſay with<note n="m" place="margin">Math. 26.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Iudas, What will you giue?</hi> and hee will ſay preſently thou art couetous, <hi>thy very ſpeech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraies thee:</hi> then will he ſet vp his two golden <hi>Calues,</hi> the worlds <hi>Idole, Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer,</hi> and make proclamation; ſaying, <hi>Theſe are thy gods in whom thou moſt truſt,</hi> and <hi>Mammon</hi> is thy <hi>Mediatour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, if the deuill ſee an <hi>Eare</hi> like<note n="n" place="margin">Hoſea. 12.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Ephraims, fed</hi> with wind, <hi>Soothing</hi> and flatterie, or doe but diſcouer the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12373:31"/>
very feet to tread an elaborate and curious pace, as the women of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> did<note n="o" place="margin">Eſay. 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>who minced as they went and made a tincking with their feet,</hi> hee forthwith apprehends an inclination to <hi>Pride</hi> (for theſe are but the inſtruments of a vaine-glorious minde:) whereupon bee ſuites ſuch perſons with the attendants of flatterers; ſo hee dealt with <hi>Ahab</hi> the king of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> preferring to his ſeruice<note n="p" place="margin">1 Reg. 21.</note> 
                     <hi>Zed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> the falſe prophet, whoſe words were euer plauſible and pleaſant; and ſo hee did with <hi>Herod,</hi> to whom hee put a troupe of Paraſites to puffe him vp with their accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, ſaying;<note n="q" place="margin">Act. 12.22.</note> the <hi>Voyce of God and not of man; Flattery</hi> is <hi>Sathans trappe</hi> for Potentates, the Page of great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages, and a diſeaſe that haunts Princes, it procures grace and countenance, but <hi>Trueth</hi> is euer <hi>diſgraced</hi> and frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vpon. <hi>Flatterie</hi> is alwayes well-liking like the fat Bulles of <hi>Baſan,</hi> but <hi>Trueth</hi> may be reſembled by one of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> leane <hi>Kine,</hi> for it ſtraues and pines away, and yet the one <hi>is ſtrong and raigneth for euermore,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is as <hi>Diogenianus</hi> ſaith; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of ſweet but deadly wine: and a poiſon drunke in a Cuppe of Gold.</p>
                  <p>Hauing thus ſifted our nature, hee turneth Practicio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſaying as God ſaid; <hi>Let vs make man according to our owne Image.</hi> Now when God made <hi>Man,</hi> hee made him of the <hi>Duſt</hi> of the ground, and breathed in his face the breath of life, and created him in his owns <hi>Image:</hi> ſo the diuell when he <hi>transformes Man,</hi> vſeth our <hi>Adamah</hi> or <hi>Duſt;</hi> that is, our old <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>Naturall corruption,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it the matteriall or ground of our <hi>Transformation.</hi> Secondly, he breaths into <hi>Man</hi> not the <hi>breath of Life,</hi> but the <hi>breath</hi> of death, <hi>For the wages of ſinne is death:</hi> his <hi>breathing</hi> is his tempting, for thereby hee enters into a <hi>Man,</hi> as hee entred into <hi>Iudas,</hi> and before he can finiſh his malicious diſſeigne, hee <hi>breatheth</hi> foure times.</p>
                  <p>By the firſt <hi>breath,</hi> hee with-drawes the minde from Gods ſeruice, to which it ſhould be euer zelouſly deuoted
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12373:32"/>
for ſo ſaith our <hi>Sauiour;</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Luke 10.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and all thy ſoule, and with all thy thought.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the ſecond, he drawes the euil thought of the hart to a <hi>Conſent in ſinning,</hi> by ſweet baites and allurements, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the <hi>Will</hi> and the <hi>Affections</hi> are delighted, bewitched, and captiuated.</p>
                  <p>By the third <hi>Breathing, Sinne</hi> is <hi>Conceiued:</hi> ſo ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
                     <note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 7.14.</note> 
                     <hi>He ſhall trauaile with wickedneſſe, hee hath conceiued miſchiefe, and he ſhall bring forth a lie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And by the Fourth, <hi>Sinne</hi> is borne; the <hi>birth</hi> of <hi>ſinne</hi> is, when by aſſiſtance both of the faculties of the Soule, and the powers of the body <hi>ſinne</hi> is committed: thus as by the <hi>breath of God, Man</hi> was made <hi>a liuing ſoule;</hi> ſo on the contrarie part by the <hi>Breath</hi> of <hi>Sathan,</hi> he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes liable to euerlaſting perdition being ſeperated from the preſence of God, and the glorie of his power. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, as God did adorne man in his <hi>Creation,</hi> with his owne image, to wit, <hi>Diuine wiſedome,</hi> and <hi>perfect holineſſe:</hi> ſo the deuill in <hi>Mans transformation,</hi> frameth him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his owne ſhape, which is directly contrary to that of <hi>God,</hi> for it conſiſteth in <hi>folly and vanitie;</hi> hence it is, that all <hi>ſinners</hi> are <hi>fooles:</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> 
                     <hi>for they ſay in their heart there is no God,</hi> and in the whole courſe of their life, they are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her lighter then vanitie it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, though <hi>Man</hi> being <hi>Created</hi> was made a liuing <hi>Soule,</hi> and decked with Gods owne <hi>Image,</hi> yet was it not <hi>compleat</hi> and perfect till the woman alſo was created: <hi>So</hi> though by actuall ſinne <hi>Sathan</hi> hath <hi>transformed vs,</hi> and caſt vs in his owne mould, yet he is not ſatisfied, vntill he hath prouided a <hi>Heuah</hi> to help vs forward to deſtruction. When God made the firſt <hi>Woman,</hi> hee tooke but one<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 2.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Ribbe</hi> out of <hi>Adams ſide,</hi> but the diuell takes ſixe, and of them maketh ſo many Women, all <hi>Sorcereſſes,</hi> ſet on by their <hi>Founder</hi> to bewitch man, and turne away his heart from God: theſe are<note n="x" place="margin">Eph. 4.17.18.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Vanitie of mind; Darknes of Cogitation: Ignorance of God; Hardneſſe of heart; Wantonneſſe in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe;</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:12373:32"/>
and <hi>Greedineſſe in ſinning.</hi> Of theſe <hi>Sixe</hi> wee may <hi>ſay</hi> as <hi>Adam</hi> ſaid of <hi>Heuah: They are bone of our bones, and fleſh of our fleſh,</hi> for their <hi>Original</hi> is from our naturall corruption: euery one of theſe is like the<note n="y" place="margin">Apoc. 17.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Purple Whore,</hi> for with the cup of <hi>Sorcerie</hi> they take away the heart of <hi>Man,</hi> and bereaue it of vnderſtanding.</p>
                  <p>The firſt two, namely, <hi>Vanitie of minde,</hi> and <hi>Darkneſſe of Cogitation,</hi> lead a ſinner,<note n="z" place="margin">Prou. 7.22.</note> 
                     <hi>tanquam bouem ad lanienam,</hi> like <hi>an Oxe to the ſlaughter:</hi> this is a ſtrange <hi>Metamorphoſis;</hi> that a <hi>Man</hi> ſhould be turned into an <hi>Oxe,</hi> yet ſo it is; for as the <hi>Oxe</hi> thinks he goes to the Paſture, when hee is led to the ſlaughter: ſo a ſinner miſled by the vanity of his mind, and hauing his <hi>Cogitation</hi> darkened, thinketh <hi>Sathan</hi> to be an <hi>Angell</hi> of light, <hi>Sinne</hi> moſt ſweet and pleaſant, and himſelfe in the practiſe of it to be euen in Paradiſe, when as poore Soule hee is in the chambers of death.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond two, to wit, <hi>Ignorance of God,</hi> and <hi>Hardneſſe of heart,</hi> worke more powerfully, for when they haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated themſelues and are growne familiar with a <hi>Man,</hi> they change him into the ſhape of a <hi>Horſe,</hi> which as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>muſt be holden in with bit and bridle:</hi> See here the effect of <hi>Cuſtome</hi> in ſinning <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Cuſtome is the food of Sinne,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> and as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith; <hi>Ex ea fit quaedam peccandi neceſſitas, it produceth a neceſſitie in ſinning;</hi> for it cauteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth and ſeares the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and takes away all ſenſe and feeling.</p>
                  <p>The two laſt are Siſters indeed in euill, out-ſtripping the former in helliſh charmes and damnable witchcraft; Namely <hi>Wantonneſſe</hi> in <hi>Vncleaneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Greedineſſe in Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> for when theſe have taken poſſeſſion of a <hi>mans</hi> heart, then is his <hi>Transformation</hi> made abſolute, euen according to the deuils owne deſire, for thereupon he is turned into a <hi>Dogge,</hi> being giuen ouer to a reprobate ſenſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore committing ſinne without all remorſe.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Dogge</hi> is the Embleme of two things,<note n="a" place="margin">Pyer. in Hyer.</note> 
                     <hi>Greedines,</hi>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:12373:33"/>
and <hi>Impudencie,</hi> as appeareth in the <hi>Aegyptian Hyerogly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheckes,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God calling all <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates</hi> by the name of <hi>Dogges,</hi> intimateth vnto vs, theſe two infallible markes of <hi>Reprobation, Impudencie,</hi> and <hi>Greedineſſe</hi> in ſinning.</p>
                  <p>Of all creatures two are moſt impudent, the <hi>Dogge</hi> and the <hi>Flie,</hi> and thereupon ſaith <hi>Pollux,</hi> the Grecians vſed the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to ſignifie <hi>Impudencie:</hi> alſo amongſt the Romanes <hi>Cotytto</hi> the goddeſſe of <hi>Impudencie</hi> was painted with a <hi>dogges-head</hi> and a womans bodie, whoſe Prieſts, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Baptae,</hi> in their ſacrifices vſed moſt impudent geſtures: like Goddeſſe, like Prieſts, and like vnto them be all <hi>repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, Dogges</hi> in diſpoſition, hauing the braſen forehead of a harlot, which neuer bluſheth at the fouleſt ſinne.<note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> was ſuch a <hi>dogge,</hi> who <hi>went into his fathers Concubines in the ſight of all Iſrael.</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 7.18.</note> The harlot in the Prouerbs was ſuch a <hi>dogge,</hi> who <hi>caught a young man in the open ſtreetes and kiſſed him, and with an impudent face ſaid vnto him, Come let vs take our fill of loue, vntill the Morning, let vs take our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in dalliance, for mine husband is not at home, &amp;c.</hi> Of ſuch like <hi>dogges</hi> as theſe there is plentie, who are ſo farre from confeſſing their ſinnes with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and weeping for them bitterly with <hi>Peter,</hi> that they will grin and barke againſt him that doth but vnwittingly touch their vlcer. Their ſinne is like the diſeaſe called <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> Touch me not; if it be handled though neuer ſo gently, they preſent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly either dart againſt the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> the Iauelin of their malice, euen bitter words; or elſe cry out in defence of their ſinnes, as the<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 19.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Epheſians</hi> did for their <hi>Diana:</hi> in this caſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience guides my tongue; for I haue Preached to ſuch <hi>dogges,</hi> as like the Prieſts of<note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 5.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Dagon,</hi> haue forborne &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne the <hi>treſhold</hi> of Gods Temple, becauſe in that place the idoll of their heart hath fallen before the <hi>Arke</hi> of God. Is not this impudencie in ſinning? is not this the brand of <hi>Reprobation?</hi> are not theſe <hi>dogges?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, the <hi>dogge</hi> is the embleme of <hi>Greedineſſe,</hi> and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12373:33"/>
therefore the holy Ghoſt cals all <hi>caſtawaies</hi> dogges, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be vſually greedy of ſinning. There is a diſeaſe (ſaith <hi>Galen</hi>) in the orifice of the ſtomacke, called <hi>Bulimia</hi> or <hi>Bulimus,</hi> which procureth in him that is diſeaſed, <hi>an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable hunger, that neuer hath inough, and a greedie appetite, or deſire of eating:</hi> ſuch a greedie worme as this haue all Reprobates in their <hi>ſoules,</hi> which makes their appetite quite contrarie to that of the elect; for theſe <hi>hunger and thirſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter righteouſneſſe,</hi> but the wicked thirſt and hunger af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne. Thus doth <hi>Vanitie of minde,</hi> and <hi>darkneſſe of Cogitation,</hi> lead the ſinner like an Oxe to the ſlaughter: <hi>Ignorance</hi> of God, and <hi>Hardneſſe</hi> of heart, make him ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate; like vnto a <hi>horſe that muſt be holden in with bit and bridle;</hi> and <hi>Wantonneſſe,</hi> or <hi>Impudencie</hi> in <hi>Vncleanneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Greedines</hi> in <hi>ſinning,</hi> transforme him into a <hi>dogge;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writing to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> giueth an excellent <hi>caueat</hi> againſt theſe ſixe <hi>Sorcereſſes,</hi> ſaying:
<q>
                        <p>This I ſay therefore and teſtifie in the Lord, that ye henceforth walke not as other Gentiles walke, in vanitie of their mind,</p>
                        <p>Hauing their cogitation darkened, and being ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in them, becauſe of the hardneſſe of their heart.</p>
                        <p>Which being paſt feeling, haue giuen themſelues vnto wantonneſſe, to worke all vncleanneſſe, euen with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe.</p>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For without ſhall be Dogges.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond generall part, is a <hi>Deteſtation:</hi> for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are heere called <hi>dogges;</hi> which importeth <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Baſeneſſe,</hi> as may appeare by the vſe of this <hi>Title</hi> both in profane and diuine writers. <hi>Odit cane peius,</hi> (ſaith the Poet) <hi>ſhe hates him worſe then a dogge. Non eum ſalutat magis quam canem,</hi> (ſaith the ſeruant in the Comedie) <hi>ſhe giues him the entertainment of a dogge.</hi> So likewiſe in the Scriptures, <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liah</hi> when hee ſaw young <hi>Dauid</hi> come againſt him, armed
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12373:34"/>
onely with his ſtaffe, his <hi>ſling,</hi> and fiue <hi>ſmooth ſtones</hi> in his <hi>bagge</hi> or <hi>ſcrip,</hi> he ſaid vnto him; <hi>Am I a dogge, that thou commeſt vnto me with ſtones?</hi> When <hi>Isboſheth</hi> reprooued <hi>Abner</hi> for going to <hi>Rispah,</hi> the Concubine of <hi>Saul,</hi> hee was wroth, and ſaid,<note n="g" place="margin">2 Sam. 3.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Am I a dogges-head?</hi> The paraphraſe then both of <hi>Goliahs</hi> and <hi>Abners</hi> words, is this: <hi>Am I ſo vile, ſo baſe, and ſo contemptible?</hi> So in theſe words Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, to ſhew and manifeſt his <hi>deteſtation</hi> and <hi>hatred</hi> of ſinne, calles all <hi>Reprobates dogges,</hi> ſaying; <hi>For without ſhall be dogges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Scriptures we reade, that when God is prouoked to anger, he declares by foure ſeuerall waies, howe much he abhors and deteſts ſinne; namely, <hi>by ſtrange ſignes, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legories, Ironies,</hi> and <hi>Characters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, by <hi>ſtrange ſignes;</hi> to omit many other, there is one moſt remarkeable in the Prophecie of <hi>Hoſeah;</hi> where wee finde that God being greatly offended at the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> for their <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> deciphers the fouleneſſe of their <hi>Sinne</hi> by an vncouth ſigne: <hi>Goe</hi> (ſaith hee to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,)<note n="h" place="margin">Hoſ. 1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Take vnto thee a wife of Fornications, and children of Fornications.</hi> So <hi>Hoſeah</hi> went and tooke <hi>Gomer</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Diblaim,</hi> and of her begot two Sonnes and a Daughter, which were thus named by God himſelf, <hi>Izreel, Lo-ruhamah</hi> and <hi>Lo-ammi:</hi> S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> the <hi>Chaldie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſe, Rabbi Kimhi,</hi> and <hi>Aben Ezrah,</hi> ſay that this was onely a <hi>Viſion,</hi> but the more ancient Hebrew Doctors affirme that it was a thing done indeed by the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, and therefore no ſinne in <hi>Hoſeah:</hi> here then God by a very ſtrange ſigne preacheth againſt the <hi>Idolatrie</hi> of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> and proclaimeth vengeance againſt them for their ſinnes, as may be ſhewed out of the names of <hi>Hoſeahs</hi> wife and his <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Fornication.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Firſt, in that <hi>Hoſeah</hi> marryes the <hi>Harlot Gomer,</hi> which is by interpretation <hi>Corruption,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Diblaim,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>a cluſter of Figges,</hi> hereby is taxt the ſpirituall <hi>Whoredome</hi> of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which being corrupted by
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12373:34"/>
the Gentiles with a full conſent had played the <hi>Harlot,</hi> for ſo ſaith God himſelfe,<note n="i" place="margin">Hoſea. 1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>The Land hath committed great whoredome departing from the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, the name of <hi>Hoſeahs</hi> firſt child is <hi>Izreel,</hi> which is <hi>diſperſed;</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Lo-ruhamah,</hi> which is, <hi>not obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mercy;</hi> and the third <hi>Lo-ammi,</hi> that is, <hi>not my people.</hi> There three names are <hi>Signes</hi> of Gods wrath, and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of <hi>vengeance.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> once Gods inheritance muſt be carryed away captiues, and be <hi>diſperſed</hi> ouer the face of the earth, becauſe they were become like <hi>a Clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of rotten Figges,</hi> corrupted with ſpirituall <hi>Fornication:</hi> and being <hi>diſperſed,</hi> though they cry vnto God for his ayde, yet <hi>will he ſhew them no mercy, nor euer acknowledge them to be his people:</hi> thus by a moſt <hi>ſtrange Signe</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeahs marrying of a Harlot, and begetting children of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,</hi> God declareth how much hee deteſteth <hi>Sinne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, by <hi>Allegories:</hi> an example hereof we haue in the Prophecie of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> where the Lord thus ſaith:<note n="k" place="margin">Ezech. 23.2.3.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Sonne of man, there were two women, the daughters of one Mother, and they committed Fornication in Aegipt, they committed fornication in their youth, there were their breaſts preſſed, and there they bruiſed the teates of their Virginitie, and the names of them were Aholah the Elder, and Aholibah her Siſter, and they were mine, and they bare Sonnes and Daughters; thus were their names: Samaria is Aholah, and Hieruſalem Aholibah, &amp;c.</hi> In theſe words Allegorically God inueyeth moſt bitterly againſt the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> in that as a token of <hi>Deteſtation,</hi> hee compares them to <hi>two Harlots</hi> being he moſt odious and loathſome of all creatures.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, by <hi>Ironies,</hi> or <hi>Iesting</hi> and <hi>Taunting:</hi> a <hi>Ieſt</hi> is Gods <hi>Hierapicra, his bitter confection, his rod of Iron,</hi> his Sheepe-hooke called <hi>Bondes,</hi> his two-edged <hi>Sword,</hi> be moſt peircing reproofe, and the beſt remedie to cure a deſperate ſore. Some Diuels ſaith <hi>Pſellus,</hi> are driuen away by <hi>Iesting,</hi> and <hi>Saules</hi> euill Spirit leſt him
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:12373:35"/>
at the ſweet ſound of <hi>Dauids Harp,</hi> and a <hi>Taunt</hi> is very forcible to make a man aſhamed of his Sinne. When <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Heuah</hi> were fallen in Paradice, God ſaid,<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the man is become as one of vs, to know good and euill:</hi> here God derideth <hi>Adams folly,</hi> becauſe hee was ſeduced by the woman. So likewiſe the Prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> mocketh the Prieſts of <hi>Baall;</hi> ſaying:<note n="m" place="margin">1 Reg. 18.27</note> 
                     <hi>Cry loud, for he is a God, eyther he talketh, or purſueth his enemies, or is in his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or it may be that hee ſleepeth, and muſt be awaked:</hi> thus God to ſhew his <hi>hatred</hi> of Sinne <hi>laugheth</hi> (as the Wiſeman ſaith) <hi>at the deſtruction of the wicked, and mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when their feare commeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, by <hi>Figures</hi> and <hi>Characters:</hi> Sinne is moſt liuely expreſſed by a foule <hi>Picture,</hi> and therefore God to ſet forth his owne <hi>hatred,</hi> and to breed in vs a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, vſeth ſometimes <hi>Characters,</hi> whereof there be diuers patternes and inſtances: as for example;<note n="n" place="margin">Prou. 30.14.</note> 
                     <hi>That generation, whoſe teeth are as ſwords, and their iawes as kniues to eate vp the afflicted out of the earth, and the poore from among men:</hi> I meane tyrannicall oppreſſors, <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtes</hi> his <hi>progenie,</hi> Land-rackers, which meaſure their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants vpon a <hi>Bed</hi> of <hi>Iron:</hi> cutting them ſhorter if they be too long, or haue too much; and tentaring or ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out longer if they be too ſhort; theſe <hi>Cater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillars</hi> I ſay, are by the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> called <hi>Kine:</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Amos. 4.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Heare this word</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ye Kine of Baſhan, that are in the mountaine of Samaria, which oppreſſe the poore and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the needy, and they ſay to their maſters, bring and let vs drinke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Furthermore <hi>vniuſt Iudges,</hi> ſuch as Iuſtifie the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for reward, and condemne the innocent; ſuch as <hi>cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie Chriſt</hi> in his members, and let the murtherer and the robber <hi>Barabas</hi> looſe, there are by the Prophet <hi>Zepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niah</hi> called<note n="p" place="margin">Zeph. 3.3.</note> 
                     <hi>Wolues,</hi> in regard of their cruell craftineſſe and craftie crueltie.</p>
                  <p>Againe, the greedy <hi>Miſer</hi> and the luxurious <hi>Epicure</hi>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:12373:35"/>
are named<note n="q" place="margin">Prou. 30.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Horſe-leaches daughters,</hi> whoſe inſatietie cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their tongues to cry out continually <hi>giue, giue,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe like <hi>hell mouth,</hi> and the barren wombe, they two will neuer ſay, <hi>it is enough.</hi> I might inſiſt in diuers other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>Characters</hi> of this nature, but let this ſuffice, that the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God in theſe words calleth the whole <hi>frye</hi> of the wicked, <hi>dogges,</hi> to ſhew how much they are abhor'd, and how hatefull they be in the ſight of God.</p>
                  <p>Though the <hi>Reprobates</hi> be generally tearmed <hi>Dogges,</hi> yet the Diuell hath a ſelected number vpon earth, which may well be called <hi>Sathans Kennell,</hi> and it conſiſteth of fiue forts of men, who as an argument of their deteſtable life are in the Scripture ſtiled <hi>Dogges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt is the <hi>Infidell</hi> or the <hi>Gentile:</hi> he is by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour in his ſpeech to the woman of <hi>Syrophaeniſſa</hi> called a <hi>Whelp,</hi> or a <hi>Dogge,</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Mark. 7.27.</note> 
                     <hi>It is not good</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>to take the childrens bread and giue it vnto Whelpes:</hi> ſee here what baſe account <hi>Chriſt</hi> makes of <hi>Infidels</hi> and vnbeleeuers: hee calles them <hi>Dogges,</hi> and well doth this name befit them; for like beaſts they are without reaſon, elſe would they neuer forſake the <hi>Creator</hi> to worſhip the <hi>Creature.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Athan. in erat. de Idolis. Lactant. lib. <hi>2..</hi> diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>inflic.</note> 
                     <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of the true <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Blindneſſe</hi> of heart were in the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the <hi>Nources</hi> of <hi>Infidelitie,</hi> and the <hi>Broachers</hi> of <hi>Idolatrie,</hi> ſaith <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Lactantius:</hi> had there beene in them but any ſparke of reaſon, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue committed ſo groſſe and palpable a ſinne, but they were without <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> meere <hi>Dogges;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore being ſtrucken with a ſpirituall madneſſe, they runne headlong like the <hi>Swine</hi> of the <hi>Gergezens,</hi> into the maine <hi>Ocean</hi> of all vncleanneſſe, and filthineſſe of <hi>Fornication:</hi> ſome going a whoring after<note n="s" place="margin">Ezech. 8.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Baal,</hi> and <hi>Chemos,</hi> as the <hi>Moabites:</hi> ſome after<note n="t" place="margin">1 Reg. 11.7.</note> 
                     <hi>Milcom</hi> and <hi>Moloch,</hi> as the <hi>Ammonites:</hi> others after<note n="u" place="margin">1 Reg. 11.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Aſteroth, Dagon, Meleketh</hi> or <hi>the Queene of heauen, Tamuz,</hi>
                     <note n="x" place="margin">Leu. 18.21.</note> 
                     <hi>Baal-zebub,</hi> and many others: nay further, what more pregnant demonſtration can be made of the bruitiſh dotage of <hi>Infidels,</hi> then to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12373:36"/>
take a ſuruay of the <hi>East and Weſt Indians,</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Munſt. Coſm.</note> who at this day worſhip the <hi>Deuill</hi> himſelfe, repreſented by an <hi>Idoll</hi> of a horrible and ougly ſhape.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond <hi>Dogge,</hi> is the <hi>Contemner of the Goſpel;</hi>
                     <note n="z" place="margin">Matth. 7.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Giue ye not</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that which is holy vnto dogges, neither caſt you your pearles before ſwine, leſt they tread them vnder their feet, and turning againe all to rent you.</hi> Here our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our prohibiteth the preaching of the Goſpel, to ſuch as wilfully reſiſt the <hi>Truth,</hi> and barke at the Miniſters of the word: Such <hi>Dogges</hi> are <hi>Papists,</hi> who are not aſhamed ſome of them blaſphemouſly to call the holy word of God, <hi>a Noſe of waxe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sil. Prier. in epit. reſp. ad Luth. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi> Concil. Trid. ſeſ. <hi>4.</hi> pag. <hi>11.</hi> &amp; <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>a dead Letter, an Incken Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>a fable.</hi> Were they not <hi>Contemners</hi> of the Goſpel of Chriſt, they would neuer vilifie it ſo much, as to make it <hi>ſubiect</hi> to the <hi>Popes cenſure;</hi> who may, as they teach, <hi>choppe and change the Scriptures at his pleaſure, equalizing to them his owne tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conſtitutions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>dogges,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Ieſuiticall Blood-hounds,</hi> are as dangerous in the <hi>Church,</hi> and the common-wealth; <hi>as</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Iudg. 15.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Sampſons Foxes</hi> in the <hi>Corne fields</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtims;</hi> their <hi>barking</hi> bewraies that they are like<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 8.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> in the gall of bitternes, <hi>and in the bond of iniquitie.</hi> But let vs heare their mouthes;<note place="margin">Lib. Ieſuit. cui tit. Concertatio Eccl. catholica. Ioan. Mariana Ieſu. Toleta. de rege. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>65. 67.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>The Pope,</hi> ſay they, <hi>is Lord of the whole earth, and therefore it is in his power alone to aduance or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe whom he will, bee it Emperour, King, or other Potentate: It is lawfull</hi> (ſay they) <hi>to murther a Prince that is a Lutheran or a Caluiniſt, either by ſword or poyſon.</hi> Doe not theſe <hi>Dogs</hi> make man admirable crie? but they would be truſt vp, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they <hi>haunt counter,</hi> contrary to the expreſſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God; who ſaith,<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
                     <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers, for there is no power but of God:</hi> and in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, <hi>Touch not mine Annoynted;</hi> and yet there bee ſome of theſe <hi>Romiſh Dogges,</hi> that can temporize, and crie <hi>Haile Caeſar:</hi> but it is as <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen</hi> ſaith, <hi>As if a man with one hand ſhould ſcratch a Kings head, and with the other ſtrike him vpon the cheek.</hi> There is no truſt to be giuen
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12373:36"/>
vnto them, becauſe there neuer can be any perfect and true loyaltie, where there is a difference in <hi>Religion: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nus Rex, vna lex; vna fides; One King, one law, and me faith, is a</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 4.12.</note> 
                     <hi>three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord, which will not eaſily be broken:</hi> they then that <hi>profeſſe another faith</hi> then we do, depending vpon <hi>that man of ſinne,</hi> who challengeth power to <hi>abſolue ſubiects</hi> from their allegiance to their Princes, though they liue amongſt vs, yet are they not of vs; they be but (as<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 26.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by King <hi>Agrippa</hi>) almoſt <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> almoſt <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects:</hi> or like vnto the <hi>Cofti</hi> in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> which are both <hi>Baptized</hi> and <hi>Circumciſed,</hi> beeing <hi>ſemi-Iewes, ſemi-Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> ſo are they <hi>ſemi-Engliſh,</hi> and <hi>ſemi-Italians:</hi> from the Nauill downeward they are their Kings, but all vpward is the <hi>Popes:</hi> to him beeing their <hi>holy Father, They giue their hearts:</hi> well, <hi>Clemencie</hi> is a <hi>Royal Vertue;</hi> but marke <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarckes</hi> ſpeech, <hi>It is not a fine ſhooe that will cure the gout, nor a gold ring the crampe, nor a crowne the head-ache;</hi> nor is the <hi>biting</hi> of a mad dogge ſtaid by gentle vſage: to cure the ſtinging of the <hi>fierie Serpents, Moſes</hi> by the appointment of God made a <hi>Serpent of braſſe,</hi> and ſet it vp for a <hi>Signe;</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Num. 21.9.</note> and when a Serpent had bitten a <hi>Man, then he looked to the Serpent of braſſe and liued:</hi> but to heale the wounds which the venemous <hi>Teeth</hi> of theſe <hi>mad dogges</hi> do make, no other remedie can be found, but to hang vp the <hi>Dogs</hi> themſelues.</p>
                  <p>The third <hi>Dogge,</hi> is the <hi>Sciſmaticke;</hi> of him the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle</hi> giueth vs a <hi>Caueat,</hi> ſaying,<note n="g" place="margin">Phil. 3.2.</note> 
                     <hi>Beware of dogges: beware of euill workers: beware of Conciſion.</hi> This <hi>Dogge,</hi> though he be not altogether ſo dangerous as the <hi>Blood-hound</hi> of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> yet is he wondrous troubleſome. To him I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that ſpeech of <hi>Seneca</hi> the Philoſopher;<note place="margin">Sen. de rem. fertu.</note> 
                     <hi>Quibuſdam ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus hoc innatum eſt, vt non proferitate, ſed pro conſuetudine latrent;</hi> Some dogges haue it by nature, <hi>to barke more for cuſtome then crueltie:</hi> and ſo doth the <hi>Schiſmaticke</hi> or <hi>Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt,</hi> whoſe mouth filles the ayre onely, little or nothing troubling the eares of wiſe men. And yet it is well that ſuch
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12373:37"/>
                     <hi>Barkers</hi> as theſe, that open their mouthes againſt thee graue <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> deſpiſing authoritie, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the preſent diſcipline, ſhould be muſled; elſe would there be no peace in <hi>Zion,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> would be euen rent aſunder by that many-headed <hi>Hydra, turbulent faction.</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">1. Reg. 6.7.</note> When the <hi>Temple</hi> was built, there was neither heard <hi>Axe</hi> nor <hi>Hammer, nor any toole of yron in the houſe;</hi> ſo ſhould Gods <hi>Church</hi> be free from <hi>tumultuous Schiſme.</hi> When Chriſt came into the world, the <hi>Quire</hi> of <hi>Angels ſung,</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Luk. 2.14.</note> 
                     <hi>Pax hominibus, Peace to men:</hi> and when after his reſurrection he appeared to his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> he ſaid,<note n="k" place="margin">Ioh. 20.19.</note> 
                     <hi>Pax vobis, Peace bee vnto you;</hi> as then he is a <hi>Salomon,</hi> ſo would hee haue his ſubiects <hi>Shulamites;</hi> and as hee is the King of <hi>Peace,</hi> ſo would he haue vs keepe the Kings <hi>Peace</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi>
                     <note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 3.9.10.</note> 
                     <hi>King Salomon made himſelfe a Palace of the Trees of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon, he made the pillars thereof of ſiluer, and the pauement of gold, the hangings thereof of purple, whoſe midſt was paued with the loue of the daughters of Ieruſalem:</hi> Like vnto this <hi>Palace</hi> ſhould the <hi>Church</hi> be; the <hi>ſiluer pillars</hi> ſignifie <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline;</hi> the <hi>golden pauement, pure doctrine;</hi> the <hi>purple hangings, regall protection;</hi> and the <hi>loue of the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Ieruſalem, peace</hi> and <hi>vnity</hi> amongſt <hi>profeſſours.</hi> Now how can this peace be preſerued, if <hi>Schiſme</hi> be not baniſht, and all gaine-ſaying <hi>Corahs</hi> put to ſilence. Of the <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall Dogges,</hi> I will ſay nothing, but as the antient <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> in like caſe ſpoke, and decreed in two ſeuerall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels,<note n="m" place="margin">Conc. Gang. Cap. <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Si quis extra Eccleſiam priuatim populos congregat, anathema ſit; If any out of the Church doe priuatly gather the people together,</hi> (as our Corner-preachers doe in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticles) <hi>let him be accurſed.</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Conc. Laodicen. can. <hi>35.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Nam non oportet Chriſtianos Eccleſiam Dei relinquere &amp; in angulis Congregationes face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, For it is not meet that Chriſtians ſhould leaue the Church of God, and make their Congregations in corners.</hi> And yet there be euen in the moſt reformed Churches ſome <hi>dogges</hi> tranſported with Singularitie, that make <hi>Conciſion,</hi> and cut and diuide themſelues, both in <hi>hearing of the word,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:12373:37"/>
of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> from the reſt of <hi>Christs family;</hi> as though the <hi>Church</hi> were <hi>Baals Temple,</hi> the Booke of <hi>Common prayer a porteſſe,</hi> the manner of miniſtring the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> ſuperſtitious, and the <hi>Eccleſiasticall</hi> gouernment <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Solin. cap. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </note> The Prieſts of <hi>Pergamus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solinus</hi>) to keepe Spiders out of the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> hanged vp in the ſame place the carkaſſe of a <hi>Baſiliske</hi> in a net of gold: <hi>Seueritie</hi> is of the ſame vertue that a Baſiliske is, beeing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by ſuch as are in Authority, it cleareth Gods <hi>Church</hi> of all <hi>Schiſmaticall dogges,</hi> whoſe chiefe delight is to trouble the peace of <hi>Zion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth <hi>Dogge,</hi> is the <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> or <hi>Back-ſlider:</hi> of whom Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh;<note n="o" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.22.</note> 
                     <hi>The dogge is returned to his own vomit, and the Sowe that was waſhed, so the wallowing in the mire.</hi> But here we muſt note, that all <hi>Apoſtates</hi> bee not <hi>dogges,</hi> or <hi>Reprobates,</hi> but onely ſuch men as wilfully and willingly reiect <hi>Faith,</hi> and doe altogether alienate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſet themſelues againſt him: This is the <hi>Sinne</hi> againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which God ſo puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, as it ſhall not be forgiuen neither in this world, nor yet in the world to come. So ſaies the Author to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes,</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 6.4.5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>It is impoſſible that they which were once lightened, and haue tasted of the heauenly gift, and were made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the holy Ghoſt, and haue tasted of the good word of God, and of the powers of the world to come, if they fall away ſhould be renewed againe by repentance, ſeeing they crucifie againe to themſelues the Sonne of God, and make a mocke of him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such a <hi>dogge</hi> was <hi>Iulian,</hi> ſurnamed the <hi>Apoſtata,</hi> who being conuerted from <hi>Gentiliſme</hi> to <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward returne to his <hi>Vomit,</hi> oppugning with his <hi>Pen</hi> that <hi>Truth</hi> which he had profeſſed, and calling <hi>Chriſt</hi> in ſcorne the <hi>Galilaean. Peter</hi> denied <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his mouth, and many other in the time of <hi>Perſecution</hi> haue fallen as <hi>Marcellinus,</hi> who fearing death offered ſacrifice to <hi>Idols;</hi> were theſe therefore <hi>dogges?</hi> No: for inwardly in their
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12373:38"/>
minde they renounced not <hi>Faith:</hi> if they had vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the <hi>Faith;</hi> they had neuer repented; for <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> is one of the fruites of <hi>Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fift <hi>Dogge</hi> is hee whom the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> calleth the <hi>blinde, dumbe</hi> and <hi>greedy Dogge:</hi> ſaying;<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 56.10.11</note> 
                     <hi>Their watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are all blinde, they haue no knowledge: They are all dumbe Dogges: they cannot barke, they lie and ſleepe, and delight in ſleeping, and theſe greedy dogges can neuer haue enough, and theſe Shepheards cannot vnderſtand; for they all looke to their owne way, euery one for his aduantage, and for his owne purpoſe.</hi> Theſe <hi>dogges</hi> euen with their breath blaſt Gods <hi>Harueſt,</hi> and pollute the <hi>Sanctuarie:</hi> they be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Chriſts</hi> kingdome, and betrayers of <hi>mens</hi> ſoules. <hi rend="sup">b</hi> It is written of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">2. Reg. 12.31</note> that hee did not onely deſtroy the <hi>Idols,</hi> and put downe their <hi>Chemarims,</hi> but alſo hauing found out the Booke of the Law, he cauſed it to be read vnto the people by the <hi>Prieſts:</hi> out of whoſe example, all Princes are taught to take into their hands the <hi>Scourge</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to <hi>whip buyers and ſellers out of the Temple:</hi> I meane ſuch as hauing no worth to commend them, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre themſelues by <hi>Simonicall</hi> compacting, and ſufferance of their beards and coates, like the<note n="s" place="margin">2. Sam. 10.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> to be <hi>halfe ſhauen,</hi> and cut ſhort, by theſe greedy <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites,</hi> ſacrilegious <hi>Patrons,</hi> who euer deſire to retaine and preſent to <hi>Eccleſiasticall</hi> Benefices the <hi>cheapeſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister,</hi> one of<note n="t" place="margin">Iudg. 17.10.</note> 
                     <hi>Micahs Leuites,</hi> that will be content to <hi>ſerue the Cure for ten ſhekels of ſiluer by yeere, a ſuite of apparrell, and his meat and his drinck:</hi> hence it is, that ſo many <hi>dumb dogges</hi> are in the Church, men that were neuer brought vp at the feete of any learned <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Pindarus</hi> calles ſuch like, <hi>Hogheards</hi> not <hi>Shepheards, Aſini coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nati,</hi> as one of the Emperours ſtiles them in his Letters to the King of <hi>France, Crowned Aſſes,</hi> vnlearned and blind Guides, whoſe <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the cauſe that <hi>Bethel</hi> is turned to be a <hi>Bethanen,</hi> and the <hi>Houſe</hi> of God, the <hi>houſe</hi> of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: thus doth Almightie God in ſigne of <hi>deteſtation</hi>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:12373:38"/>
and hatred, call <hi>Infidels, Goſpel-contemners, Schiſmatickes, Apoſtates,</hi> and vnworthy <hi>Miniſters; Dogges.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>For without ſhall be Dogges.</head>
                  <p>The third generall part is a <hi>Separation:</hi> the viſible <hi>Church</hi> here vpon earth is like vnto<note n="u" place="margin">Gen. 25.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Rebeccaes</hi> wombe, in which at one time were incloſed both <hi>Iacob,</hi> whom God loued, and <hi>Eſau,</hi> whom hee hated: it is like vnto a<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 13.27.</note> 
                     <hi>Field,</hi> wherein grow both <hi>Wheat</hi> and <hi>Tares:</hi> it is like vnto the<note n="y" place="margin">Act. 10.12.</note> 
                     <hi>Sheet</hi> knit at the foure corners, <hi>wherein were all manner of foure-footed beaſts of the earth, and wilde beaſts, and creeping things, and fowles of the heauen:</hi> for in this life, the <hi>Elect</hi> and the <hi>Reprobates,</hi> are mixt together as the <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Iebuſites</hi> in old <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> but it ſhall not be ſo at the laſt day, for when our Sauiour comes to <hi>Iudgement,</hi> hee ſhall like a <hi>Shepheard, ſeparate the Sheepe from the Goates:</hi> his <hi>Reapers</hi> ſhall gather the <hi>Tares,</hi> and binde them in ſheaues to burne them, but gather the <hi>Wheate</hi> into his barne: and the true <hi>Iſraelites that haue done his Commandements ſhall haue right in the tree of life, and enter in through the gates into the Citie:</hi> but <hi>without ſhall be Dogges, and Enchanters, and Whore-mongers, and murtherers, and Idolaters, and whoſoeuer loueth or maketh lyes.</hi> This <hi>Separation</hi> ſhall be as the <hi>Springes</hi> of <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the righteous, but as the <hi>Waters</hi> of <hi>Marah</hi> to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly; as ſweet as honie and the hony-combe to the true beleeuer, but as bitter as Gall and wormewood to the Infidell.</p>
                  <p>In this world the <hi>commixion</hi> of the <hi>Good</hi> and the <hi>Euill,</hi> is euill for the <hi>Good,</hi> but good for the <hi>Euill:</hi> Firſt, it is euill for the <hi>Good</hi> to liue amongſt, and conuerſe with the wicked: for which cauſe <hi>Dauid</hi> complaineth, ſaying, <hi>Woe is me, that I am conſtrained to dwell with Meſech, and to haue my habitation amongeſt the Tents of Kedar:</hi> but on the contrary part it is good for the <hi>Euill,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Euill</hi> by the <hi>Good</hi> are ſhielded from many plagues: if<note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 18.32.</note> ten
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12373:39"/>
righteous men had bene found in <hi>Sodome,</hi> God would not haue deſtroyed it for the <hi>tennes</hi> ſake, and one<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 39.5.</note> 
                     <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was the cauſe that the bleſſing of the Lord was vpon the whole houſe of <hi>Potiphar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This life is a time of <hi>weeping</hi> and <hi>mourning</hi> to <hi>Gods Children,</hi> but a time of <hi>laughing</hi> and <hi>dauncing</hi> to the <hi>Sonnes</hi> of <hi>Beliall;</hi> the <hi>Righteous</hi> mourne to ſee the <hi>Vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> daunce, and the <hi>Reprobate</hi> laugh to ſee the <hi>Elect</hi> weepe:<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.1.</note> But as all things haue their appointed time, and are ſubiect to change and alteration, euen ſo the eſtate of <hi>Men:</hi> for when that <hi>Generall Separation</hi> ſhall be made, then they <hi>that haue ſowne it teares ſhall reape in ioy;</hi> and to ſuch whoſe <hi>Seed-time</hi> hath beene <hi>Mirth,</hi> a <hi>harueſt</hi> ſhall befall of <hi>weeping</hi> and gnaſhing of teeth. As one hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen cannot hold<note n="b" place="margin">Apo. 12.7.8.</note> 
                     <hi>Michael</hi> and the <hi>Dragon;</hi> nor one Temple<note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Gods Arke</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>gon;</hi> nor one ground beare both the <hi>Oke</hi> and the <hi>Oliue:</hi> no more ſhall the glorious Citie <hi>New Hieruſalem</hi> containe both the <hi>Sheepe</hi> and the <hi>Goates,</hi> the <hi>pure</hi> in heart, and the <hi>polluted</hi> in ſoule; no, no, <hi>Within</hi> onely the <hi>Lambe</hi> ſhall be and the <hi>bleſſed Virgins</hi> his followers: but <hi>without ſhall be dogges.</hi> Theſe two words <hi>Within</hi> and <hi>Without,</hi> are like <hi>Hercules Pillars,</hi> vpon which was written <hi>Nil vltrà, Nothing further:</hi> for in them we ſee the <hi>end</hi> of all <hi>fleſh: Within,</hi> ſhewes the <hi>Map</hi> of <hi>heauen; Without</hi> declares the <hi>Topographie</hi> of <hi>hell: Within,</hi> promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>life euerlaſting; Without</hi> threatneth <hi>death aeternall.</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 28.30.</note> The two words <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> being by Gods appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment written vpon the breſt of the <hi>High Prieſt</hi> were to put him in minde of <hi>Zeale</hi> and <hi>Knowledge,</hi> two eſſentiall and neceſſarie vertues in the Miniſters of God; ſo theſe two <hi>Within</hi> and <hi>Without</hi> being Characters of <hi>Separation,</hi> doe intimate vnto vs the glorious <hi>Eſtate</hi> of the <hi>Righteous</hi> and the miſcrable <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>Wicked</hi> in the world to come.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>Within</hi> like a <hi>Remembrancer</hi> puts vs in minde of that <hi>felicitie</hi> which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> calleth a <hi>Myſterie,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12373:39"/>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 2.7.6</note>
                     <hi>The things which eye hath not ſeene, neyther eare hath heard, neyther came into mans heart, are, which God hath prepared for them that loue him:</hi> oh then thrice happy are the Elect, which ſhall be free Denizons in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> and coheyres with Chriſt in his Kingdome, enioying<note n="f" place="margin">Iohn. 16.22.</note> 
                     <hi>a ioy which none ſhall take from them; euen the</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> 
                     <hi>ioy of their Lord, being with him to behold his glorie:</hi> whoſe preſence ſhall be to them ſaith <hi>Auſtin, tanquam Cythara, Speculum, Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, Mel &amp; Flos:</hi> like a <hi>Harp</hi> for their hearing, like a <hi>Glaſſe</hi> for their ſeeing, like <hi>Balme</hi> for their ſmelling, like <hi>Hony</hi> for their taſting, and like a <hi>Flower</hi> for their touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: the <hi>Meditation</hi> hereof worketh in the Regenerate ſtrange effects. Firſt, as the ſweet ſound of<note n="h" place="margin">1. Sam. 16.13</note> 
                     <hi>Dauids</hi> Harp did driue away the <hi>Euill Spirit</hi> from King <hi>Saul,</hi> and as the<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 15.25.</note> 
                     <hi>Wood</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> caſt into <hi>Marah,</hi> changed the <hi>bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Water</hi> into <hi>ſweetneſſe:</hi> ſo though the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous be enuironed and encompaſt with a thouſand bitter afflictions in this life, and be euen heauy loaden with <hi>croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> laid on them by <hi>Sathan</hi> and the world; yet when they caſt vp their eyes to heauen, <hi>the bright and glorious coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie of the ſoule,</hi> as <hi>Zoroaſtres</hi> cals it, then is their Worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood turned into hony, and their griefe of minde into gladneſſe of heart, becauſe they know that a time ſhall come, when the Saints that are now eclipſed by the ſhadow of aduerſitie<note n="k" place="margin">Dan, 12.3.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall ſhine like the Sunne and the Starres of the Firmament,</hi> and they that now weare <hi>Sackcloth,</hi> with <hi>Dauid; hairecloth</hi> with <hi>Eliah;</hi> and garments of <hi>Camels hair</hi> with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ſhall be cloathed with <hi>long white robes,</hi> made <hi>white</hi> in the <hi>bloud</hi> of the <hi>Lambe.</hi> Secondly, as the ſight of the blood of grapes, made the Elephants of King <hi>Antiochus</hi> fight more furiouſly: ſo euen the very thought of <hi>heauenly ioy</hi> ſtirres vp the mindes and the hearts of the <hi>Righteous, to fight a good fight, to runne a good race,</hi> and <hi>to offer violence to the Kingdome of heauen,</hi> by taking paines to heare Gods word preached in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> and out of <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> by praying continually, by beating downe the <hi>fleſh</hi> and
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12373:40"/>
keeping it in ſubiection by Faſting and Abſtinence, by ſweating blood and water, and watring their Couches with teares; had it not beene for the <hi>remembrance</hi> of <hi>Chanaan,</hi> a land flowing with milke and honie; the <hi>barrenneſſe</hi> of the Wilderneſſe would haue broken the hearts of the people of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> our life is a <hi>pilgrimage,</hi> and the World is a Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, through it the <hi>way</hi> to the land of <hi>Promiſe</hi> is ſtraite and hard to find. Is not this enough to daunt and diſmay a <hi>Paſſenger?</hi> but <hi>hope</hi> of beeing at the laſt <hi>within</hi> the gates of the <hi>holy City,</hi> cheares vp the <hi>Chriſtian pilgrime,</hi> &amp; armes him with <hi>patience</hi> againſt all <hi>dangers;</hi> and <hi>hope</hi> once to bee ſeparated from the ſocietie of <hi>dogges,</hi> cauſeth him to thinke <hi>Chriſts</hi> yoke ſweet, and his <hi>croſſe</hi> a <hi>tree of Life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, this word <hi>Without,</hi> points vs to <hi>Hell, the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Deuils, the hold of all fowle ſpirits, and a cage of euery vncleane, and hatefull bird;</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Eſay 30.33.</note> 
                     <hi>which of old is prepared for the wicked, and by Almighty God is made deepe and large, the burning whereof is fire and much wood.</hi> As was the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah</hi> out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> ſuch ſhall bee the exile of Dogges: God to debarre their re-entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> ſet the<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 3.24.</note> 
                     <hi>Cherubims</hi> and the blade of a Sword ſhaken, to keepe the way of the Tree of Life: our Sauiour at the laſt day, ſhall be the annoynted <hi>Cherub,</hi> to guard the gates of new <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> his fiery <hi>ſword,</hi> ſhal be this Sentence;<note n="m" place="margin">Matth. 25.41</note> 
                     <hi>Depart from me ye curſed into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, which is prepared for the Deuill and his Angels.</hi> Theſe words are,<note n="n" place="margin">Dan. 7.10.</note> 
                     <hi>that fierie ſtreame iſſuing out of the throne of God,</hi> by the violent current whereof, the Wicked like the Swine of the <hi>Gergeſens,</hi> ſhall be carried headlong into the Lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Dan. 5.</note>Three words, <hi>Mene, Tekel,</hi> and <hi>Vpharſin,</hi> written vpon the plaſter of the wall in <hi>Belſhazzers</hi> Palace, foretold the ruine of himſelfe, and his whole Monarchie; but here in this Scripture, one word, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Without,</hi> ſupplies the place of theſe three: the interpretation of <hi>Mene,</hi> is, <hi>God hath num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred thy Kingdome, &amp; finiſhed it:</hi> of <hi>Tekel, Thou art waighed
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12373:40"/>
in the ballance, and art found too light:</hi> and of <hi>Vpharſin, Thy Kingdome is diuided, and giuen to the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. All theſe ſignifications, are included in this one word, <hi>Without;</hi> Firſt, <hi>Without ſhall be dogges,</hi> that is, the Kingdom of the Wicked ſhal then be at an end, for the years of their raigne is expired when Chriſt comes to iudgement. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>Without ſhall be dogges;</hi> that is, God will exerciſe vpon them iudgement in meaſure, and iuſtice in waight. Thirdly, <hi>Without ſhall be dogges;</hi> that is, They ſhall not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be depriued of all earthly pleaſures, but alſo bee diuided and ſeparated from the ſight of Gods glorious Maieſtie, and from the fellowſhip of Saints and Angels.</p>
                  <p>To be <hi>without Heauen,</hi> is to be <hi>within Hell.</hi> Hell then is the place appointed for the impriſonment of Dogges: but is there ſuch a reall place? Many heads haue hammered many conceits:<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 14.1.</note> 
                     <hi>The foole hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God:</hi> the<note n="q" place="margin">Matth. 22.23</note> 
                     <hi>Sadduces</hi> held there were no Angels, and deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Reſurrection of the dead, &amp; the Day of Doome: &amp; there haue bin ſome <hi>Opinioniſts,</hi> which haue affirmed Hel to be nothing elſe, but a bare Separation from Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the Sting or gnawing Worme of a Guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. We muſt confeſſe indeed, that theſe are very dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full torments, wherewith the Wicked, euen in this life, are grieuouſly oppreſt: as may appeare in <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> both which before their death, were in this Hell; but yet all Hell is not contained herein: for theſe two are but bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of the Tree of Death. That there is ſuch a reall place, may be prooued both by Scripture, Teſtimonie of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and pregnant reaſon.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, for Scripture: the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> thus ſpeaketh of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and fooliſh worldlings, which thinke that their <hi>houſes and habitations ſhall continue for euer, and call their Lands by their owne names:</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 49.15.</note> 
                     <hi>Vt ones liſcheol deponuntur, mors illos paſcit, &amp;c. Like ſheepe they lie in hell, Death deuoureth them.</hi> Alſo it is written of<note n="s" place="margin">Num. 16.33.</note> 
                     <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram, that they went downe quicke, Sche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lah ad infernum, to Hell.</hi> Theſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12373:41"/>
words prooue that Hell is not onely a <hi>certaine place,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo demonſtrate where it is; namely below, in the Bowels of the earth. But to theſe places it is anſwered, that <hi>Scheol</hi> ſignities the <hi>Graue:</hi> I know it doth; for the word beares three ſignifications: ſometimes by it is meant the <hi>Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher:</hi> and ſo is it vſed by the Patriarch <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſaying;<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 37.35.</note> 
                     <hi>Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I will goe downe (Scheolah)</hi> into the graue vnto my <hi>ſonne,</hi> mourning: ſometimes metaphorically, it is put for the <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitses</hi> and <hi>afflictions</hi> of this life: ſo the Prophetical King <hi>Dauid</hi> applies it ſaying;<note n="u" place="margin">2. Sam. 22.6.</note> 
                     <hi>Cheble ſcheol ſebabuns, The Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes or Snares of hell compaſſed me about, and ouertooke me.</hi> Sometimes it ſignifies <hi>Eternall deſtruction,</hi> and the real and certain place of the <hi>Damned:</hi> and ſo it is to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in thoſe Texts of Scripture aboue named. For if by <hi>Scheol,</hi> wherein the vngodly like Sheepe ſhall be deuoured by death the <hi>Graue</hi> ſhould onely bee vnderſtood; then ſhould there be no difference betwixt the <hi>Righteous</hi> and the <hi>Wicked;</hi> for Death, &amp; the Graue are common to them both: neither ſhould the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeake of any extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie puniſhment, in ſaying, <hi>They ſhall lie in the graue.</hi> But if we obſerue the Text ſeriouſly, we ſhal find that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> doth moſt directly point to <hi>Hell;</hi> as may appeare out of the words following:<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 49.13.</note> 
                     <hi>But God ſhall deliuer my ſoule from the power of Scheol,</hi> or <hi>hell, for he will receiue me.</hi> The ſame ſignification that <hi>Scheol</hi> hath in theſe words, it hath in the words going before; but here of neceſſitie is meant the <hi>Place</hi> appointed for Caſt-awaies, wherein both body and ſoule ſhall bee tormented. Therefore in the former ſpeech <hi>(Vt oues liſcheol deponuntur mors illos depaſcis) (Like ſheepe they lie in hell, death deuoureth them.)</hi> The ſpirit of God doth plainly deſcribe <hi>hell</hi> to be a <hi>reall</hi> place, and the <hi>Receptacle</hi> of <hi>Reprobates.</hi> Alſo whereas it is ſaid, that they which periſhed in the <hi>gaine-ſaying</hi> of <hi>Corah,</hi> went downe <hi>quicke into hell:</hi> Here-out we may gather, not onely that there is ſuch a <hi>certaine</hi> place; but alſo that it is <hi>below,</hi> euen in the nethermoſt parts of the earth. This is confirmed by
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12373:41"/>
the authoritie of <hi>Epiphanius, Hierom,</hi> and others; all which,<note place="margin">Epiphan. in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorato: Hiero. in <hi>4.</hi> cap. ep. ad Eph. Pagninus in gen. <hi>37.</hi>
                     </note> in that Text of Scripture, by <hi>Scheol,</hi> vnderſtand <hi>Hell.</hi> I might alleadge diuers other teſtimonies out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; as that in <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Deut. 32.22.</note> 
                     <hi>Fire is kindled in my wrath, and ſhall burne vnto the bottome of hell.</hi> Alſo the Wiſe-man ſaith,<note n="z" place="margin">Prou. 15.24.</note> 
                     <hi>The way of life is on high to the prudent, to auoid from hell beneath:</hi> and in another place,<note n="a" place="margin">Prou. 9.18.</note> 
                     <hi>but he knoweth not, that the dead are there, and that her gueſts are (baamake ſcheol) in the depth of hell.</hi> All which places moſt euidently prooue that there is ſuch a Lake, ſuch a Dungeon, and ſuch a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe Pit. But let vs deſcend to the Fathers, prophane Writers, and Reaſon; though theſe to the Scriptures, are but like <hi>Zilpha</hi> and <hi>Billa,</hi> to <hi>Rachel</hi> and <hi>Leah,</hi> hand-maides, or ſeruants. Firſt, <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaies it is a <hi>hollow vault in the earth, full of ſmoake and darkneſſe: Tertullian</hi> calles <hi>hell a Treaſurie of hidden fire in the bowels of the earth:</hi> to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact,</hi> it is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>a darke region vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth:</hi> and of the ſame mind is Saint <hi>Hierom,</hi> and Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. ep. <hi>57.</hi> ad Darda.</note> and with them the prophane Writers conſent, <hi>Heſiod, Homer,</hi> and diuers others; amongſt whom, this is an article of their beliefe.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</l>
                     <l>As farre as heauen is aboue the earth, ſo farre is hell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>But leauing them, let vs come to Reaſon. Who will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that a <hi>Body</hi> can be but in a place? Seeing then that the Reſurrection ſhall be both of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soule,</hi> as well for the <hi>Reprobate</hi> as the <hi>Elect;</hi> and that the one ſort of them muſt enter into a<note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 25.34</note> 
                     <hi>Kingdome prepared for them from the foundations of the world,</hi> and the other<note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 25.41</note> 
                     <hi>into eternall fire which is prepared for the Deuill and his angels:</hi> muſt not both the <hi>Sheepe</hi> and the <hi>Goates</hi> be in two <hi>distinct, ſeuerall,</hi> and <hi>reall</hi> places? it cannot be gaine-ſaid: but what places be theſe? Some thinke that the Fruition, and the Want of Gods preſence and Glorie is that Kingdom, and this Fire: if it were ſo, why ſhould there be any generall Iudgement?
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12373:42"/>
for in this Life the <hi>Elect</hi> enjoy Gods gracious aſpect, which is <hi>Heauen</hi> vpon <hi>Earth,</hi> and the <hi>Reprobates</hi> are depriued of it, which is a kinde of <hi>Hell.</hi> This I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe is a <hi>heauen,</hi> and a <hi>hell</hi> for the <hi>Soule,</hi> but take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way that <hi>Place</hi> which is called <hi>Coelum Coelorum,</hi> the <hi>heau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen</hi> of <hi>heauens;</hi> and that <hi>Dungeon</hi> which is named <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebrae exteriores, vtter Darkneſſe,</hi> and how ſhall the bodies of the <hi>Righteous</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 12.3.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhine as the brightneſſe of the Firmament;</hi> and the bodies of the wicked riſe againe to <hi>perpetuall ſhame and contempt.</hi> My concluſion then is this: As God hath ordained ſome to be <hi>Veſſels</hi> of <hi>honour,</hi> ſome of <hi>diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour:</hi> ſo hath hee prepared two ſeuerall places for them, <hi>heauen</hi> and <hi>hell;</hi> the one <hi>aboue,</hi> the other <hi>beneath:</hi> betwixt which there is a<note n="e" place="margin">Luke. 16.26.</note> 
                     <hi>great gulfe, ſo that they which would goe from heauen to hell cannot, neyther can they come from hell to heauen.</hi> That there ſhall be a <hi>Corporall Aſcenſion,</hi> and <hi>Deſcenſion</hi> into two <hi>diſtinct places, Eliah</hi> and <hi>Corah,</hi> are two <hi>figures;</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">2 Reg. 2.11.</note> 
                     <hi>Eliah went vp by a whirle-wind into heauen, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in a fiery Chariot, drawne by horſes of fire:</hi> and<note n="g" place="margin">Num. 16.33.</note> 
                     <hi>Corah</hi> and his companie went <hi>aliue into hell:</hi> neyther of theſe <hi>dyed, but were changed</hi>
                     <note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.52</note>, (as the liuing ſhall be at the laſt day) <hi>in a moment, and in the twinckling of an eye:</hi> and their bodies being <hi>corruptible</hi> did put on <hi>Incorruption;</hi> ſharing betwixt them <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> eternall, both in body and Soule: and all this was done to teach vs what ſhal become of our ſoules and bodyes, at the generall reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and to informe vs that as there is a <hi>Place</hi> aboue, <hi>Heauen</hi> for the <hi>Elect;</hi> ſo there is a <hi>Place</hi> beneath, <hi>hell,</hi> for the <hi>Reprobates.</hi> Here ſhall <hi>Dogges</hi> endure <hi>paines</hi> moſt <hi>bitter</hi> and <hi>eternall;</hi> namely, <hi>a fire vnquenchable, and a worme that ſhall neuer ceaſe gnawing:</hi> of this <hi>Fire</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> ſhall be the <hi>Fewell;</hi> and to this <hi>Worme,</hi> the <hi>Soule</hi> ſhall be <hi>food.</hi> Seeing then that there ſhall be a <hi>Separation,</hi> a <hi>within</hi> and a <hi>without;</hi> and that there is a <hi>heauen</hi> and a <hi>hell; Ioy</hi> eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and <hi>Torment</hi> euerlaſting, O let vs continually medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate vpon this <hi>Lake burning</hi> with <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone,</hi> the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12373:42"/>
thought whereof, if all ſparkes of grace be not quencht in our hearts, will be like a <hi>Bridle</hi> to curbe vs, and keepe vs from ſinning.</p>
                  <p>Our Sauiour to diſſwade vs from <hi>back-ſliding,</hi> bids vs <hi>Remember Lots wife:</hi> the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> ſaith, <hi>Remember thine end, and thou ſhalt neuer doe amiſſe:</hi> and ſo ſay I, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Hell;</hi> this <hi>Memento</hi> is like a <hi>Iewell</hi> made of <hi>Iacinthes,</hi> to which the <hi>Lapidaries</hi> attribute three excellent effects; namely to preſerue a man from <hi>lightning,</hi> from the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence,</hi> and to procure <hi>ſleepe:</hi> ſuch like is the <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of hell,</hi> in that it is an <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt the <hi>poyſon of ſinne, it ſaues the ſoule from that furnace of fire,</hi> where there is nothing but weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues it from thoſe vnſpeakeable plagues and torments, which God hath prepared for the Diuell and his <hi>Angels:</hi> laſtly, becauſe hee that euer thinkes of <hi>Hell,</hi> will be afraid to commit ſinne, this <hi>Memento</hi> doth disburden the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> of all internall <hi>horrour</hi> and <hi>Anguiſh;</hi> which like <hi>Saules</hi> euill Spirit doe euer haunt the guiltie minde, and conſequently procureth ſpirituall <hi>peace and Reſt</hi> to the <hi>Soule:</hi> This <hi>Peace</hi> hee giue vs, who is the <hi>Prince of Peace, Chriſt Ieſus the righteous:</hi> to whom with the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>holy Spirit,</hi> be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, prayſe, power, glory and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion both now and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>For <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Arians.</hi> read <hi>Acrians</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ced<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nius.</hi> read <hi>Macedenious</hi>
               </item>
               <item>For <hi>Seli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> read <hi>Silen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
